<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The only vvay to rest of soule in religion here, in heaven hereafter: shewed plainly and succinctly by pure scripture, in three treatises: demonstrating, I. That the church was left by Christ, as the means to teach us his gospel. 2. Which is she that was left in that office. 3. What it is, she teacheth for gospel. By I.L. Bach of Div. Licensed by the university of Oxford, to preach throughout Engalnd, and late rector of L. in the county of S. now a Catholike.</title>
            <author>Lewgar, John, 1602-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 235 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 111 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48286</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1832A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218105</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829728</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829728</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34171</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48286)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34171)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2009:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The only vvay to rest of soule in religion here, in heaven hereafter: shewed plainly and succinctly by pure scripture, in three treatises: demonstrating, I. That the church was left by Christ, as the means to teach us his gospel. 2. Which is she that was left in that office. 3. What it is, she teacheth for gospel. By I.L. Bach of Div. Licensed by the university of Oxford, to preach throughout Engalnd, and late rector of L. in the county of S. now a Catholike.</title>
                  <author>Lewgar, John, 1602-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>216 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I.L. = John Lewgar.</note>
                  <note>Errata on pg. 216.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34171:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ONLY VVAY TO Reſt of Soule, IN RELIGION HERE, IN HEAVEN HEREAFTER: SHEWED Plainly and ſuccinctly by pure SCRIPTURE, IN THREE TREATISES: DEMONSTRATING,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That the</hi> Church <hi>was left by Chriſt, as</hi> the means <hi>to teach us his</hi> Goſpel.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Which is she that was left in that</hi> office.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>What it is, she teacheth for</hi> Goſpel.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>L. L. Bach</hi> of Div. Licenſed by the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> to preach throughout <hi>England,</hi> and late Rector of <hi>L.</hi> in the County of S. now a <hi>Catholike.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Tim. 3.15.</hi>
               </bibl> The Church is the pillar and ground of the truth.</q>
            <p>Printed for the Author, 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:34171:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34171:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:34171:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:34171:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ADVERTISEMENTS</hi> Of the Author to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Suppoſe you to be a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſober-minded <hi>Proteſtant;</hi> having a love to the truth; not much further learned than the English Bible; regarding it as Gods word, and no authority but its in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of religion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You are not to think we uſe this way, of proving our grounds by Scripture, either as neceſſary, or as wanting other (for we are able to prove them, independently of it, and praecedently to it, to any rational man, by the ſame means as Moſes (<hi>Exod.</hi> 4.1.) and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prophets (1 <hi>Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 17.24.) did theirs, afore any word of the Old,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34171:4"/>
and Chriſt (<hi>Iohn</hi> 5.35.) and his Apoſtles (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12.) theirs, afore any word of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament was written; to wit, <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, ſuch as no other doth, (Ioh.</hi> 15.24.) <hi>joyn'd with eminent Sanctity;</hi> as shal be shewn in next Treatiſe:) but onely becauſe <hi>in it you think to have eternall life (Ioh.</hi> 5.39.)</p>
            <p n="3">3. Out of my great deſire of bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, I have often omitted to quote the texts at large. And therefore I could wish you would take the paines to read them in your Bible; for there is not one of them put for shew onely (as is too much uſed on your ſide); but is pertinent to confirm or illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate what it is quoted for.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Out of the ſame deſire, I have many times omitted divers
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34171:4"/>
proofes on our ſide, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſome on yours. If therefore you miſſe any, doe not think it was either of craft, or for any dread of it (for I hope by that time you have read it over, you will not ſay I have pleaded your cauſe partially): but either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it eſcaped me, or was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned by me, or I thought the anſwer given to ſome other, would ſerve it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Above all things, I am to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech your charity, afore you cenſure our opinion, or drift of the book, as tending to derogate from the honour, office, or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of H. Scripture, you will read over the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> §. in the Praeface. And if any expreſſion uſed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34171:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in the book ſeem to have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſenſe varying from what is there ſet down, not to underſtand it in any ſuch ſenſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:34171:5"/>
            <head>THE PRAEFACE To the firſt Treatiſe: Stating the quaeſtion, explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the tearmes, &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>§ 1.</hi> Grounds agreed upon, leading to the Quaeſtion.</head>
               <p>1 <hi>Ground.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>WIthout faith, it is not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to pleaſe God (<hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6.); and without holines no man shall ſee him (<hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14.)</p>
               <p>2. <hi>Ground.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. What <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>holineſſe</hi> it is as he requires, and will accept from his creature, to this <hi>pleaſing</hi> and <hi>ſeeing</hi> of him, <hi>cannot enter into the heart of man</hi> (yea, or Angel) by any light poſſible in <hi>nature;</hi> but it is neceſſary he reveale it to us by his holy Spirt <hi>(1</hi> Cor. <hi>2.9).</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:34171:6"/>3. <hi>Ground.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This revelation he makes not <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately</hi> to every one; but to ſome one (perſon, or company) at firſt; and ſo makes uſe of that one, <hi>(di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely authoriſed, and aſſiſted by him to that end)</hi> as his inſtrument to <hi>teach</hi> it to others in an ordinary way, <hi>by word of mouth,</hi> or <hi>wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> (becauſe this way is <hi>ſufficient,</hi> the other <hi>miraculous;</hi> which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he uſeth not without ſome neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.) See examples hereof, if you pleaſe (Gen. <hi>18.19.</hi> Exod. <hi>18.16.</hi> S. Mat. <hi>28.20.</hi> Act. <hi>9.6.</hi> &amp; <hi>10.6.</hi>)</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">What is meant by <hi>[teaching].</hi>
                  </note>By <hi>[teaching]</hi> I meane [inſtructing in religion, in ſuch manner as the Scholar may, and untill he doe (without it be his own fault) underſtand it aright, and perfectly, ſo far as is needfull to his Soules health]. And when it is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34171:6"/>
of, as the act of a reaſonable creature; I mean by it [inſtructing (as afore) by word of mouth, in way of publike office.] And it includes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers acts, as principal and moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. The firſt is, to give the <hi>firſt</hi> inſtruction, called by a proper name, <hi>Catechiſing.</hi> The other, which is to give the <hi>perfecting</hi> inſtruction, hath two acts; <hi>1.</hi> In quality of a <hi>Judge,</hi> to decide all emerging <hi>controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies. 2.</hi> In quality of a <hi>Guide,</hi> or <hi>Councellor,</hi> to direct in, and reſolve all <hi>caſes of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> And all the ſame I underſtand by <hi>[preaching.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When I ſay <hi>[by word of mouth, or writing]</hi> I mean, either of that <hi>firſt,</hi> or of others, from, or under him, in the ſame manner <hi>divinely authorized and aſſiſted;</hi> for elſe no man may, much leſſe can be obliged to believe it,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34171:7"/>
by <hi>divine</hi> faith, no more then they could the teaching of the <hi>firſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">What is meant by <hi>[divinely au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed.]</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>[Divinely authoriſed]</hi> includes three properties, <hi>1. free from all error,</hi> in its teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>2. obliging</hi> all creatures un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der penalty of aeternal torments, to believe and obey it. <hi>3. ſecuring</hi> all that doe, of an aeternall recompence.</p>
               <p>4. <hi>Ground.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In this</hi> immediate <hi>way;</hi> in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry manners, and at ſundry times, he ſpake of old to the Fathers, by the Prophets (Adam, Abraham, Moſes, <hi>&amp;c.) (Heb.</hi> 1.1.). <hi>Some of whom,</hi> by him moved (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20.) <hi>committed their revelations unto</hi> writing, <hi>now called the [Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment].</hi>
               </p>
               <p>5 <hi>Ground.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The rule delivered by theſe his <hi>ſervants</hi> (Heb. <hi>3.5.</hi>) being (when at beſt) but <hi>imperfect</hi> (Heb. <hi>7.19.</hi>) and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34171:7"/>
(for the greateſt part of it) but <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary</hi> (Gal. <hi>3.19.</hi>) at length, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in the viſible perſon of Ieſus Chriſt, vouchſafing to become a Teacher of it; he (as became him <hi>the Lord</hi>) taught it perfectly, and as it was to endure to worlds end. Whence he is ſtyled [<hi>our one Maſter</hi> (Mat. 23.8.); <hi>the author and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher of our faith</hi> Heb. <hi>12.2.</hi>]</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">What is meant by <hi>[Religion]</hi> and <hi>[the Goſpel]</hi>
                  </note>And this forme, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, law, or rule of faith and holineſſe, thus by God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty revealed, is called by a proper name <hi>[Religion:]</hi> and as by Ieſus Chriſt revealed, or promulgated, is called [<hi>the Chriſtian Religion;</hi> or (in Scripture-phraſe) <hi>the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel</hi>] (Mar. <hi>16.15.</hi>)</p>
               <p>6 <hi>Ground.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tbis <hi>Goſpell,</hi> he taught to his Apoſtles: and ſo left them as the <hi>firſt,</hi> and <hi>temporary</hi> meanes, to teach it to others.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:34171:8"/>Conſequently, at their death, all teaching of it by or from him <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate,</hi> ceaſed (at leaſt, regularly ſpeaking). Whence, (as one reaſon, at leaſt) thoſe dayes of his and their teaching in the flesh, are called [<hi>the laſt dayes,</hi> (Eſa. <hi>2.2.</hi> Heb. <hi>1.1.) the fulneſſe, of time,</hi> (Gal. <hi>4.4.) and the ends of the world.</hi>] (<hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>10.11.</hi>) And ſo, he that will know any thing touching it, muſt goe to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel by them taught and left, as [<hi>the fountaine of all both ſaveing truth and diſcipline of manners</hi> (ſo our late H. Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> calls it) (Seſſ. <hi>4.</hi>) to all ſucceeding generations].</p>
               <p>7 <hi>Ground.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They (in their</hi> perſons) <hi>being to die ſoon after him, he left (or, at leaſt, deſigned they should leave) ſomething to remaine as the</hi> (ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, or perpetual) <hi>means to teach it to others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:34171:8"/>
                  <note place="margin">What is meant by <hi>[the means.]</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Where, by</hi> [the means of teaching it] <hi>I mean not any ſort of meanes;</hi> humanely authorized <hi>onely, or</hi> fallible, <hi>in</hi> its teaching, <hi>or</hi> inſtrumentall <hi>only to ſome other creature, or</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable <hi>only, or neceſſary in</hi> ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects <hi>onely, or</hi> ſufficient <hi>to teach ſome</hi> part <hi>of it onely, or to</hi> ſome <hi>creatures onely: but</hi> [the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, principall, neceſſary, and ſufficient, to teach every creature, every particular of it, and divine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly authorized and aſſiſted to that end:] <hi>and ſo deſerving to be ſtiled in abſolute and ſimple ſenſe</hi> [the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of the Lord (or, interpreter of his will to humane creatures); the guide of mankind in the way to heaven; the light of the world; the Pillar, or ground of the truth; the Judge of the Chriſtian Law; the Chaire of Chriſt; the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34171:9"/>
Schoole of the Goſpell; the ſteward, depoſitary, or diſpenſer of the myſteries of faith; the ſtore-houſe or treaſury of divine knowledge, wiſedome, or truth; the power <hi>(or powerfull inſtrument)</hi> of God unto ſalvation of all that believe, or uſe it]: <hi>and its voice, doctrine, or teaching</hi> [the word, law, oracles, doctrine, or Goſpell, of God, Chriſt, truth, grace, life, or ſalvation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the faith; the truth; the ſeed <hi>(of grace);</hi> the faithful word; the ſword of the ſpirit; the forme of ſound words, or doctrine; the depoſitum, or trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, of heavenly truth, left by Chriſt, or his Apoſtles; the whole revealed will, or counſell of God; the guide of faith; the rule of religion <hi>&amp;c.] Or, of which it is, or may be ſaid,</hi> [it shall teach you religion; if there ariſe a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34171:9"/>
too hard for thee, thou shalt goe to it to enquire; ask, or ſeek the Law of God, at it, or its mouth; in controverſie it shall ſtand in judgement; it shall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve knowledge; it shall shew thee what thou oughteſt to doe; follow it; make it your rule, or guide; prove all things by it; by it we know the ſpirit of truth, and ſpirit of error; it is able to make you wiſe to ſalvation, or, to ſave your ſoules, or to shew you the way to eternal life; he that believes, or followes it, shall be ſaved]: <hi>or, unto which, God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty ever ſaid</hi> [Teach people; <hi>or,</hi> teach the Goſpell.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To whatſoever creature, theſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes, offices, properties, phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſpeeches, or any one of them, or any other to the ſame ſenſe, is rightfully given, or appertaines,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34171:10"/>
that's</hi> [the meanes] <hi>I ſpeak of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>8. <hi>Ground.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This meanes (what ever it be), is ſomewhere or other in H. Scripture, ſet forth, and named to us, in moſt plain, and expreſſe manner, as being the fundamental of all fundamentals (as to <hi>us</hi>) within the Chriſtian religion; without which firſt known and certaine, it is in vain for any man to talk of religion, or to preſume to judge of what is true or falſe, pious or ſuperſtitious, neceſſary or not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, in any matter pertaining to it: and which when it is known and certaine, no more remaines for any man to doe (that deſires to know what he is to believe, doe, or avoid to obteining eternall ſalvation), but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to find it out, and hear, believe, and practice, what it teaches, comands, or forbids, as Goſpell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:34171:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>§. 2.</hi> The Queſtion to he handled, propoſed.</head>
               <p>Hither to you and we agree in our principles, as <hi>rational</hi> men, and <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But then the Queſtion is, <hi>What is that means?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And it lies betwixt two, <hi>The Church,</hi> and H. <hi>Scripture.</hi> For, either he left them in quality of a <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,</hi> or <hi>Community</hi> (ſuch as our Lawyers call, <hi>a body corporate</hi>) to have a permanency by ſucceſſion; and then <hi>the Church</hi> will be it; or they were to leave ſome writing, to teach in their ſtead, or office, at their death; and then <hi>the Scripture</hi> will be it: or he left them in quality of a Society, as to ſome <hi>part</hi> of the office, and they were to leave the Scripture in the other <hi>part;</hi> and then both will be it.</p>
               <p>By <hi>[the Church]</hi> then throughout
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34171:11"/>
this treatiſe,<note place="margin">What is meant by the <hi>[Church].</hi>
                  </note> I meane nothing els, but <hi>[a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, or ſome company of men].</hi> For, this is deſcription ſufficient for the intent of this Treatiſe, which is onely to diſtinguish her from the <hi>Scripture,</hi> and the <hi>perſons</hi> of the Apoſtles. Nor do I mean by her, the whole ſociety ſo called; nor any part of her, as to any effect of juſtifying <hi>grace</hi> or <hi>ſalvation;</hi> but (properly, and immediately) that part by which she <hi>teacheth;</hi> as I ſpeak, by my <hi>mouth;</hi> and a <hi>Univerſity</hi> teaches by her <hi>Profeſſors.</hi> In which ſenſe, our B. Saviour uſed the name, when he ſaid <hi>[Tell the Church]</hi> (Mat. <hi>18.17.</hi>) and S. Paul <hi>[the Church is the pillar of truth].</hi> (<hi>1</hi> Tim. <hi>3.15.</hi>)</p>
               <p>And ſo, in fine, the quaeſtion is,
<q>[Whether the Church, or the Scripture, or both, be <hi>the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34171:11"/>
meanes</hi> left by Chriſt (or his order), for teaching his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell]?</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>§. 3.</hi> The importance of it.</head>
               <p>And it is (as appeares ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by what is ſaid already) the moſt tranſcendently-fundamental one poſſible to be within the Chriſtian religion: ſeeing by <hi>this meanes,</hi> it is to be <hi>taught;</hi> and all queſtions in it to be <hi>reſolved.</hi> And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, it is of moſt tranſcendent importance, what wee hold in it; as you will quickly ſee, if you but reflect on the conſequences of it. For,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> If H. Scripture be it; <hi>1.</hi> All reading of other books; conſulting Miniſters, or Divines; going to Church to hear their Catechiſing, or Sermons; conferring, or arguing one with another; or any other acts,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34171:12"/>
or meanes whatſoever, to this end, to inſtruct, or direct our ſelves in religion, will be vain and ſuperfluous, yea, improper: but every one is to goe to the Bible, and it alone, and by it ſelf alone. For (ſuppoſing it left in this office) there will be no denying, but it is as plain and intelligible by it ſelf alone, to any child, or other no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, having the uſe of reaſon, as to the learnedſt Divine in the world. <hi>2.</hi> No creature uſing it for his guide, can offend God by any hereſie, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, or prophaneſſe; unleſſe he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve or practice contrary to what it teacheth him, according to his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of it. <hi>3.</hi> It will be out of the power of the Church, to hinder or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine any creature from reading, and uſing it, at his pleaſure, in any language.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:34171:12"/>
                  <hi>2.</hi> On the other ſide, if the Church be it; <hi>1.</hi> all reading of Scripture, by the people, unto this end, will be vain and ſuperfluous, yea, impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; but every one is to ſeek the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel at her mouth, and hers onely. <hi>2.</hi> It will be in the power of the Church to permit or reſtrain the uſe of the Bible unto the people; more or leſſe, thereafter, as she in her prudence (all things conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and not ſome only,) and in her charity to their ſouls, shall judge it moſt expedient for them to their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. <hi>3.</hi> No man, though baptized in Chriſts faith, though believing never ſo humbly and firmly, and practiſing never ſo fervently all that he finds in Scripture, may hope to ſee the face of God, if he pertina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly refuſe to believe, do, approve, or avoid any one leaſt thing taught
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34171:13"/>
or commanded by the Church, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſalvation to be believed done, approved, or avoided, (although in Scripture not mentioned); and die in that ſtate of ſoule.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> If <hi>both</hi> be it; the part, or share of each in the office, is to be ſet out, and certainly known by every creature, that they may have recourſe to each for that which pertaines to its office: to the Scripture, for its; to the Church, for its.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>§. 4.</hi> The Proteſtants Tenet in it.</head>
               <p>In the anſwer to this Queſtion, you and we (as near as ſome imagine the two religions to be one to the other) differ extreamly. For albeit you grant, that Chriſt left a Church to continue for ever in ſome office of teaching religion, and that office of hers <hi>proper,</hi> and in ſome reſpects
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34171:13"/>
                  <hi>ſufficient,</hi> and <hi>neceſſary:</hi> yet you will not allow it to be, either <hi>ſimply</hi> neceſſary, or ſufficient, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then a meer <hi>miniſtery</hi> to the Scripture; or ſo much as that, <hi>with divine authority.</hi> Conſequently, your Tenet is,
<q>[Chriſt left, or appointed, the Scripture, for the meanes to teach us his Goſpell.]</q>
               </p>
               <p>This is the prime and maine prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of your religion, (in <hi>proper,</hi> or as it is diſtinguished againſt ours, by the name of <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed):</hi> upon the truth therefore and certainty whereof, depends in fine the whole truth and certainty of your religion (and conſequently, of your hope of ſalvation, in, or by it), as the firmneſſe of any whole building does, upon the firmneſſe of its foundation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:34171:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>§ 5. What,</hi> Catholicks acknowledge to H. Scripture.</head>
               <p>We are as forward as any of you can be, to give unto H. Scripture, what is its. Namely,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That ſome of the Apoſtles wrote the <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> which, and the <hi>Old,</hi> make up that holy book called <hi>[the Scripture, or Bible.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> That it is (<hi>all,</hi> and every word of it) <hi>given by inſpiration of God,</hi> and therefore the very word of God, of truth moſt infalible, of authority moſt ſupreme, as to all creatures (even the Church her ſelfe; yea, in <hi>quality</hi> and <hi>degree</hi> of the authority, ſuperiour to that of the Church;); and the only divine <hi>writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> rule, now being, or ever to be.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> That they left it unto, or with the <hi>Church,</hi> as a ſacred <hi>depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:34171:14"/>
in the nature following. <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> A <hi>rule,</hi> which she is bound to have an eye unto, in all her doctrines, and lawes; and not only that they be not <hi>repugnant</hi> to it, in more or leſſe either by <hi>adding to,</hi> or <hi>taking from,</hi> either the words, ſenſe, or law of it, any one leaſt tittle (for, ſuppoſing that poſſible, and her, <hi>a Church all of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles or heavenly Angels,</hi> she were inſtantly, to be deteſted by all, <hi>as a Synagogue of Satan;</hi> and all ſuch her doctrines and lawes to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred as <hi>will-worship,</hi> and <hi>tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men</hi>), but that they be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant</hi> to it, as neer as she may judge of the ſenſe or intent of the H. Ghoſt (as we find the Apoſtles had ſuch an eye to it in theirs. <hi>Acts 1.20. &amp; 15.15.</hi>) And in acknowledgement hereof, in all her Generall Councels, she placeth it in the moſt ſumptuous throne; at the uppermoſt end of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34171:15"/>
aſſembly (above Pope, and all), as that which is to have the <hi>chiefeſt</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, and <hi>ſwaying</hi> vote, in all her debates, and reſolutions.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> A <hi>meanes,</hi> excellent <hi>proper,</hi> yea the incomparably <hi>principall</hi> (in the ſort, and order of <hi>inanimate</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, as it is) unto the ends for which it was ordained. Namely, <hi>1.</hi> To corroborate by its concurring teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, the authority, and doctrine of the Church; and our faith to it. <hi>2.</hi> To preſerve, in way of a <hi>record,</hi> a world of moſt admirable truths, rules, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, admonitions, exhortations, motives, hiſtories, genealogies, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, formes of prayer, &amp;c. per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teining to faith, and holines. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect whereof, it is a meanes <hi>profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> (ſuperlatively, beyond all that can be ſaid of it by tongues of men or Angels) to <hi>furnish the man of God</hi> (or Divine), <hi>perfectly, for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:34171:15"/>
(yea, of faith), <hi>for reproof</hi> (of the adverſaries), <hi>for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſneſſe, and for every other good work</hi> (proper, or perteining to his function). <hi>(2. Tim. 3.16.)</hi> And therefore not only doe our Divines, <hi>give diligent attendance to the reading</hi> and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of it, and make uſe of it, (incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably for above any other meanes) to all theſe ends; yea, and to the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting, and guiding themſelves, for and in the knowledge of truth, and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving caſes of conſcience; and our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, in and for the making lawes, or determining cauſes Eccleſiaſticall; but the Church her ſelf, in all General Councells, makes her firſt, and chief repaire to it, for light and direction; nay, all her debate, and ſearch into former Councells, Fathers, School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, tradition, practice, and ſenſe of the Church, is to no other end, (gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34171:16"/>
ſpeaking), then the better to find out, and determine, its true ſenſe, or intent.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> A <hi>meanes,</hi> not only as in the hand of <hi>the man of God,</hi> but as in the hand of every <hi>Chriſtian</hi> (rightly principled, firme in faith, <hi>(2. Pet. 3.16.)</hi> and reading it in obedience to them that are over him in the Lord, <hi>(Heb. 13.7.)</hi> with the humble ſpirit of the Eunuch, <hi>(Acts 8.31.)</hi> unto the ends for which it was ordeined (if or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined) as to him; to wit, to confirm, advance, and perfect himſelf in faith, <hi>(Joh. 20.31.)</hi> ſaving wiſedome, <hi>(2. Tim. 3.15.)</hi> hope, <hi>(Rom. 15.4.)</hi> charity, <hi>(1. Th. 4.9.)</hi> and other Chriſtian vertues), ſingularly proper unto thoſe ends: as having from its divine author, ſpeciall force and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, beyond all poſſible enditings of humane brain, <hi>to inlighten the eyes,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34171:16"/>
and convert the heart of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> And therefore (ſpeaking of it, <hi>per ſe,</hi> or as in the hands of ſuch a one), <hi>bleſſed is he that reades and meditates in it, day and night, (Pſ. 1.1.) and makes it a lanthorne to his feet, and a light unto his paths.</hi> (Pſ. <hi>119.105.</hi>)</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4.</hi> A <hi>meanes</hi> (ſince its writing) <hi>neceſſary</hi> unto the Church, as by which God will guide her into the truths there recorded; without it (when it may be had), not.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5.</hi> A <hi>meanes</hi> perfectly <hi>ſufficient</hi> unto the ends for which it was ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; which is all the perfection of an inſtrument.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6.</hi> A <hi>record,</hi> conteining <hi>all</hi> that man is to believe, doe, or avoid, to the obteining eternall ſalvation; and <hi>expreſly,</hi> all the <hi>principall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In regard of which many and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable properties and uſes of it, it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34171:17"/>
is the ſame (in a manner) to us, as the pillar of cloud by day, and fire by night was to the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> guiding <hi>Moſes</hi> in the way to <hi>Canaan,</hi> and by him, them. In a word, it deſerves to be called, by way of <hi>excellency [the Word Law, doctrine, oracles, or Goſpell of God, Chriſt, ſalvation, &amp;c. the guide of faith; the rule of religion, the light of the world, &amp;c.].</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>§. 6. The Catholick tenett.</head>
               <p>But then we deny it to be, either a <hi>proper, principall, neceſſary,</hi> or <hi>ſufficient</hi> meanes, to teach religion. And ſo, to give unto the Church alſo what is hers; our tenett is, that
<q>[The Church was left by Chriſt, for the meanes of teaching his Goſpell.]</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Concluſion of the praeface.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>YOu ſee the true ſtate of the quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, the tenetts of each ſide,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34171:17"/>
and the importance of what you hold in it. That which remaines for this Praeface, is to admonish you, that your principle is notoriouſly falſe, repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to holy writt, and mother of all the ſects in theſe parts of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and therefore to beſeech you (dear Chriſtian brother) as you deſire to pleaſe God heere, and ſee his bleſſed face hereafter, to <hi>ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> (with the noble <hi>Bereans,</hi>) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe things be ſo or no, as your <hi>Miniſters</hi> have taught you out of it, touching the Scriptures being left for your rule and guide.</p>
               <p>To help you in it (if God shall put it in your heart), that you may not be gull'd, as now you are, with the meer ſound or ſuperficies of words, but dive to the depth of the ſenſe of it (for, that is properly to <hi>ſearch</hi> it) is all the buſineſſe of this enſuing treatiſe. Wherein I shall firſt <hi>prove</hi> our tenet;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:34171:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
then, <hi>defend</hi> it againſt your obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; in the third place, <hi>examine</hi> what may be ſaid for yours; and in the laſt, <hi>refell</hi> it. And when you have thus the whole matter laid afore you; you will be able to <hi>judge righteous judgement;</hi> which now you give, upon hearing one tale told; or, at leaſt, the other, but by halves, and for the greateſt part, falſely.</p>
               <p>Be the event of it what it will, it cannot but be worth ſo ſmall a paines; either by confirming you in follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (for your guide, and rule) that which you <hi>doe;</hi> or, by its own mouth, shewing you to that which you <hi>should.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I shall be bold to adde thus much for a further encouragement: that if you can finde any one text for your Tenet, and not a multitude moſt plainly and expreſſely againſt it; if any one againſt ours, and not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:34171:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
a multitude moſt plainly and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely againſt it; if any one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ours, and not a multitude moſt plainly and expreſſely for it; I will adviſe you to keep your own ſtill, and take all your perill upon my head: hoping, if you doe not, you will think it reaſon to forſake it, and embrace ours. And I ſuppoſe you cannot ſay, but as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did to <hi>Elijah,</hi> in ſomewhat a like propoſall <hi>[Thou haſt well ſpoken] 1</hi> Kin: <hi>18.24.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:34171:19"/>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:34171:19"/>
            <head>THE Firſt Treatiſe: SHEWING, That Chriſt left the Church for the meanes to teach us his GOSPELL, THE FIRST PART Proving it.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Proving it, from</hi> the Law.</head>
               <p>WEe ſay <hi>[Chriſt left the Church for the meanes to teach us his Goſpel].</hi> And are able to prove it; from <hi>the Lavv, the Prophets, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpels, the Acts, and the Epiſtles.</hi> To begin with <hi>the Lavv.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:34171:20"/>1. It is certain, <hi>all things happened to the old people in figure</hi> of ſomething, but more excellent, to correſpond to it in the nevv (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11.). So, their meanes of teaching, a figure of ours; and <hi>figures</hi> require <hi>fulfilling,</hi> as vvell as <hi>Prophecies.</hi> (S. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.14. &amp; 19.36).</p>
               <p n="2">2. Preſumption of reaſon is, that vvhat ſort of meanes the divine vviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſaw moſt proper, and therefore made choice of, and uſed as the <hi>meanes of teaching Religion,</hi> from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the vvorld, untill Chriſts time; the ſame he vvould aftervvard, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vvorlds end (untill he that denies it, shevv reaſon to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary).</p>
               <p>Novv I am ſure you vvill grant me, that <hi>afore</hi> the vvriting of the Lavv, <hi>ſome company of men,</hi> vvas <hi>the meanes</hi> to that end. And if <hi>afore, after</hi> it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</p>
               <p n="1">1. You vvill not find that that Lavv made any alteration in the office more then this: 1. That it <hi>determined</hi> it to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:34171:20"/>
the family of <hi>Aaron,</hi> (vvhereas till then it had been one of the rights of <hi>Primo geniture) Gen.</hi> 25.31). 2. and <hi>added;</hi> 1. To the <hi>matter</hi> to be taught. 2. To the <hi>Teachers,</hi> the help of a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That Lavv expreſly ſettles it in <hi>Aaron,</hi> and his poſterity. <hi>[That ye may teach my Statutes, &amp;c.</hi> (Lev. 10.11.) <hi>Thou shalt go to the Prieſts to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, and they shall shevv thee</hi> (Deu. 17.8.) <hi>They shall teach thy Lavv,</hi> &amp;c. Deu. 33.10.]</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hereunto accord the ſayings of the Prophets (<hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.23. <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.5.) and the <hi>practice</hi> of that Nation, noted aftervvard upon divers occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. [<hi>The Prieſts taught the people.</hi> (2 Chr. 17.9.) <hi>They cauſed the people to underſtand the Lavv</hi> (Neh. 8.8.) See more, if you pleaſe, to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.9. <hi>Agg.</hi> 2.11.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Both <hi>Law</hi> and practice, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued the ſame, as vvell <hi>after</hi> the old Canon vvas finished, as afore. See
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:34171:21"/>
S. <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.4. &amp; 19.26. S. <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.17. &amp; 12.14. S. <hi>Lu.</hi> 4.20. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.22. &amp; 22.3.</p>
               <p>And appeares particularly by our B. Saviours ovvn, both <hi>practice</hi> (vvhen he <hi>vvent into the Temple, to hear the Doctors, and ask them queſtions</hi> (S. Lu. 2.46.) <hi>and rule</hi> given by him to the people [<hi>They ſit in</hi> Moſes <hi>Chaire, all things therefore, &amp;c. S. Mat.</hi> 23.2.] vvherein I pray note vvell:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That <hi>Moſes</hi> Lavv had ſetled in the Prieſts and others by them autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized, a <hi>Chair</hi> for teaching Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, untill Chriſt should erect his in place of it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the authority of that Chair vvas <hi>divine,</hi> and conſequently <hi>equall</hi> (in the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the authority) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that of <hi>Moſes</hi> Lavv, it being <hi>his Chair,</hi> as much as the other <hi>his Lavv.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. That the people therefore vvere bound to obey its reaching, abſolutely and univerſally <hi>[all things vvhatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. And not for its conſonancy vvith
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:34171:21"/>
the Scripture, but ſufficiently, <hi>for the meer authority of the Chair</hi> [All things <hi>therefore.</hi>]</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Proving it from the Prophets.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe Lavv</hi> hath teſtified vvell to our Tenent. But <hi>vve have a more ſure vvord of Prophecy.</hi> To in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in a fevv of the plaineſt.</p>
               <p>Firſt proof. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Micah</hi> 4.1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eſay and Micah</hi> thus. [<hi>In the laſt daies shall the Mountain of the Lords houſe be eſtablished, in the top of the Mountains, and all Nations shall flovv unto it, ſaying, Come ye, and let us go up to the mountain of the Lord, to the houſe of the God of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and he vvill teach us of his vvayes, &amp;c. for out of</hi> Zyon <hi>shall go forth the Lavv, and the vvord of the Lord from Ieruſalem.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Where 1. by <hi>[the laſt daies,]</hi> it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be doubted, but he meant <hi>the daies of the Goſpel (Heb.</hi> 1.1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11.)</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:34171:22"/>2. Nor, but that by <hi>[the Lords houſe]</hi> he meant <hi>[the Church]</hi> ſo called (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.) vvhich he calls [<hi>the Mountaine of Gods houſe,</hi> and namely, <hi>Mount Zion;</hi>] becauſe she vvas to be <hi>born</hi> (or compleatly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from her mothet, <hi>the Synagogue</hi>) on that Mount (<hi>Pſa.</hi> 87.1, 5.) as she vvas on the day of <hi>Pentecoſt, Act.</hi> 2.1. vvhen the H. Ghoſt (as her ultimate ſoul) vvas infuſed into her: it being certain by conſent of all Writers Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, that upon that <hi>hill</hi> vvas ſcituate the houſe in vvhich the Apoſtles, the B. Virgin, and other <hi>firſt-born in Chriſt (Heb.</hi> 12.22.) after his Aſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on aſſembled to holy duties; In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard vvhereof, as the <hi>Synagogue (Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Ievves)</hi> by reaſon she began (as to her laſt and compleat ſtate) at the publishing of the Law on that <hi>Mount,</hi> was called <hi>[Mount Sinai:]</hi> So she <hi>(Mother of us Chriſtians)</hi> vvas called (<hi>Mount Zion, Gal.</hi> 4.26.) And this muſt of neceſſity be granted, to the truth of this, and divers other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:34171:22"/>
which all agree in this, that the Church, and publique preaching of the Goſpel by her, was to begin on that Mount (<hi>Pſa.</hi> 2.6. &amp; 48. <hi>per totum.</hi> &amp; 110.3. &amp;c.)</p>
               <p>So, this for certain is one of thoſe Prophecies of which our Saviour ſaid <hi>[Thus it is written, and thus it behoves that the Goſpel be preached in all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, beginning at Ieruſalem.)</hi> Lu. 24.43.</p>
               <p>The ſenſe of the place thus open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it yeelds four points, moſt plainly and fully to my purpoſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That <hi>the Church</hi> was to be the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary meanes for teaching mankind the Goſpell. [<hi>They shall ſay, Come let us go up to the houſe of God; and he</hi> (in, or by that houſe) <hi>will teach us his wayes, &amp;c.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That <hi>her</hi> teaching was to be <hi>Gods teaching; he,</hi> to be the <hi>principall</hi> teacher (though inviſible); <hi>she,</hi> but his <hi>mouth [He, shall teach us</hi>]. According to what is elſwhere aſſured to all her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or ſcholars [<hi>they shall be al taught of God.</hi> Eſa. 54.13].</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:34171:23"/>3. That the word by her taught, is heere called, 1. <hi>Gods word, and Law</hi> (therefore it of divine authority, and she a teacher divinely authoriſed). 2. In ſimple ſenſe <hi>[the Law, and the word of the Lord].</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. That she is to continue in all the ſame office and authority of teaching, wherein she began at Mount Zyon, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till she have <hi>taught the Goſpel to all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> which will not be till neare the worlds end. (Mat. 24.14).</p>
               <p>Second proof. Eſay <hi>59.20.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, Eſay <hi>[The Redeemer shal come to Zion. And this is my covenant with them</hi> (of Zion) ſaith <hi>the Lord, My Spirit which is upon thee, and my words which I have put in thy mouth, shall not depart out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeed, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeeds ſeed (ſaith the Lord) from henceforth, and for ever.</hi>] Not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be underſtood of any (perſon, or company) but the <hi>Church.</hi> Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, aſſuring unto Gods Elect, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, that he will teach
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:34171:23"/>
them unto the worlds end, all the ſame word of his, by the mouth of the ſame Church, with all the ſame divine au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and aſſiſtance, as he did the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Saints at Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> on Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonday, <hi>when he firſt put his Spirit upon her, and his words into her mouth,</hi> Act. 2.5.</p>
               <p>Third Proofe. Ezek. <hi>44.23.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the ſame effect, <hi>Ezekiel, [Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doc, and his ſons, shall teach my people, &amp;c. in controverſie they shall ſtand in judgement, &amp;c.]</hi> This <hi>Sadoc</hi> was he upon whom the High-Prieſthood was transferred from <hi>Eleazars</hi> line (1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 2.27.) And ſo here the <hi>typical</hi> name of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> upon whom it was transferred from <hi>Aarons</hi> line. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, this place aſſures unto Gods people under the Goſpel, a race of <hi>faithful</hi> Paſtors (therefore teaching no errors) in the office of teaching Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, unto the worlds end, according to that [<hi>I will raiſe me up a faithfull Prieſt, and will build him a ſure houſe, and he shall walk afore my Chriſt for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.35.]</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:34171:24"/>Fourth Proofe. Mal. <hi>2.4.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moſt plainly, <hi>Malachy [Ye shall know</hi> (by the wonderfull performance of it) <hi>that I have ſent this Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto you, that my Covenant</hi> (of teaching) <hi>might be with</hi> Levi (the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and their Succeſſors.) <hi>The Law of truth was in his mouth, the Prieſts lips should</hi> (it is their office) <hi>preſerve knowledge, and they shall ſeek the Law at his mouth, for he is the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel</hi> (or as yours, prophanely, <hi>the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger) of the Lord of Hoaſts.</hi>]</p>
               <p>See more, if you pleaſe, to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Pſa,</hi> 19.1. unto <hi>v.</hi> 7. (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>Rom,</hi> 10.18. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.14.) and <hi>Pſalm</hi> 68.11, 16, 18. (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11.) <hi>Eſa.</hi> 30.20. and 60.11. and 62.6. <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.14. and 33.15. to the end, and 50.5. <hi>Ezek,</hi> 37.21. <hi>all,</hi> aſſuring unto the Church, a race of Teachers divinely authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, unto worlds end.</p>
               <p>Nor can you ſay theſe places meant the Church, as preaching <hi>Scripture,</hi> or her doctrine, as conſonant to it,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:34171:24"/>
when you cannot shew that any of the Prophets foreſaw that any one tittle of the Goſpel was ever to be written.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP III.</hi> Proving it from the Goſpels.</head>
               <p>ACcording to the exigence of theſe types and Prophecies, as our Saviour himſelf ſaith, (S. <hi>Lu.</hi> 24.44.) he inſtituted the office of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel, in his Church, as is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt.</p>
               <p>Firſt Proofe. S. Mat. <hi>5.14.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, from that attribute given by him to his Apoſtles, as <hi>Paſtors,</hi> and conſequently to his Paſtors for the time being for ever <hi>[Ye are the light of the world.]</hi> as much as to ſay [<hi>the Sun,</hi> or fountain of ſpiritual light unto mankind] which therefore if it should once <hi>loſe its light</hi> (by teaching any er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in faith) the whole world muſt neceſſarily remain in darkneſſe (and oh how great darkneſſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.23.) ever after. For, wherewith should the Sun be enlightened?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:34171:25"/>
                  <hi>Second Proofe. S. Mat.</hi> 7.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24, 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 26.13. <hi>S. Lu.</hi> 8.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.28, <hi>S. Ioh.</hi> 8.47. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.47.</p>
               <p>Secondly, from thoſe titles ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily given by him to his <hi>word,</hi> as <hi>preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> calling it, in ſimple ſenſe, <hi>[the word, his word, his voice, the word of God, the Goſpel, the ſeed]</hi> of all grace in the ſoul, whereof <hi>faith</hi> the firſt: and conſtantly naming <hi>preaching,</hi> as the ordinary means on his part, of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; and <hi>hearing,</hi> on the peoples part, of coming to the knowledge of it.</p>
               <p>Nor can you ſay, by theſe titles, he meant <hi>[the Scripture preached;]</hi> or the Churches doctrine, <hi>as conſonant to Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture;</hi> when you cannot find, he ever intended, or (as man) foreſaw that any one tittle of his Goſpel should ever be written.</p>
               <p>Third Proofe. S. Mat. <hi>18.17.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, from that rule of his, to all his, for ever <hi>[Tell the Church, &amp;c.]</hi> plainly implying, he meant to leave
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:34171:25"/>
her, as the ordinary Supreame <hi>Iudge,</hi> in all cauſes pertaining to his Court, and a Judge <hi>divinely authorized;</hi> for elſe none could be bound <hi>abſolutely</hi> to hear her, under pain of eternal damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is here implicitely threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened to ſuch as neglect to hear her: for, no leſſe is due to <hi>heathen:</hi> and he would not have ſuch refractory per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons worſe to <hi>us,</hi> then they are to <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe:</hi> nay, he ſaith, [<hi>it shall be more to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable, in the day of Iudgement, for Heathen, then for them, S. Mat.</hi> 10.14.]</p>
               <p>Fourth Proofe. S. Mat. <hi>28.19.</hi> Mar. <hi>16.15.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, moſt plainly and fully, from the Charter it ſelf, for the found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this office, recorded by two of the Evangeliſts. [<hi>Ieſus ſaid to them</hi> (his Apoſtles:) <hi>Goe ye into all the world, teach all Nations, preach the Goſpel to every creature, baptizing them: teach them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you. He that believes</hi> (you, or your teaching, or the Goſpell
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:34171:26"/>
by you taught), <hi>and is baptiſed, shall be ſaved, but he that beleeves not, shall be damned.</hi>].</p>
               <p>In which words, I am ſure, your ſelf will not ſay, but he left them as the <hi>firſt,</hi> and <hi>temporary</hi> meanes, of teaching his Goſpell, and baptizing. And if for the firſt; for the <hi>ordinary</hi> (or <hi>perpetuall</hi>), by vertue of thoſe <hi>incorporating</hi> words <hi>[you, to worlds end].</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſequently, as the preſent Church, <hi>baptiſes</hi> with all the ſame office and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority as the Apoſtles did; ſo she <hi>tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> alſo with all the ſame, as they did, in vertue of this Commiſſion. For, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever other powers or priviledges they had, (of infallibility, in more then one; the gift of miracles, authority of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Canonicall Scripture, &amp;c. in any one); was not in vertue of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</p>
               <p>A more plain, and full proof, H. Scripture hath not, for any point of Chriſtian faith: nor am I able to deviſe, what other anſwer you can give to it then this <hi>[what need any more witneſſes?]</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:34171:26"/>
But for more aboundant confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let's hear more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Proving it from the Acts.</head>
               <p>THe beſt interpreter of figures, and propheſies, is their fulfilling: and the beſt comment upon Chriſt's commiſſion is the practice and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in the execution of it, regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in the Hiſtory of the Primitive Church. In which as there is no doubt but the H. Ghoſt recorded the things of moſt importance for the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and direction; ſo nor but that he recorded thoſe he did, for the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne and imitation of future ages. Conſequently, what it ſets forth to have been then the means for teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpell; is to be ſuppoſed to have been left by them in that office.</p>
               <p>Now that the Church was that means: is manifeſt from aboundance of paſſages in it: whereof I shall name ſome.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:34171:27"/>1 <hi>Proofe. Act.</hi> 2.3, 5.</p>
               <p>The gift conferred from heaven on the Apoſtles, on the day of Pente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſt, as neceſſary and ſufficient to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able them to their office of teaching the Goſpell, was not <hi>penns</hi> (though none of them were any great <hi>Scribes,</hi> and the greater part of them (for ought appeares) not able to <hi>write</hi> a word), but <hi>tongues.</hi> A ſigne, they were to teach religion, not by their <hi>writing,</hi> but their <hi>ſpeech,</hi> or <hi>utterance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2 <hi>Proofe. Act:</hi> 2.14. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt, and all the means (ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of in this Hiſtory) uſed by them, <hi>in their own perſons,</hi> for bringing Infidells to faith, was <hi>preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. [Peter with the eleven, standing up,</hi> &amp;c.] v. 14.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Such as were moved by it to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Chriſtian Law, ſought it at their mouth <hi>[Men and brethren, what shall we doe?]</hi> v. 37.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Peter</hi> taught them their Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme [<hi>Repent and be baptized,</hi> &amp;c.] v. 38. without bringing any Scripture
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:34171:27"/>
proofe; as he did afore, when he taught them as <hi>Infidels</hi> (v. 16, 25, 34.)</p>
               <p n="4">4. The rule afterward of faith, worship, diſcipline, &amp;c. unto the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving people, was the doctrine and inſtitutes of their Paſtors <hi>[They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſtedfaſtly in the Apostles do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and felowship, and in breaking of bread, and in prayer]</hi> v. 41.</p>
               <p>Loe here, the Church ſettled and compleated in all her forme of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Worship, Sacraments, &amp;c. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any ſyllable of the Goſpell was written, or (for ought appeares) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be.</p>
               <p>Loe here, in the <hi>Mother-Church (Mount Zyon.</hi> Gal. 4.26. <hi>the aſſembly of the first-borne,</hi> Heb. 12.22.) the pattern according to which all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches afterward were to be gathered, ſetled, and governed, to worlds end.</p>
               <p>3 <hi>Proofe. Act.</hi> 6.6, 7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.4. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>All the meanes taken notice of in this Hiſtory, <hi>beſides their own perſons,</hi> provided, uſed, ſettled, declared, and left by them, for teaching the Goſpell;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34171:28"/>
was the <hi>preaching</hi> of others, whom they took into their body, to that end; and ſent them abroad over the world; (<hi>Act.</hi> 11.19. &amp; 13.4.); and placed ſome one or more of them, in every City and Towne where the Goſpell took roote (<hi>Act.</hi> 9.10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.22.) to inſtruct and guide the people of thoſe Townes, in all things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to religion, in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as a <hi>sheapheard</hi> doth his <hi>flock</hi> (Act. 20.28.)</p>
               <p>4 <hi>Proofe. Act.</hi> 8.4, 14, 25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.28.</p>
               <p>Theſe others, were Teachers, <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely authoriſed,</hi> as well as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: they being <hi>ſent</hi> to preach, and <hi>ſet over the flock</hi> to feed it, by the ſame H. Ghoſt the Apoſtles were; and their teaching, <hi>Gods word</hi> (in the ſubſtance of it) no leſſe then that of the Apoſtles: only with this difference <hi>accidentall;</hi> that in the Apoſtles mouth it was ſo, originally, ſupreamly, abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, and infallibly; in the others, ſubordinately, fallibly, and no longer
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:34171:28"/>
or further then they taught what they received from the Church. (<hi>Act.</hi> 15.24).</p>
               <p>Nor therefore can you ſay, that the teaching of theſe other, was called, <hi>[the word of God],</hi> becauſe they preached <hi>Scripture, or conſonantly to it:</hi> being here called ſo (<hi>Act.</hi> 8.14.), many years afore a word of the new Teſtament was written, and they could not ground Evangelicall doctrine [<hi>Chriſt is come. Ieſus is he, is riſen,</hi> &amp;c,.] upon the Old Teſtament.</p>
               <p>5 <hi>Proofe. Act.</hi> 8.29. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.9.</p>
               <p>When God Almighty would have any taught the Goſpell, he either ſent them to the Church, or the Church to them. Nor was there any difference in the meanes, whether <hi>Apoſtles</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Pastors; Saul</hi> being ſent in all the ſame manner to <hi>Ananias,</hi> as <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius</hi> to S. <hi>Peter:</hi> and S. <hi>Philip</hi> to the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Macedonians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>6 <hi>Proof. Act.</hi> 11.14.</p>
               <p>The word thus <hi>preached</hi> by the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:34171:29"/>
Church, (in which it was by accident, if any Scripture were cited to <hi>belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</hi>) was <hi>ſufficient to ſave the ſoules of the people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>7 <hi>Proofe. Act.</hi> 15.2, <hi>&amp;c. &amp;</hi> 16.4, 5.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In caſe the Teachers differed; the peoples remedy was, to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe (not to the Scripture then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, albeit it conteined rules proper to have decided the queſtion, viz. <hi>VVhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circumciſion was neceſſary to all that were to be within the covenant of grace made with Abraham;</hi> and one party of the Teachers founded their doctrine upon the expreſſe words of it (viz. that it was a law given to him <hi>for all generations for ever</hi> (Gen. 17.13. Pſal. 105.9.); and the other party, were no leſſe then Apoſtles, in <hi>extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> but) to <hi>the Church</hi> (or eminent bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Paſtors in ordinary,) then by accident, reſiding at <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Theſe <hi>coming together to conſider of,</hi> and decide <hi>it,</hi> founded the deciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not upon ſcripture (though in a very fundamentall point of faith), but
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:34171:29"/>
meerly upon their own illumination, and guidance by the H. Ghoſt <hi>[It ſeemed good to the H. Ghoſt and to us]</hi> v. 28. So, <hi>their</hi> decree, <hi>his</hi> decree; theirs, as <hi>his mouth;</hi> his, as the <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall</hi> Law-giver; and conſequently, to reſiſt it, no leſſe ſin then to reſiſt the H. Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>Nor can you ſay they intitled it to him, becauſe part of the aſſembly were <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> For as it were purpoſely to preclude you from this evaſion, the H. Ghoſt took care to note; 1. That the Apoſtles ſate and voted there, in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of <hi>Presbyters,</hi> as it was a name com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon then to Prieſts and Bishops, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they <hi>the chief,</hi> therefore named firſt, and ſingularly. 2. That there was much <hi>diſputing</hi> upon the point (<hi>v.</hi> 7.). Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, the Apoſtles, proceeded not to the ſentence, as <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> or taught by <hi>inſpiration;</hi> but as <hi>Paſtors,</hi> or by the <hi>ordinary</hi> authority of the Church, as it was to continue in their ſucceſſors.</p>
               <p n="3">3. S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> though
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:34171:30"/>
                  <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> thought it an honour to <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> to be officers to the Church in publishing and diſperſing her decrees; and to their <hi>doctrine,</hi> that it was by her approved. (16.4.)</p>
               <p n="4">4. As they went through the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, they <hi>delivered them the decrees of the Councell for to keep</hi> (Act. 16.4.) which was more then we finde they did, any book of Scripture.</p>
               <p n="5">5. When the good Chriſtians heard what the Councell had decreed, <hi>they rejoyced for the conſolation,</hi> of being certain now what was true doctrine in that point (15.31.)</p>
               <p n="6">6. And <hi>thus were the Churches eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished in the ſaith</hi> (16.5.)</p>
               <p>8 <hi>Proofe. Act.</hi> 20.20, 27, 32.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Apoſtles, by word of mouth, committed unto the Church, all things <hi>needfull,</hi> nay but <hi>profitable</hi> only, for them to know for the full diſcharge of their office, unto ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of themſelves and their flock. And ſo made her <hi>the depoſitary</hi> of what Chriſt had committed to them.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:34171:30"/>2. That which they thus commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by word of mouth to the Church, was in ſimple ſenſe <hi>[the word of grace]:</hi> nay expreſſely <hi>[the whole counſell of God].</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. This forme of doctrine thus taught by tradition, was left and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely recommended by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, unto rhe Church for her ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent rule, and guide; [<hi>And now bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren I commend you to the word of Gods grace, which is able to eſtablish you,</hi> &amp;c.] v. 32.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And this, at their death, or as good as their death, when they were never like to ſee one anothers faces more in this world. [<hi>I know that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my departure,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
               <p n="5">5. So at their deaths they left the Church to continue for ever, in all the ſame office and authority for <hi>feeding</hi> and <hi>ruling</hi> the flock of Chriſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they then were, or had been at any time afore; and namely, afore the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the New Teſtament. [<hi>Take heed to your ſelves, and to the flock over
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:34171:31"/>
the which the H. Ghoſt hath made you Bishops</hi> (or, as yours, prophanely, <hi>overſeers) to feed the Church,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <p>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Proving it from the Epiſtles.</p>
               <p>TO the practice and proceedings of the Apoſtles in their <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> accord the rules, inſtructions, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and admonitions in their <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles;</hi> all ſetting forth, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending unto us the Church for our guide, and her teaching for our rule, in ſuch manner, as if there were no ſuch book as <hi>Scripture,</hi> nor to be. To name a few of the principal, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p>1 <hi>Proofe. Rom.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Iude,</hi> 3.2 <hi>Io.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is their ordinary language to call the Churche's doctrine [<hi>the word, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, oracles, Goſpell,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of God, Christ, life, ſalvation,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the faith, the truth,</hi> &amp;c.] in ſimple ſenſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And not <hi>that</hi> preached by the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:34171:31"/>
                  <hi>Apoſtles</hi> only, but by the <hi>Paſtors;</hi> (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom it was by accident if any were an <hi>Apoſtle). Rom.</hi> 10.8, 17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.21.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Nay, <hi>that,</hi> which was preached by <hi>Paſtors;</hi> of whom the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> none, for certaine (<hi>Col.</hi> 1.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.16.)</p>
               <p>Nor can you ſay it was ſo called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was the <hi>Scripture</hi> preached, or in regard of its <hi>conſonancy</hi> to it. For</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Old</hi> Teſtament, could give neither the <hi>matter,</hi> nor <hi>rule,</hi> for <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall</hi> doctrine: and very little of the <hi>New,</hi> was written when S. <hi>Paul</hi> called it ſo, in the firſt Epiſtle by him written (1 <hi>Th.</hi> 2.13.) and S. <hi>Peter,</hi> in the firſt that was written (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12, 25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.2.)</p>
               <p n="2">2. Many <hi>Evangelicall</hi> doctrines then <hi>revealed,</hi> were not <hi>written</hi> then: to wit, thoſe mentioned in S. <hi>Iohn</hi>'s Goſpells, and Epiſtles, more then are in the other: namely the inſtitution of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Prieſtly abſolution</hi> (Ioh. 20.21.); Chriſt's <hi>committing his flock to S. Peter</hi> Ioh. 21.15.).</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Epiſtles themſelves expreſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:34171:32"/>
require all Traditions to be held, <hi>unwritten</hi> as well as <hi>written;</hi> and not thoſe onely taught by the Apoſtles, <hi>but</hi> by their Paſtors (<hi>Timothy, Silvanus, &amp;c.</hi> among whom it was by accident that S. <hi>Paul was one) [Hold the traditions which you have been taught, whether by word, or our Epiſtle,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 2.15.]</p>
               <p>2. Proof, <hi>Ro.</hi> 1.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.6. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.16. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.20. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Iude</hi> 23.</p>
               <p>The Churches teaching, or doctrine by her taught, is called alſo, in ſimple ſenſe, [<hi>the power (i.e.</hi> powerful inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) <hi>of God unto ſalvation of all that believe it; the rule</hi> (or as you call it, <hi>proportion) of faith; the ſword of the Spirit; the myſterie of faith; the good thing, depoſitum, or treaſure of heavenly truth; the form of ſound words or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, committed by the Apoſtles to the Church; the faith once delivered to the Saints; the faithful word, able to ſave the ſouls of all that follow it.</hi>]</p>
               <p>3. Proof, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14, 17.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle expreſſely averrs, he
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:34171:32"/>
knows no means wherby men may come to faith, but the word <hi>preached;</hi> and thereupon concludes abſolutely <hi>[Faith comes by hearing, and hearing by the word of God.]</hi> As much as to ſay <hi>[the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary means of faith is hearing the word preached.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. Proof, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.9. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.14. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.7, 9.</p>
               <p>The rule of teaching, to the Paſtors, was <hi>[the doctrine they had received.]</hi> And it was the rule even to <hi>Prophets</hi> to, <hi>[If any man prophecy, according to the analogie, rule, or</hi> (as you render it) <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of faith,</hi> Rom. 12.6.] that is, the known doctrine of the Church: For, that it could not mean the Scripture, ſee the reaſons given, <hi>ſup. pag.</hi> 59.</p>
               <p>5. Proof, <hi>Ro.</hi> 16.17. 2 <hi>Th.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7, 17. <hi>Iud.</hi> 3.1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.2, 6. 2 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6, 9.</p>
               <p>The rule of belief and holy practice to the people, was <hi>the doctrine wherein they had been, Catechiſed,</hi> called by S. <hi>Iohn [the unction of the H. Ghoſt,</hi> 1 Ioh. 2.20.] and generally, <hi>the doctrine or inſtitutes of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:34171:33"/>
the Church. [Hereby know we the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of truth and the ſpirit of error. He that knows God, hears us; he that is not of God, heareth not us</hi> (1 Ioh. 4.6.).</p>
               <p>This doctrine of our Catechiſme, is given unto all Chriſtians (ſuppoſed catechiſed by a <hi>lawfull</hi> Paſtor, as the <hi>Galatians</hi> were) as a rule of that ſupream authority, and infallible certainty, as by it we are to try the ſpirits of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> (1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.21.) yea even of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,</hi> or <hi>heavenly Angels (Gal.</hi> 1.8.), if poſſible for them to teach repugnant to it.</p>
               <p>And if a rule whereby to judge of the <hi>Apoſtles preaching,</hi> of their <hi>wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> alſo: it being as impoſſible for them to <hi>write,</hi> as to <hi>preach</hi> repugnant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to it; and their <hi>writing</hi> being of no greater authority then their <hi>preaching.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſequently this text (<hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8.) which your men uſe to urge againſt <hi>Traditions,</hi> gives ſo great authority to them, as it implicitely warnes us, on perill of our ſoul, not to beleive or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any text of H. Scripture it ſelf; in
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:34171:33"/>
any ſenſe repugnant (if poſſible for it to have any, as it is not) to the doctrine of our <hi>Catechiſme</hi> (ſuppoſe it given by a lawfull Paſtor).</p>
               <p>Nor can you ſay, that this ſubſiſts not with what we teach, that any <hi>particular</hi> Paſtor, yea <hi>Pope</hi> and all as <hi>ſuch,</hi> may teach falſe doctrine; for we will not ſay, that any <hi>lawfull</hi> Paſtor can doe it (which who is, we shall ſee in next Treatiſe).</p>
               <p>6 <hi>Proofe.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.7.</p>
               <p>The Paſtors in <hi>common</hi> (among whom it was by accident if any one were an Apoſtle) are ſtyled in ſimple ſenſe [<hi>the miniſters of Chriſt, his em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, the ſtewards</hi> (depoſitaries, and diſpenſers) <hi>of the myſteries of God</hi>] whereof thoſe of <hi>faith,</hi> the firſt.</p>
               <p>7 <hi>Proofe. Gal.</hi> 2.1.</p>
               <p>So ſupreame at that time was, (and conſequently, to worlds end was to be; for els wherefore read we the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures now?) the authority of the Church; as God Almighty ſeeing
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:34171:34"/>
how S, <hi>Pauls</hi> teaching was with leſs fruit, becauſe oppoſed by other Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers (who called themſelves <hi>Apoſtles of Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13.) yea, pretended to teach the doctrine of the Church, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.1.): willed him by revelation to go up to the chief Paſtors, reſiding then (by accident) at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to confer his doctrine with them, and procure their approbation to it.</p>
               <p>Nay, S. <hi>Iohn</hi> himſelf (though an Apoſtle <hi>in ordinary</hi>) for the greater cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and fruit of his Goſpel, as to the people, in regard of the great oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was like to be made againſt it by the hereticks that denied Chriſts Divinitie, and were verie malapert againſt him for aſſerting it (3 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.) was moved by the H. Ghoſt, to procure and inſert in the cloſe of it, the teſtimonie of ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors [<hi>we know that his teſtimony is true,</hi> Ioh. 21.24.] A ſingular inſtance, to shew in what high eſteem and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the teſtimonie of the Church (even to the <hi>truth</hi> of H. Scripture it ſelf, as to <hi>us,</hi> and much more to the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:34171:34"/>
it) then was, and was left by the Apoſtles at their death, for ever to be, amongſt all good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
               <p>8. Proof, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle delivers our tenet, in almoſt expreſs <hi>words;</hi> plainly and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in <hi>ſenſe [VVhen Chriſt aſcended, he gave ſome, Apoſtles, &amp;c. for the perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Saints, &amp;c.</hi> (that is, as the ordinary means to that end) <hi>until we all come in unity of faith</hi> (which will not be till the ſecond coming of Chriſt) &amp;c. <hi>that we henceforth be no more as children toſſed to and fro, &amp;c.</hi>] which end is not poſsibly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable, if thoſe <hi>Pastors</hi> may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed liable to teach an errout in faith.</p>
               <p>9. Proof, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.</p>
               <p>The Church is called in ſimple ſenſe:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Houſe of God</hi> (meaning with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, that <hi>School houſe</hi> for teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Religion, of which <hi>Eſay</hi> foretold, <hi>Eſay</hi> 2.2.)</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:34171:35"/>2. <hi>The pillar of truth,</hi> not of the <hi>written truth</hi> only; but of <hi>the truth,</hi> abſolutely; that is, of <hi>all</hi> truth (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed). And not a pillar upon which Scripture is promulged or notified on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the people, as Princes edicts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome poſt: but ſuch a <hi>pillar</hi> as is alſo the <hi>foundation</hi> to the whole frame of truth. Therefore he ſaith in the next word,</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>[The ground of the truth].</hi> Which in ſimple ſenſe <hi>abſolutely,</hi> is the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable attribute of God Almighty <hi>(the first truth):</hi> in ſenſe wherein it may be given to any created meanes (that is, as to <hi>us,</hi> or our attaining to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or certainty of truth) is here gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Church. And ſo it compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes our Tenet, in the fulleſt, higheſt, ſenſe poſſible; and particularly, the <hi>infallibility</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> in her teaching. For</p>
               <p n="1">1. If she the ground of <hi>all</hi> truth; then of this, <hi>[there was a Ieſus of Nazareth;]</hi> of this <hi>[there is a Scripture;]</hi> of this <hi>[there is a H. Ghoſt;]</hi> nay,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:34171:35"/>
of this <hi>[there is a God.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. If theſe and other revealed points be infallible truths; she, <hi>the ground</hi> of them, muſt be infallible. So as if poſſible for her ever once to totter in the truth of her teſtimony touching any one point (by either af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming ſomething to be Goſpell, which is not; or denying ſomething to be, which is): the whole frame of the truth and certainty of Chriſtian Religion (as to <hi>us</hi>) muſt neceſſarily totter with it; as any building muſt, whoſe foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on does: and as we could not believe the Scripture in <hi>any</hi> thing, if we found it falſe in any <hi>one</hi> thing.</p>
               <p>Nor can you evade this place, by ſaying, he gives this attribute here to a particular Church (namely that of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> in which <hi>Timothy</hi> was to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have himſelf</hi>); which we will not ſay was infallible. For, that Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then a part of the <hi>Catholick;</hi> though it were not infallible, yet he being (im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately) Paſtor of <hi>it,</hi> was (mediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) a Paſtor of the <hi>Catholick,</hi> whoſe
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:34171:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
attribute that was. As he that came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any gate, lane, or houſe of <hi>Ieruſalem, came into the Holy City,</hi> (Mat. 27.53.) though that gate, lane or houſe, were not ſo.</p>
               <p>10. Proof, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. &amp; 2.2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.9. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The means,</hi> preſcribed and named by the Apoſtle, for preſerving to worlds end the knowledge or doctrine of the Goſpel, was, <hi>Tradition</hi> of the Paſtors from hand to hand: <hi>[The things thou haſt heard of me, commit thou to faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful men, who shall be able to teach others alſo.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A means, ſubject indeed to corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in tract of time, if the depoſitaries be conſidered as <hi>men;</hi> but not, if as men aſsiſted to the pure and uncorrupt keeping of it, by the H. Ghoſt, to that end ſent down from heaven upon them (<hi>Act.</hi> 2.3.) with ſuch admirable graces, as even <hi>the Angels deſire,</hi> and are delighted, <hi>to behold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>11. Proof, <hi>Apoc,</hi> 2.1.</p>
               <p>The Paſtor of a particular Church,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:34171:36"/>
is called <hi>[the Angel of it.]</hi> Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, by the rule of proportion, the whole company of them, is <hi>[the Angel of the Church univerſal:]</hi> that is, the ordinary means under God, to illuminate and guide them, and interpret Gods will to them in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual things.</p>
               <p>12. Proof, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.23.</p>
               <p>Finally, the teaching of the <hi>New Ieruſalem</hi> (which in the <hi>firſt</hi> ſenſe, means without doubt the Catholick Militant Church of Chriſt, in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the <hi>Synagogue,</hi> the <hi>old earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ieruſalem</hi>) is called [<hi>the light, in which shall walk the nations of them that are ſaved</hi> (Acts 2.47. &amp; 13.48.) whoſe light is not the <hi>Sun or Moon</hi> (any created, corruptible means) but <hi>God himſelf and the Lamb</hi> (Mat. 28.20.) ſo as, there <hi>shall never be any night</hi> (of error) <hi>in that City,</hi> becauſe <hi>its Sun shall never ſet, &amp;c.</hi> Eſa. 60.20.] You ſee how expreſly, how abundantly H. Scripture (from firſt to laſt) ſets forth our principle. It had been eaſie
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:34171:37"/>
to have quoted ten times more texts to the ſame purpoſe: but to whom this is not enough, nothing would: Now let's ſee what you have to object againſt it.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:34171:37"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PART: Defending the Catholick Tenet.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Solving Objections againſt the Churche's authority.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>true</hi> reaſon wherefore your <hi>Miniſters</hi> deny unto H. Church this office of teaching Religion, is becauſe they are conſcious, both of their having no title to <hi>the church;</hi> and of being ſure to be condemned, if they should ſubmit to any judge but a <hi>mute</hi> one. And yet under colour of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting Scripture by it ſelf, they finde a way to exerciſe all the ſame office themſelves, as they deny to her, and with much greater arrogance.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:34171:38"/>The <hi>pretended</hi> reaſon is, becauſe (forſooth) she is liable to error in her teaching, except when she teaches Scripture, and therefore is limitted to it, as to a <hi>bar-rule,</hi> beſide or beyond which she may not teach or command any thing as Goſpel: and the people lawfully may, nay, and at their peril are to examine by it their Paſtors teaching; and if not there, reject it.</p>
               <p>Any of which allegations, if true, would indeed quite overthrow our tenet. But they are egregious falſe ones, as will appear by our anſwers to the beſt proofs for them.</p>
               <p>1. <hi>Object.</hi> Deut. 4.2. &amp; 5.32.</p>
               <p>[Thou shalt not adde to this word, &amp;c.] <hi>As much as to ſay</hi> [not teach, do, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve any thing in Religion, but what is written.]</p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>No ſuch thing: For, 1. He ſpake not of the <hi>written</hi> Law; but the words <hi>commanded by him.</hi> 2. Grant he meant the <hi>written</hi> Law, he neither ſaith, nor
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:34171:38"/>
meant as you gloſs him. Becauſe, then</p>
               <p n="1">1. None could have believed, or taught [the creation of the Angels; fall, and punishment of the Devils; the ſpiritual taint of humane nature by <hi>Adams</hi> ſin; the immortality of the ſoul; reſurrection of the body; eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal punishments of the wicked, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of the juſt.]</p>
               <p n="2">2. Then, <hi>Ioſuah</hi> had tranſgreſſed this Precept, when he <hi>added</hi> to the Law, <hi>his Book:</hi> (Ioſ. 24.26.) <hi>Ezra,</hi> or whoever elſe it was, that <hi>added to it,</hi> the Book of <hi>Iob,</hi> and the reſt of the Old Teſtament: much more they, that to things expreſſely ordained by it, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded other; namely, <hi>David, Pſalms</hi> and <hi>Muſick; Solomon,</hi> a Temple; <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah,</hi> 14 days to the Paſſover (2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 30.22.) he that firſt appointed the Law to be read to the people every Sabboth day; and permitted them to have it in their own hands to read, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Then, when the High Prieſt had
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:34171:39"/>
given ſentence in any cauſe, no man might have believed, or done, but what was in that ſentence; for of it, it is ſaid [<hi>Thou shalt not decline from it,</hi> &amp;c. Deut. 17.11.] 4. Then <hi>Ioſuah</hi> declined from the ways of <hi>David,</hi> when he read the Law in the Temple; (2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 34., 30.) which <hi>David</hi> never did.</p>
               <p>Thoſe phraſes then [<hi>thou shalt not add,</hi> &amp;c.] meant no more but this that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows preſently, as it were to explicate them [<hi>thou shalt obſerve to do all,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
               <p>2. <hi>Object.</hi> Eſa 8.20.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[To the Law, and to the teſtimony. If they ſpeak not according to this word, &amp;c.]</hi> Plainly, authorizing and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting people, to examine their <hi>Paſtors</hi> doctrine, by the Scripture, and if not there, reject it.</p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>As wide as the former. For</p>
               <p n="1">1. He names not the Scripture, nor meant it, <hi>neceſſarily</hi> (much leſs <hi>ſolely.</hi>) 2. Grant, he meant it; yet 1. not as in the <hi>people's hand;</hi> but as read, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted, to them by their <hi>Paſtors</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:34171:39"/>
(Exod. 24.12. 2 Chr. 17.9. Neh. 8.7.) 2. Nor therefore by <hi>[they,]</hi> did he mean their <hi>Paſtors;</hi> but Sorcerers, Idolaters, or ſuch like impious wretches, ſpoken of in the words next afore. 3. Nor, by <hi>[not according to it,]</hi> did he mean, <hi>beſide,</hi> or <hi>beyond it;</hi> but <hi>evidently repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> to it; as that counſel <hi>[Seek unto wizards]</hi> was, of which he there par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly ſpoke.</p>
               <p>3. <hi>Object.</hi> Eze, 44.24.</p>
               <p>[They shall judge it, according to my judgement;] <hi>meaning,</hi> according to Moſes Law.</p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Perhaps not, 2. Grant, he meant it, he meant it as <hi>guide-rule</hi> onely, not a <hi>bar-rule: according to it,</hi> not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it <hi>alone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. <hi>Object.</hi> S. Mat. 15.9.</p>
               <p>[Teaching for doctrines, the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of men;] <hi>that is,</hi> unwritten <hi>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>No ſuch matter; but <hi>commandments repugnant to God's Law</hi> (whether writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:34171:40"/>
or unwriten.] Such as that, in which he there inſtanced [<hi>God ſaid,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But you ſay,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>v.</hi> 4, 5.]</p>
               <p>5. <hi>Object.</hi> S. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.14. &amp; 16, 6, 12.</p>
               <p>[<hi>Take heed of the doctrine of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> (which yet ſate then in <hi>Moſes Chair:) they are blinde guides;</hi> and <hi>if the blinde lead the blinde,</hi> &amp;c.] Plainly intimating, that people, at their own peril, are to uſe their eyes, in judging of the truth of what is taught them, be the Teacher never ſo lawfully autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized: ſeeing they may be <hi>blinde guides.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>The Scribes and Phariſees (ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>generally, &amp; per ſe) ſate in Moſes Chair,</hi> that is, <hi>taught what they had au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for from the Synagogue.</hi> And in conſideration thereof, our Saviours rule was [<hi>All things therefore whatſover,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.2.] Sometimes they ſate in <hi>their own Chair;</hi> that is, taught their private opinions, or traditions of their Sect. Whence, ſometimes the people might have reaſon to doubt of their
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:34171:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
teaching: which when they had; they were, at their own peril, to examine, and judge of it; but not by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but <hi>the doctrine of Moſes Chair;</hi> or if by the Scripture, not but as <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted</hi> by that chair.</p>
               <p>6. <hi>Object.</hi> Acts 17.11.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Bereans</hi> are commended for ſearching in Scripture, even <hi>Pauls</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. Much more, may people their <hi>Paſtors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>Neither t'one, nor t'other. For</p>
               <p n="1">1. Perhaps not commended for <hi>ſearching;</hi> but onely for <hi>[receiving the word with all greedineſs:]</hi> that is, <hi>liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> to it very greedily, whereas the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> ſtopt theirs at it. Nay, perhaps not for that neither; but onely noted for a <hi>more noble</hi> people, without particularizing, <hi>wherein.</hi> For, thoſe words <hi>[in that]</hi> implying a reaſon given, are onely of your Tranſlators inſerting, and confeſſed for ſuch, by a ſmaller Character, in moſt of your editions: the text rightly rendred, being a meer
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:34171:41"/>
relation of what paſſed <hi>conſequenter, [Theſe were more noble; receiving the word,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>ſearching.</hi>]</p>
               <p n="2">2. Grant, <hi>commended</hi> for it; it will not therefore follow, that ſo may peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple examine their <hi>Paſtors</hi> doctrine; Becauſe, 1. They were then no <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> (as I think) and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he, none of their <hi>Paſtor.</hi> And my reaſon is, 1. Becauſe they ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed [<hi>whether Chriſt ought to have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered,</hi> &amp;c.] in order to judging, <hi>whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ieſus were the Chriſt,</hi> (v. 3.) which no Chriſtian could doubt of. 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe upon, and after the ſearch, it is ſaid <hi>[therefore many of them believed.]</hi> So, ſome, not then: till then, none. And conſequently, that might be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in <hi>them,</hi> which would have been a mortal ſin in them, if <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> 2. Becauſe (granting they were <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi>) 1. They did not ſearch for any doctrine of his, delivering Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>faith</hi> (viz. <hi>Chriſt is come, Ieſus is the Chriſt, is riſen,</hi> &amp;c.) which was not poſsible to be found in the Scripture
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:34171:41"/>
they ſearched; but onely for a <hi>proof</hi> he brought toward it [viz. <hi>Chriſt ought to have ſuffered, &amp;c. riſen again;</hi>] which he affirmed to be in Scripture, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired his hearers not to believe it, or him, unleſs it were (<hi>v.</hi> 3. &amp; 26.22.) 2. Nor did they ſearch with doubt, or intent to <hi>judge</hi> of the truth of his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; but onely to ſatisfie their <hi>curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity,</hi> or to <hi>confirm</hi> and <hi>comfort</hi> their yet tender faith, by reading in their own Bible, with their own eyes, what they little dreamt to be in it; having been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways taught out of it to the contrary; and having read perhaps the places quoted, a hundred times over, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver obſerved any ſuch thing in them.</p>
               <p>7. <hi>Object.</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.27.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[Prove all things.]</hi> If <hi>all;</hi> the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of our <hi>Paſtors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>I might aſwel infer [<hi>all things are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for me,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.23.] If <hi>all; lying,</hi> and <hi>theft.</hi> we are therfore to underſtand him as in that, ſo in this, of all things of the ſort there ſpoken of, viz. <hi>Prophecyings</hi> (the word next afore.)</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:34171:42"/>8. <hi>Object.</hi> 1 Cor. 10.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[Iudge ye what I ſay].</hi> Leaving his doctrine to be judged of by the people.</p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>By a judgement of pure <hi>approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> For elſe you muſt ſay (which I think you will not preſume) that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are judges even of <hi>Scripture</hi> it ſelf; for ſo was that, which he then bad them judge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 1 Cor. 4.6.</p>
               <p>[Not to think of men above what is written.]</p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>That is, whereas he had <hi>named</hi> no man, but under the borrowed names of <hi>himſelf</hi> and <hi>Apollos;</hi> they should not <hi>think</hi> (or <hi>gueſs</hi>) who he <hi>meant,</hi> by him, or him.</p>
               <p>10, <hi>Object.</hi> 1 Pet. 4.11.</p>
               <p>[If any man ſpeak; as the oracles of God.]</p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>That is, if any man have the gift of utterance, or eloquent ſpeech, let him uſe it, as Gods words, ſpeech, or gift, that he may be glorified.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:34171:42"/>11. <hi>Object.</hi> Apoc. 22.18.</p>
               <p>[If any man shall adde unto the words <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>Either by corrupting them, or hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing <hi>contrary</hi> to them; for example, that <hi>Antichrist shall be a Chriſtian; or reign</hi> 1000. <hi>years; or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor Gods Tabernacle, or them that dwell in heaven</hi> (Apoc. 13.6.) &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Solving Objections againſt her <hi>Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>1. <hi>Object.</hi> Exod. 32.4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[THey ſaid, Theſe are thy Gods, O Iſrael.]</hi> Idolatry taught by the Prieſts, High Prieſt and all.</p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>No ſuch matter. For 1. Perhaps that was not the <hi>Prieſts</hi> ſaying, but the <hi>Peoples.</hi> 2. If the <hi>Prieſts;</hi> not <hi>Aarons</hi> 3. If <hi>his</hi> alſo; <hi>enticing</hi> to Idolatry, migh be without <hi>teaching</hi> it. 4. If he <hi>taught</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:34171:43"/>
it; he was not then the <hi>Supreme Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor,</hi> but <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. <hi>Object.</hi> Ier. 50.6.</p>
               <p>[Their shepherds have cauſed them to go aſtray.]</p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>But he doth not ſay, [<hi>by their teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. <hi>Object.</hi> Mal. 2.8.</p>
               <p>[You have cauſed many to ſtumble at the Law.]</p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>But he ſaith not <hi>[by your teaching.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. <hi>Object.</hi> Mat. 7.15. &amp; 24.5, 24.</p>
               <p>[Take heed of falſe Prophets. Many shall ariſe, and deceive many, &amp;c.]</p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But he never ſaid</hi> [Take heed of your Paſtors; they shall ſeduce you.]</p>
               <p>5. <hi>Object.</hi> Mat. 13.25.</p>
               <p>The Church is compared to a <hi>field,</hi> ſown at firſt <hi>with good ſeed,</hi> afterward over run with <hi>tares</hi> of errors.</p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Perhaps not <hi>the Church;</hi> but par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches, or ſouls. 2. Grant,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:34171:43"/>
                  <hi>the Church:</hi> thoſe <hi>tares</hi> meant not errors in <hi>doctrin,</hi> but in <hi>life,</hi> or <hi>practice.</hi> 3. Grant erronous <hi>doctrines;</hi> yet 1. Not ſown by <hi>her,</hi> or any of <hi>hers,</hi> but the <hi>enemy.</hi> 2. Nor ſpringing up within her <hi>doctrine;</hi> but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly within the ſame <hi>field</hi> (or countrey) where it was ſown, or is growing.</p>
               <p>6. <hi>Object.</hi> Mar. 14.64. Ioh. 9.22.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The very</hi> Chair of Moſes <hi>taught falſe doctrine; viz.</hi> [that Ieſus was not the Christ.]</p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Moſes Chair</hi> was not then in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, further then it was authorized by him: who albeit <hi>he did authorize</hi> it as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, in <hi>all things,</hi> until his own should be erected; yet <hi>it is manifest he excepted himſelf, who put all things under it,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>7. <hi>Object.</hi> Luke 18.8.</p>
               <p>VVhen the Son of man comes shall he finde faith in the earth?</p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>Little <hi>perfect</hi> faith, in the <hi>world;</hi> but he shall, <hi>true</hi> and <hi>perfect</hi> faith, believed and profeſſed by all (lively) members of his church (&amp; conſequently
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:34171:44"/>
taught by her <hi>Paſtors;</hi>) that company of his <hi>Elect</hi> ſpoken of, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18. &amp; 24.24.</p>
               <p>8. <hi>Object.</hi> Acts 20.30.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Even</hi> [Paſtors were to ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things, and drawing away diſciples after them.]</p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>True: <hi>particular</hi> perſons (<hi>e.g. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Cranmer, Calvin,</hi> &amp;c.) There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaid not <hi>[your ſelves,]</hi> but <hi>[of, or among your ſelves.]</hi> Nor did he give any <hi>item,</hi> touching falſe <hi>Pastors</hi> to come; but unto <hi>Paſtors</hi> onely.</p>
               <p>9. <hi>Object.</hi> Rom. 11.21.</p>
               <p>Even <hi>the Church of Rome</hi> her ſelf is warned of her being in danger of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>from grace,</hi> and not onely by <hi>wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs</hi> of life, but by <hi>Infidelity,</hi> as the <hi>Synagogue</hi> had done.</p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>Not <hi>the Church of Rome</hi> (for, that includes the <hi>Pastor</hi> of it, which then was S. <hi>Peter</hi>) but the <hi>generality of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, among the Gentiles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:34171:44"/>10. <hi>Object.</hi> Gal. 2.11.</p>
               <p>Even <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf <hi>erred.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>But not in <hi>teaching falſe doctrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>11. <hi>Object.</hi> 2 Theſſ. 2.3.</p>
               <p>Afore Antichriſt's coming, there was to be a notable <hi>falling away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>But he doth not ſay <hi>[from faith;]</hi> much leſs, <hi>[of the Church.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>12. <hi>Object.</hi> 2 Pet. 2.1.</p>
               <p>[There shall be falſe Teachers among you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>But he doth not ſay, <hi>[the Church shal become a falſe Teacher:]</hi> or ſpeak, or mean, of <hi>Teachers,</hi> coming in quality of her <hi>Paſtors,</hi> but of <hi>Prophets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>13. <hi>Object.</hi> 1 Ioh. 4.1.</p>
               <p>[Try the ſpirits whether they are of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Solution.</p>
               <p>But he doth not ſay, <hi>[Try every ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; believe none;]</hi> nor doth he mean, <hi>the ſpirits</hi> of Teachers <hi>authorized by the Church;</hi> much leſs, <hi>her ſpirit:</hi> but
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:34171:45"/>
the ſpirits of ſuch as come in quality of <hi>Prophets.</hi> Now that Chriſt and his Apoſtles, should ſo often and ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly warn people of <hi>falſe Teachers,</hi> to come, in after ages; and always ſpeak of them, under the name of <hi>Prophets;</hi> and never once give any leaſt intimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of danger poſsible by believing the <hi>Church,</hi> or their <hi>Paſtors,</hi> if any ſuch danger were to be; but on the contrary, adviſe and encourage them, <hi>(abſolutely)</hi> to believe and obey them; is againſt the very light of reaſon.</p>
               <p>Concluſion of the ſecond Part.</p>
               <p>You ſee, how nothing is to be ſaid againſt our Principle; now let us exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine yours.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:34171:45"/>
            <head>THE THIRD PART: Examining Proteſtant Proofs.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Examining Proofs for the Tenet.</head>
               <p>YOu ſay <hi>[The Scripture was left for the means of teaching the Goſpel.]</hi> See, if you can finde where it ſaith any ſuch thing of it ſelf, in words or ſenſe.</p>
               <p>1. <hi>Argu.</hi> Deut. 30.10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, is called <hi>[the Law]</hi> in ſimple ſenſe.</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>Not in ſimple ſenſe; but onely [the Law <hi>by him written:</hi>] for elſe it would exclude the <hi>Prophets</hi> (with which it is
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:34171:46"/>
often joyn'd (<hi>Mat.</hi> 5.17.) nay, the Book of <hi>Iob,</hi> which was then <hi>written;</hi> and a multitude of Divine Precepts then not written; namely, thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding <hi>faith, hope, contrition</hi> for ſin, &amp;c. forbidding <hi>drunkenneſs, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>2, <hi>Argu.</hi> Deut. 31.10.</p>
               <p>[Thou shalt read this law in their hearing, that they may learn to fear the Lord.]</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>But he doth not ſay <hi>[that it may teach it them:]</hi> nor any of thoſe things above named that contain or imply the ſenſe of your principle; compare it with them one by one, and you will finde it true as I ſay.</p>
               <p>3. <hi>Argu.</hi> Mark 1.1.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Mark's</hi> is called <hi>[the Goſpel of Chriſt]</hi> in ſimple ſenſe.</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>Not; but onely [the Goſpel <hi>by him written:</hi>] for els it would exclude the other three.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:34171:46"/>4. <hi>Argu.</hi> Iohn 5.39.</p>
               <p>[Search the Scriptures; for in them ye think, to have eternal life; and they are they which teſtifie of me.]</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>But he doth not ſay <hi>[in them you may have eternal life;</hi> or, <hi>they will teach you]</hi> or any other of the words you are to prove, or to the ſame ſenſe.</p>
               <p>5. <hi>Argu.</hi> Rom. 3.2.</p>
               <p>[To them were committed the oracles of God.] <hi>Meaning,</hi> the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>Not <hi>neceſſarily;</hi> much leſs, ſolely: there having been many <hi>oracles</hi> given to them, more then were <hi>written;</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; 1. Divers we meet withal in the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> (2 Tim. 3.8. Heb. 9.19. &amp; 11.37. Iud. 6, 9, 14.) 2. All thoſe given by the High-Prieſt, <hi>viva voce</hi> (from <hi>Adam's</hi> time, until <hi>Chriſt's,</hi>) to them that conſulted him; he being a conſtant (or ordinary) <hi>oracle.</hi> (Gen. 25.22. Iudg. 1.1. 1 Sam. 23. 2. Ioh. 11.51.)</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:34171:47"/>6. <hi>Argu.</hi> Rom. 15.4.</p>
               <p>[The Scripture was written for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.]</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>No doubt of it, and it is an excellent means thereunto. But this is none of the things you are to prove.</p>
               <p>7. <hi>Argu.</hi> 2 Th. 2.15.</p>
               <p>[VVhich you have been taught by our Epiſtle.]</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>But he doth not ſay, nor mean <hi>[which it hath taught you:]</hi> but onely [which you have been taught <hi>by us, whether by word or epiſtle.</hi>]</p>
               <p>8. <hi>Argu.</hi> 2 Tim. 3.15.</p>
               <p>[VVhich are able to make thee wiſe to ſalvation, by faith, &amp;c.]</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>But he doth not ſay [which are able to make <hi>you</hi> wiſe:] meaning, <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in general: nor [which are able to make <hi>thee</hi> wiſe to ſalvation] <hi>abſolutely;</hi> but <hi>[by faith in Chriſt.]</hi> That is, by bringing thee to faith, or confirming, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting thee in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:34171:47"/>Better proofs then theſe, I am ſure you have not: and the beſt of theſe (as you may ſee a <hi>little</hi> alreadie; will <hi>more,</hi> anon) is verie short of a proof. And no wonder; when the Scripture cannot contradict it ſelf (in <hi>ſenſe;</hi>) as it would, if in one place (as I have named an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred) it should ſet forth <hi>the Church</hi> for our Teacher, Guide, or Rule; and in another, <hi>it ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Examining the proofs of Scripture's ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the four <hi>requiſites</hi> to the office. And firſt, in this Chapter [VVhether a <hi>proper</hi> means?]</head>
               <p>TO shew you more manifeſtlie, the falſeneſs of your Tenet, by giving you larger ſcope of proof.</p>
               <p>I named above; four <hi>requiſites</hi> to <hi>the means</hi> we ſpeak of, [<hi>proper, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal, neceſſary, ſufficient.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of therefore if Scripture vvant
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:34171:48"/>
but any one, it cannot poſſibly be it. See, if you can prove, it hath (I do not ſay, <hi>all;</hi> but ſo much as) any <hi>one</hi> of them. And firſt, that it is [<hi>proper</hi> (uſeful, or intended) <hi>to give the firſt instruction.</hi>] Which as it is the firſt, ſo the incomparably principal and moſt neceſſary act of the office of <hi>Teaching,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. <hi>Argu.</hi> Deut. 31.11.</p>
               <p>[Thou shalt read this law afore the children that have not known any thing, that they may hear and learn to fear the Lord.] <hi>Therefore proper to give</hi> no vices <hi>their</hi> firſt <hi>inſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>It follows not. 1. Becauſe this place ſpeaks not of <hi>novices,</hi> but of the <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> ſort of people, young or old. For, thoſe words <hi>[any thing]</hi> are not <hi>Moſes's,</hi> but an addition of your Tranſlators (confeſſed, in ſome editions, by a ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler character,) to help the ſenſe, when they mar it (as they do in divers other places, and inſtead of the H. Ghoſt's, give their own ſenſe for Scripture, which is properly that <hi>adding to it,</hi> as
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:34171:48"/>
is forbidden, and accurſed (<hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.22.) the text being no more then this <hi>[children, &amp;c. that have not known.]</hi> that is, are <hi>ignorant</hi> of the dreadful majeſtie, ſanctity, power, juſtice, and other perfections of God Almighty, and of the great awe and obedience due to him from his creatute, ſet forth in that Book. 2. Nor therefore, by <hi>[learning to fear God,]</hi> did he mean the <hi>firſt,</hi> but the <hi>perfecting</hi> knowledge. And it is the more probable; becauſe this reading of the Law was appointed to be but once in ſeven years; whereas children were to be inſtructed touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God Almighty, aſſoon as two or three year old.</p>
               <p>2. <hi>Argu. Pſal.</hi> 19.7. &amp; 119.30.</p>
               <p>[The law of God gives light to the ſimple, and little ones.]</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>True; but impertinent. For, 1. He doth not name the Scripture, nor (I think) mean it, but <hi>the Goſpel, as preached</hi> by the Church, among the Gentiles, to the converſion of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:34171:49"/>
ſpoken of from the firſt ver. of this Pſalm; S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf being the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter (<hi>Rom.</hi> 10.18.)</p>
               <p n="2">2. Nor, had he meant it, do thoſe <hi>ſimple,</hi> or <hi>little</hi> ones, mean <hi>novices:</hi> but <hi>humble, upright</hi> ſouls; ſuch as <hi>himſelf</hi> was, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 131.11. <hi>Iacob,</hi> (Gen. 25.27.) <hi>Iob,</hi> Iob 1.1. the <hi>Apostles,</hi> Mat. 11.25.) and as all Chriſtians, yea the greateſt Divines in the world, muſt be, ere God reveal his myſteries to them, either by Scripture, or any other means (<hi>Mat.</hi> 18.3. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.)</p>
               <p>3. <hi>Argu.</hi> S. Ioh. 20.31.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[Theſe are written, that ye may believe, that Ieſus is the Christ.]</hi> Implying, his Goſpel was proper to give inſtruction in that point, the <hi>firſt</hi> principle of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith.</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>Short ſtill. For he ſpake not that, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 1. to <hi>novices;</hi> but to Chriſtians <hi>cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed.</hi> 2. or touching any <hi>doctrines,</hi> in his Goſpel; but the <hi>miracles</hi> of Chriſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated in it [<hi>Many other ſigns he did, which are not written; but theſe</hi> (i.e.
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:34171:49"/>
                  <hi>ſigns) are,</hi> &amp;c.] 3. or of <hi>inſtructing</hi> in that point, but <hi>confirming</hi> in the belief of it, [<hi>theſe are written that ye may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
               <p>4. <hi>Argu.</hi> 2 Tim. 3.14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[Timothy knew the Scriptures of a childe]</hi> Sure then, profitable to inſtruct him in his childehood.</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>No doubt, ſingularly profitable; but not to give him his <hi>firſt</hi> inſtruction.</p>
               <p>5. <hi>Argu.</hi> 5. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.13.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Iohn</hi> wrote to <hi>little children.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>Such children as knew the Father; <hi>nay,</hi> needed no man to teach them <hi>the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Catechiſme,</hi> (ver. <hi>20, 27.)</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Examining the proofs for Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's being <hi>a principal</hi> means.</head>
               <p>SEcondly, that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is call'd <hi>[the meanes]</hi> to any end, muſt be the <hi>principal</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:34171:50"/>
means to it (as <hi>principal,</hi> oppoſes <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental.</hi>) Now H. Scripture, we ſay, is a moſt ſuperlatively excellent proper means, and (in its kind) the principal to give the <hi>perfecting</hi> inſtruction: but we will not ſay, it is at all proper to it, as <hi>principal;</hi> that is <hi>of or by it ſelf,</hi> or as in the hand of <hi>any one</hi> (the profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Divine); but only as an <hi>instrument</hi> in the hand of <hi>the Church,</hi> or <hi>one of her Schollars.</hi> As a pen is proper to write; but not as a <hi>principal</hi> means, but as an <hi>inſtrument</hi> onely, in the hand of one that hath ſtrength and skill to uſe and guide it to its end. You ſay, (or muſt renounce your principle) it is <hi>ſelf</hi>-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to this end, as in the hand of any (or every) underſtanding <hi>Christian.</hi> See, if you can prove it.</p>
               <p>1. <hi>Argu.</hi> Deut. 17.19.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[He shall read therein, that he may learn to fear the Lord:]</hi> that is, that by <hi>it,</hi> he may inſtruct and direct himſelf in his duty to God.</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>True, if you underſtand it of the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:34171:50"/>
                  <hi>King</hi> in the diſcharge of his <hi>civil</hi> office. But if you will underſtand it of him as one of the <hi>faithful,</hi> in the diſcharge of his duty to God, in matters of <hi>faith,</hi> and <hi>holineſs;</hi> it was not meant of every, or any one, but one trained up in the true Religion, by or under Orthodox Paſtors.</p>
               <p>2. <hi>Argu.</hi> Deut. 30.11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[This commandment is not hidden from thee, &amp;c.]</hi> Implying, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is not dark to any one, in matters neceſſary.</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>It implies no ſuch thing. For 1. It ſpeaks not of <hi>Scripture;</hi> but of the <hi>words</hi> by him <hi>commanded viva voce.</hi> And ſo was a figure of the Goſpel to be <hi>preached</hi> (Rom. 10.8.) which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is hid to none but the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3.) 2. Grant, he had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of <hi>Scripture;</hi> and by name, of that book of <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> (the plaineſt in the Bible, and conſiſting of nothing els in a maner but <hi>moral</hi> precepts (written in our hearts by the light of nature) exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:34171:51"/>
admonitions, motives, &amp;c. to <hi>piety</hi> and <hi>obedience:</hi>) yet it was ſo unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, yea dangerous, for ignorant peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as it was neither intended for <hi>their</hi> reading, (<hi>Deu.</hi> 31.9.) nor to be ſo much as read <hi>to</hi> them, without an <hi>interpreter</hi> authorized. (<hi>Neh.</hi> 8.7. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17.9. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.22.</p>
               <p>3. <hi>Argu.</hi> Deut. 31.11.</p>
               <p>[<hi>Thou shalt read this law before the people that have not known any thing; that they may learn to fear God,</hi> &amp;c.] Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, it was ſo <hi>ſelf-plain,</hi> as the ſole <hi>hearing</hi> it <hi>read,</hi> was ſufficient to inſtruct ignorant people, in the knowledge and fear of God.</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>No ſuch thing, as appears from what is ſaid in the anſwer laſt afore. And now I shall illuſtrate and confirm it to you, by giving ſome of the reaſons of it in an inſtance. In that Book (of <hi>Deuteronomie</hi>) are ſundry paſſages, moſt admirably ſetting forth the great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of God, for which we ought to fear him; propoſing effectual mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:34171:51"/>
to it, &amp;c. and ſo, moſt excellent proper, to inform and perfect the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or hearer, in that duty. But then withal, there are intermixed ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsions; ſometimes, ſo deſcending to the vulgar capacity (of God's <hi>eyes, hands, anger, glittering ſword,</hi> &amp;c. (Chap. 32.40, 41, &amp;c.) ſometimes ſo <hi>dark</hi> (e.g. <hi>Ieſurun waxed fat; I lift up my hand to heaven,</hi> &amp;c. (Chap. 32.15, 40. &amp;c.) ſometimes ſo repugnant in <hi>words:</hi> (for example, calling God ſometimes by a name of the <hi>ſingular</hi> number, <hi>Iehovah,</hi> as if but one perſon; generally, of the <hi>plural, Elohim,</hi> which your Tranſlators ought to have ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, <hi>Gods,</hi> or <hi>the Gods;</hi>) ſometimes, ſetting him forth, as an infinitely <hi>dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> otherwhiles as an infinitely <hi>gentle</hi> power, &amp;c.) as they would be apt to beget, or confirm, in ignorant people, erroneous apprehenſions of him, &amp; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too <hi>little,</hi> or too <hi>great</hi> a dread of him, unleſs heard or read by one, that had been taught ſome rules for the right underſtanding of them; which
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:34171:52"/>
rules cannot be given with certainty, but by the Church.</p>
               <p>4. <hi>Argu.</hi> Pſal. 19.8. &amp; 119.105.</p>
               <p>[The law of the Lord is a light, enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the eyes of the ſimple.] <hi>Now,</hi> a light, <hi>is a</hi> ſelf-ſufficient (<hi>or</hi> principal) <hi>means, to guide a man in his way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Moſt certain, the Law of God, is (in its <hi>kinde</hi>) a moſt excellent light, yea the <hi>principal</hi> in this world, to guide us (even Church and all) in the way to heaven. But <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks not here of the <hi>Scripture;</hi> nor doth he mean it, <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily;</hi> much leſs <hi>ſolely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Grant he meant it; <hi>light</hi> is not a <hi>ſelf</hi>-ſufficient means to direct a traveler in his way; no, not the <hi>Sun</hi> it ſelf, to one that hath a filme over his eyes, or is ignorant of his way, or is drunk, or mad; but shall light him as well out of his way, as into it; yea, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of his way, shall light him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a pit to break his neck. Now ſuch men, with a filme over their eyes, are all not inſtructed in Religion
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:34171:52"/>
by the Church; and ſuch drunk or mad men, are all pertinacious Sectaries.</p>
               <p>5. <hi>Argu.</hi> Pſal. 199.99.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have more underſtanding then all my Teachers; for thy Teſtimonies are my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation.</hi>] Implying, that a man, by ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying the Scripture, may come to more knowledge in divine things, then is in his Teachers; and conſequently, to underſtand Scripture better then they, and therefore without their help.</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>It implies no ſuch thing. For 1. He ſpake not of the <hi>Scripture;</hi> nor perhaps meant it. 2. Nor did he perhaps ſpeak this of himſelf, in quality of a <hi>Believer;</hi> but of a <hi>Prophet</hi> (taught by <hi>inſpiration.</hi>) 3. Nor did he prefer his underſtanding, to <hi>all</hi> Teachers, but to all <hi>his.</hi> 4. Nor did he perhaps ſpeak of wiſdom <hi>ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative,</hi> but <hi>practical</hi> or <hi>experimental</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: wherein many times, ſimple peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by devout meditation, and ferve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous practice of what is taught them by the Church, or read by them in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, come to exceed their Teachers.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:34171:53"/>6. <hi>Argu.</hi> S. Luke 10.26.</p>
               <p>When one demanded of our Saviour the way to heaven, he ſent him to the <hi>Scripture [How is it written? How read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou?]</hi> Implying; that it by it ſelf alone, is enough to shew any reader of it, the way to heaven.</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>Still wide. For, that <hi>one,</hi> did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the way, <hi>abſolutely</hi> (whereof him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was a Teacher;) but that <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, new, perfecter</hi> way, as Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to teach: which favour he not thinking him worthy of, ſent him to <hi>Moſes, whoſe diſciple he was</hi> (Ioh. 9.28.) And in the ſame manner, he did at firſt with the other <hi>Phariſee,</hi> that came to him with the ſame queſtion (<hi>Mar.</hi> 10.19.) but when by his anſwer he ſaw cauſe to <hi>love</hi> him, he taught him the <hi>perfect</hi> way to happineſs, as he did <hi>Nicodemus</hi> (at <hi>firſt</hi> asking) the <hi>neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> (Ioh. 3.3.) by his <hi>new</hi> Law: and without ſending either of them to the Scripture for either way; where indeed it was not to be found.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:34171:53"/>7. <hi>Argu.</hi> S. Luke 16.29.</p>
               <p>When <hi>the glutton</hi> in hell begged of <hi>Abraham</hi> a <hi>Teacher</hi> from the dead, for his brethren on earth, the anſwer was <hi>[They have Moſes and the Prophets; let them hear them.]</hi> Implying, Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture alone, was a means proper to teach them piety ſufficient to eſcape hell.</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>Not a tittle to any ſuch ſenſe. For</p>
               <p n="1">1. He begged not a <hi>Teacher,</hi> but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>witneſs</hi> to the doctrine of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue touching the grievouſneſs of hell-torments, &amp;c. nor therefore did <hi>Abraham</hi> remit them to <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> as <hi>Teachers;</hi> but onely as <hi>witneſſes,</hi> more competent, then he who was deſired <hi>(a Ghoſt from the dead.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Nor, by <hi>[Moſes and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets]</hi> did he perhaps mean their <hi>wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,</hi> but the <hi>Teachers</hi> then living upon earth: thoſe in <hi>ordinary</hi> (ſitting in his Chair) by <hi>Moſes;</hi> thoſe in <hi>extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary</hi> (which that Nation was ſeldom
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:34171:54"/>
without) by <hi>the Prophets.</hi> And it is the more probable; 1. Becauſe it were more proper, where a living witneſs was deſired, to ſend them to a living witneſs, more credible then the other. 2. Becauſe it is improper to ſay of <hi>wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings</hi> [Let them <hi>hear</hi> them.]</p>
               <p n="3">3. Grant, he meant the <hi>Scripture,</hi> and as a means of <hi>instruction;</hi> yet not as <hi>read,</hi> much leſs, <hi>interpreted,</hi> by the <hi>people;</hi> but as read, and interpreted to them, by their <hi>Paſtors.</hi> Therefore he ſaid [Let them <hi>hear</hi> them.]</p>
               <p>8. <hi>Argu.</hi> S. Ioh. 5.39.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[Search the Scriptures: they are they that teſtifie of me.]</hi> As who should ſay [They are the proper, principal, ſufficient means to teach people Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.]</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>Far from any ſuch ſenſe. For 1. He ſpake not this to the <hi>people;</hi> but the <hi>Teachers</hi> (as you will ſee anon, <hi>cap.</hi> 6. §. 1. <hi>argu.</hi> 6.) 2. Nor perhaps did he ſay to them <hi>[Search,]</hi> but <hi>[you do ſearch;]</hi> the Greek word, being indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:34171:54"/>
to either; and the later as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the ſcope and coherence of the Text, as the former, 3. Nor did he ſend any to it, as a <hi>Teacher</hi> of any thing, but onely as a <hi>witneſſe</hi> to his <hi>perſon.</hi> 4. Nor as <hi>the proper, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal, neceſſary, or ſufficient</hi> witneſs (for, thoſe he had newly afore urged, <hi>ver.</hi> 35, &amp;c.) but as a witneſs, he was <hi>compelled</hi> to, by their obſtinacy to the other, and eſteem of it. <hi>[Him whom the Father hath ſent, ye believe not. Search the Scriptures; for in them ye think, &amp;c.]</hi> 5. Nor did he ſend them to it, by <hi>it ſelf</hi> alone; but (as his maner was, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.27, 32, 45,) <hi>alledged</hi> the texts, and <hi>opened</hi> them. 6, Nay nor then neither, were they a teſtimony ſufficient to weigh againſt <hi>thoſe,</hi> brought by his adverſaries, out of the ſame Scripture, to the contrary; without putting into the ſcale, <hi>the authority of his perſon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter</hi> (as you will ſee anon, <hi>par.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 4. §. 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:34171:55"/>9. <hi>Argu.</hi> Acts 18.28.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[Apollos mightily convinced the Iews; shewing by the Scriptures, that Ieſus was Chriſt.]</hi> He, a lay-man, by ſcripture alone, convinced, shewed, or made clear, even to infidels, the firſt, &amp; one of the higheſt myſteries of Chriſtian faith: much more could he shew it to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and if that point, any other.</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>An argument ſomewhat ſpecious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but wanting ſoliditie. For 1. Though a <hi>lay-man;</hi> yet he had been taught by the Church, how to <hi>alledge, and open the Scripture</hi> to that point. 3. His <hi>convincing,</hi> or <hi>shewing,</hi> meant no more, then bringing proofs, or ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments for it; for we do not read he converted anie: and it is certain, not <hi>all</hi> that he diſputed with. 3. It was not poſsible for him to prove by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (there ſpoken of) more then one of his propoſitions. For, his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the old Scripture could be no other, but this [<hi>Chriſt, was to ſuffer death, and riſe again,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ieſus hath
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:34171:55"/>
ſuffered death, is riſen again,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is Chriſt.</hi>] The former propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he was able to convince by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; the later not.</p>
               <p>10. <hi>Argu.</hi> Rom. 15.4.</p>
               <p>[VVhat things were written, were written for our learning] <hi>or inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>Moſt certain, and are ſingularly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to that end in the hand of <hi>an Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Teacher,</hi> alledging and interpreting them (in their right ſenſe) unto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as he did then to them.</p>
               <p>11. <hi>Argu.</hi> 2 Cor. 4.3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[If our Goſpel be hid, it is hid to them that perish.]</hi> As much as to ſay [Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is plain to all but reprobates.]</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He ſpake not, nor dreamt of <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> but of the Goſpel <hi>preached</hi> by the Church. 2. Grant, he ſpake of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; he meant it as <hi>preached by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, Silvanus,</hi> and <hi>Timothy,</hi> their Paſtors. Conſequently, no wilful Proteſtant, or other Sectary whatever, to whom the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:34171:56"/>
Scripture as <hi>preached to him by his pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent lawful Paſtors, is hid;</hi> may hope of himſelf, that he is one of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinate, if he dye in that ſtate of ſoul.</p>
               <p>12. <hi>Argu.</hi> 2 Tim. 3.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[The Scriptures are able to make thee wiſe to ſalvation.]</hi> Spoken to <hi>Timothy,</hi> as a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> to encourage him to be diligent in reading them, as a means proper by it ſelf alone, to inſtruct him in Religion, ſufficiently to his ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>Not a ſyllable in it to any ſuch purpoſe. For 1. He ſpake not to him as a <hi>meer</hi> Chriſtian; but as a <hi>Catholick,</hi> trained up in the Church under himſelf (<hi>v.</hi> 14.) 2. Nor perhaps did he here incourage him to <hi>reading</hi> the Scripture, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>continue firm in the things</hi> himſelf <hi>had taught him</hi> out of it; not ſo much for the evidence of their conſonancy with it, as for the authority of his <hi>perſon,</hi> the interpreter [<hi>knowing of whom thou haſt learned them,</hi> v. 14.] 3. Nor there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:34171:56"/>
did he recommend it to him, as an <hi>inſtructer</hi> in Chriſtian faith, but as a <hi>witneſs</hi> to it. 4. Nor therefore did he ſay <hi>[wiſe to ſalvation] abſolutely;</hi> as if ſalvation were attainable by the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and belief of the Scriptures there ſpoken of; but <hi>[wiſe to ſalvation by faith in Chriſt:]</hi> that is, by <hi>confirming</hi> and <hi>perfecting</hi> you, in Chriſts faith. And ſo <hi>[wiſe to ſalvation,]</hi> means no more then <hi>[wiſe, in ſaving wiſdom.]</hi> Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, the uttermoſt ſenſe of this place is no more then this <hi>[The old Scriptures are able to make a Catholick, wiſe in ſaving wiſdom, by confirming, or improving him in faith:]</hi> which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to what you are to prove.</p>
               <p>13. <hi>Argu.</hi> 2. Tim. 3.16.</p>
               <p>[All Scripture is profitable for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, &amp;c.]</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>Superlatively, beyond all that can be ſaid of it, by tongues of men or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; (being <hi>given,</hi> to that end, <hi>by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration from an infinite VViſedome.</hi>)</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:34171:57"/>But it makes nothing to your pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. For</p>
               <p n="1">1. He doth not ſay <hi>[ſufficient.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. No, nor <hi>[ſelf-profitable.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. No [<hi>nor profitable in the hand of every Chriſtian,</hi> no nor <hi>of every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Divine,</hi> ſuppoſe him the profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ever lived:] but of <hi>[the man of God;]</hi> that is, <hi>the Orthodox</hi> or <hi>Catholick</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, or Teacher. For 1. That by <hi>[the man of God]</hi> he meant not a meer <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> or <hi>believer;</hi> is manifeſt 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that name is never found in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, uſed of any but in whom there was ſome higher excellency then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary. 2. Becauſe it was a <hi>proper</hi> name, in that Nation, of <hi>Prophets</hi> (1 Sam. 2.27. &amp; 9, 6, &amp;c.) 3. Becauſe <hi>Timothy</hi> to whom he then wrote this, was a Paſtor; and called by him, by this name [<hi>thou, O man of God,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.11.] 4. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all theſe works, here named, as to which it is profitable <hi>[doctrine, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, correction, and inſtruction]</hi> are the proper works of a <hi>Divine,</hi> or <hi>Preacher.</hi> 2. That he meant a <hi>Catholick</hi> Divine, is
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:34171:57"/>
as certain. For, a <hi>Heretick,</hi> he would never call <hi>[a man of God]</hi> but a limb, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, or factor of the Devil (<hi>Gal.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.10, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.9, 15.)</p>
               <p n="4">4. Grant, by that name, he meant a <hi>lay-Chriſtian;</hi> yet not any other but a <hi>Catholick</hi> one; for the Scripture would be far from calling <hi>a heretick, a man of God;</hi> which alone is enough to render this place of no uſe to you.</p>
               <p>13. <hi>Argu.</hi> 2 Pet. 1.19.</p>
               <p>[To which you do well to take heed as to a light, &amp;c.]</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the hand of your Paſtors,</hi> alledging, and expounding it to you [<hi>we</hi> have a light, to which <hi>you</hi> do well to take heed.]</p>
               <p>14. <hi>Argu.</hi> Apoc. 1.3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[Bleſſed is he that reads this Book.]</hi> Sure then profitable, in the hand of any Chriſtian reader, to inſtruct and guide him, to his ſouls health.</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>No ſuch thing. For</p>
               <p n="1">1. I do not think he ſpake here of
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:34171:58"/>
                  <hi>lay</hi>-Chriſtians, but the <hi>Paſtor</hi> of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Churches to whom that Epiſtle was directed (<hi>Chap..</hi> 2.1, &amp;c.) and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately delivered, for him to <hi>read</hi> it himſelf, and <hi>preach</hi> it to the people. My reaſon is; 1. Becauſe it was fit, <hi>he</hi> should have his encouragement as well as the <hi>people.</hi> 2. Becauſe the <hi>people,</hi> in quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>hearers,</hi> are ſpoken of in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry next words, in the <hi>plural</hi> number <hi>[He that reads; and they that hear.]</hi> Now let him that ſaith, in both places he meant the <hi>people;</hi> give a reaſon, why he should ſo ſuddenly change the number. 3. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when none of the writers, nor he himſelf, encouraged the people, to the reading of any Book of Scripture (as we shal ſee anon) rather diſcouraged (&amp; namely from S. <hi>Pauls Epiſtles</hi>) by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome things in it hard to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16.) I cannot think it likely he would encourage them to the reading of <hi>this,</hi> of leaſt uſe, and more abounding with things hard to be underſtood, and eaſie to be wreſted by them to their damnation, then any
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:34171:58"/>
one of S. <hi>Pauls Epiſtles;</hi> or any other Book in Scripture.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Grant he meant <hi>lay-Chriſtians;</hi> yet not <hi>any</hi> (or <hi>every</hi>) one; not a <hi>Nicolai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> (Apoc. 2.6.) not one of <hi>Diotrephes</hi> Congregation (3 <hi>Io.</hi> 9.) for certainly ſuch a one would read it but to his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er damnation: but ſuch a one as was under his <hi>Angel</hi> (or Catholick Paſtor) whoſe <hi>hearer</hi> he was, as well as its <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> Bleſſed are <hi>ſuch</hi> readers of it: woe to others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Examining the proofs for the <hi>neceſsity</hi> of Scripture.</head>
               <p>THirdly, nothing can be called <hi>[the means]</hi> to any end, to which it is not (ſimply) <hi>neceſſary.</hi> See then if you can prove, that H. Scripture is ſimply <hi>neceſſary</hi> to the teaching of Religion: <hi>viz.</hi> either that there was any neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for its writing (more then neceſsity of <hi>command,</hi> for ſome few pieces of the Old Teſtament, and the <hi>Apocalipſe,</hi> in the New, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.10.) or that ſince its
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:34171:59"/>
writing, Religion cannot be taught, or ſubſiſt, without it.</p>
               <p>1. <hi>Argu.</hi> 2 Pet. 1.20.</p>
               <p>Holy men of old, wrote as they were moved, &amp;c.]</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>True: but <hi>moving,</hi> is not <hi>command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. <hi>Argu.</hi> S. Iude 3.</p>
               <p>[It was needful for me to write.]</p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>But 1. <hi>Needful</hi> is short of <hi>neceſſary.</hi> 2. Nor did he mean needful <hi>abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;</hi> but onely that, reſolving to write, he ſaw it needful to write to them, <hi>to that end,</hi> or <hi>of that ſubject [to exhort them to contend earneſtly, &amp;c.]</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Examining the proofs for Scripture's being ſufficient.</head>
               <p>FInally, nothing can be called <hi>[the means]</hi> to any end, but it muſt be <hi>ſufficient</hi> to it. Which, Scripture can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſsibly be, to the teaching of the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:34171:59"/>
Goſpel, unleſs it contain <hi>expreſſely</hi> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular of it. I think it vain to ſay <hi>[importing to ſalvation,]</hi> becauſe, <hi>the Goſpel</hi> can conſiſt of none but do ſo, in ſome kinde or other.</p>
               <p>I ſay <hi>[expreſly:]</hi> becauſe els, there will need ſome other means <hi>with authority</hi> (for as good none at all, as not w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                  <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi>) to deduce the inferences, &amp; apply the general rules or examples of it to particular doubts or caſes (which is the main part of the office of teaching;) and ſo it could not deſerve to be called <hi>[the means.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If then you think H. Scripture does not contain every particular of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel expreſſely; renounce your prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple. If you think it do; ſee, if you can prove it.</p>
               <p>1. <hi>Argu.</hi> S. Luke 1.3. Acts 1.1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S.</hi> Luke <hi>calls his Goſpel</hi> [a Treatiſe of all things, that Ieſus taught, or were believed among Christians.] <hi>And</hi> the Goſpel <hi>cannot conſiſt of more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Yes, it may; namely, of thoſe as
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:34171:60"/>
are in S. <hi>Iohn's</hi> Goſpel, or Epiſtles (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed long after S. <hi>Lukes</hi> death.) 2. Grant it did not; he did not mean <hi>[all]</hi> in <hi>proper,</hi> or <hi>logical</hi> ſenſe, for <hi>all abſolutely:</hi> but in <hi>vulgar</hi> ſenſe onely, for, the <hi>generality, greater,</hi> or <hi>notable</hi> part (uſual in Scripture, and particularly in him, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.14, 27. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.19. &amp; 2. 12. &amp; 3.11, &amp;c.) it being evident, he wants divers particulars, that are in the other Evangeliſts, and ſome of them of the moſt fundamental in Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; namely [<hi>the divinity of Chriſt, the number and names of the perſons in the Godhead;</hi> the inſtitution of the two Sacraments of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</hi>]</p>
               <p>2 <hi>Argu.</hi> 2 Tim. 3.16, 17.</p>
               <p>[Scripture is profitable, for doctrine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that the man of God may be perfect, throughly furnished to every good work.] <hi>Therefore it contains expreſly every particular of the Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwer.</p>
               <p>A very weak inference: there being a great diſtance; 1. betwixt every <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:34171:60"/>
of the Goſpel,</hi> and <hi>every good work</hi> (which are but a <hi>part</hi> of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.) 2. betwixt every good work <hi>abſolutely;</hi> and every good work, <hi>of the ſorts there ſpoken of,</hi> pertaining to a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, <hi>viz doctrine, correction,</hi> &amp;c. 3. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>profitable to furnish for them;</hi> and <hi>containing them expreſſely.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Examining the proof of things leſs yet.</head>
               <p>VVHat do I ſpeak of proving ſuch things <hi>as theſe?</hi> See, if you can prove but ſo much as any of <hi>theſe that follow:</hi> namely.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 1.</hi> From Old or New Teſtament.</head>
                  <p>n. 1.</p>
                  <p>That God Almighty ever ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or expreſſed any intent, the <hi>lay</hi> people should <hi>read</hi> the Bible, or <hi>have it</hi> to read in, if they pleaſed, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct themſelves in Religion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:34171:61"/>1. <hi>Argu.</hi> Deut. 6.7.</p>
                  <p>[Thou shalt write theſe words upon thy walls, teach them thy children, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>Nothing to the purpoſe. For 1. He doth not ſpeak of (or mean perhaps) words <hi>written,</hi> but <hi>commanded</hi> by him. 2. Grant, words <hi>written;</hi> he doth not ſay <hi>[thou shalt read them.]</hi> If you ſay, he meant it; give a reaſon, why then he should not name it, as well as he named the other <hi>[teaching, meditating, writing:]</hi> and as well as he named it with the other, when he ſpake of the Law, as to be uſed by <hi>the chief Ruler</hi> (Deut. 17.19. Ioſ. 1.8.) Nor can you ſay, he neceſſarily implyed it in thoſe commands, of <hi>writing, teaching,</hi> and <hi>meditating</hi> on it: for they might be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed (ſufficiently to their intent) as now they are, by pious Catholicks, without <hi>reading</hi> it; namely, by being taught the commandments, and other the principal parts of Gods Law, moſt uſeful for them, by the Prieſts (<hi>Exod.</hi> 24.12. <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.9, 19.21.)</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:34171:61"/>2. <hi>Argu.</hi> Deut. 27.3.</p>
                  <p>[Thou shalt ſet up great stones, and write upon them all the words of this law, plainly.] <hi>Sure, to the end people should read them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>It may be ſo. But it expreſſes no ſuch intent. It doth this, and thats all it expreſſes, that it should there remain as a <hi>witneſs.</hi> Nor is it likely that he meant the whole book of <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> (much leſs; <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Pentateuch;</hi>) for, what a wall would that ask? ſure, longer then that hill <hi>Ebal,</hi> could contain: but onely the <hi>ten Commandments,</hi> with perhaps ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moral precepts, admonitions, and exhortations, moſt uſeful for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and needing no interpreter; and the <hi>bleſsings</hi> on the obedient, <hi>curſes</hi> on the tranſgreſſors (<hi>Ioſ.</hi> 8.34.) Now ſuch a writing, in that manner ſet forth, is a different thing from the Bible: H. Church at this day, permitting people the one, in <hi>Primars,</hi> &amp;c. when she will not the other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="120" facs="tcp:34171:62"/>3. <hi>Argu.</hi> Deut. 31.9.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Moſes</hi> delivered the Law into the hand of the <hi>Elders,</hi> as well as the Prieſts. Sure, vvith intent they should read it.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>Very likely: but not as to inſtruct themſelves in <hi>Religion,</hi> but to guide themſelves by it in <hi>judicature,</hi> as it contained the <hi>Civil</hi> Law of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>4. <hi>Argu.</hi> Eſa. 24.16.</p>
                  <p>[Seek ye out of the Book of the Lord, and read, &amp;c.] <hi>Spoken to the</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It may be, not. 2. Grant it; it names not, nor perhaps meant, <hi>the Bible;</hi> nor any Book, as <hi>to inſtruction</hi> in <hi>Religion;</hi> but onely ſome <hi>Prophecy</hi> then written, touching the <hi>Captivity,</hi> or ſome other future <hi>temporal</hi> cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; (proper to that Nation, and age.)</p>
                  <p>5. <hi>Argu.</hi> S. Mat 12.3.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>[Have ye not read, &amp;c.]</hi> Spoken by
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:34171:62"/>
our Saviour to the people; there, and elſe where often.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Never once; but to <hi>Teachers</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and <hi>as</hi> ſuch. And one reaſon I have for ſaying ſo, is becauſe when a <hi>lay</hi> Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee demanded of him the way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, he ſent him not to the <hi>Scripture,</hi> (as he did the <hi>Lawyer,</hi> Luk. 10.26.) but to his <hi>Catechiſm [Thou knoweſt the Commandments,</hi> Mar. 10.19.]</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Grant, ſpoken to the <hi>people;</hi> it <hi>ſuppoſes</hi> they <hi>did,</hi> expreſſes no <hi>intent</hi> they <hi>should</hi> read it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Argu.</hi> 6. S. Ioh. 5.39.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>[Search the Scriptures.]</hi> Plainly expreſsing intent the people should read them.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>No ſuch thing. For 1. It is not certain be ſpake to the <hi>people:</hi> nay, it is probable that not to <hi>them,</hi> but to the <hi>Rulers.</hi> My reaſon is, becauſe he ſpake it to thoſe (<hi>v.</hi> 10.) who had (perhaps) <hi>convented</hi> afore them (for certain) pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:34171:63"/>
                     <hi>rebuked</hi> the man for carrying his bed on the Sabbath day, and examined him touching his author or counſellor; to whom he ſubmiſſively gave the beſt account he then could of who it was; and as ſoon as he knew, went to give them a better; who thereupon proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted our Saviour for his life. All which look like proceedings of men <hi>fitting in Moſes Chair:</hi> nor is it to the contrary, that they are there called bare <hi>[the Iews:]</hi> for, by that name, this Evangeliſt often without queſtion meant <hi>them in authority</hi> (Ioh. 4.19. &amp; 9.21, &amp; 18.12.) 2. Grant, ſpoken to the <hi>people;</hi> perhaps he ſaid not to them, as your Tranſlators render it, <hi>[Search;]</hi> but onely <hi>[you do ſearch.]</hi> For the Original is indifferent to either ſenſe; and the later as agreeable to the ſcope and coherence of the Text, as the former. 3. Grant the ſpeech as you render it <hi>[ſearch:]</hi> it doth not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily infer their <hi>reading</hi> it: becauſe they might ſearch <hi>by their Prieſts,</hi> in their copy. And it is the more poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:34171:63"/>
becauſe <hi>the Bible</hi> was then a Book of too coſtly a price for the ordinary peoples purſe to purchaſe.</p>
                  <p>7. <hi>Argu.</hi> Acts 8.28.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Enuch</hi> reading Scripture, is ſet forth for an example.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>Perhaps not, no more then his ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den embracing a new Religion, upon no more prudencial motives then are ſet down; eſpecially when (ſuppoſing it true as you hold) he had <hi>no ground in Gods word,</hi> for his reading it.</p>
                  <p>8. <hi>Argu.</hi> Acts 17.11.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Bereans</hi> (at leaſt) are <hi>expreſſely</hi> commended for it.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It may be, not (<hi>vid. ſupra par.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>ob.</hi> 6.) 2. Grant they were; it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, other people, in ſuch a caſe as that was, lawfully may do the ſame; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes no intent they should, no more then the commending of <hi>Solomon</hi> for building ſuch a magnificent Temple; <hi>David,</hi> for intending it. 3. Grant <hi>that</hi> alſo; their <hi>ſearching</hi> it, doth not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſarilie
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:34171:64"/>
include their <hi>reading</hi> it, no more then the King's <hi>writing</hi> a copie of it, doth the writing it <hi>himſelf</hi> (Deu. 17.19.) See, what is ſaid in the anſwer above to the 6. <hi>Arg.</hi> § 3.</p>
                  <p>9. <hi>Argu.</hi> Rom. 15.4.</p>
                  <p>[Scripture was written for our inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.]</p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>Moſt certain. But ſtrange, if written for the peoples <hi>reading,</hi> it should never tell them ſo.</p>
                  <p>10. <hi>Argu.</hi> 2 Cor. 1.13. Eph. 3.4.</p>
                  <p>[VVhereby when ye read, &amp;c.] <hi>Spoken to the</hi> people.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Perhaps not; no more then divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things in the Epiſtles are (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.27.) but to the <hi>Paſtors</hi> (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlie.) And as is ordinarie, in writing to a community, to ſay [when <hi>you</hi> read this] when none is meant properlie, or in his own perſon, but the <hi>Clerk,</hi> or, other, <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer,</hi> to the Companie. 2. Grant, to the <hi>people;</hi> it <hi>implies a ſuppoſal</hi> they did, or would; <hi>expreſſes no intent,</hi> they should read it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="125" facs="tcp:34171:64"/>
                     <hi>Argu.</hi> 11. Col. 4.16.</p>
                  <p>[Read the Epiſtle from Laodicea.]</p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>Spoken to the <hi>Paſtor,</hi> to <hi>cauſe it to be read among the people,</hi> or, <hi>in the Church;</hi> as he ſaid in the vvords a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
                  <p>12. <hi>Argu.</hi> 2 Ioh. 1.</p>
                  <p>At leaſt, the Lady <hi>Elect,</hi> was to read the Epiſtle to her written.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>No doubt, it was ſo intended. But little to your purpoſe. For 1. She was but <hi>one</hi> perſon, and a perſon to whom <hi>in particular</hi> it was written; nor is there any intimation of intent she should give a copie of it, or impart it to any other. 2. Nor vvas it then, <hi>a part of the Bible.</hi> 3. Nor did it contain any <hi>doctrinal</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, further then by way of <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition</hi> or <hi>motive</hi> to beware of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>n.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>That God Almighty ordained, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed any intent, there should be any copy (or <hi>tranſcript</hi>) of any one ſacred
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:34171:65"/>
book (more then, that <hi>the King of the Iews,</hi> when there should be one, should have a copy of <hi>Moſes Law,</hi> Deut. 17.18.)</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>n.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p>That God Almighty ordained, or expreſſed any intent, H. Scripture, or any part of it, should be ſo much as read <hi>to</hi> the people; more then the book of <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> once in 7 years (namely, in the year of <hi>Iubilee,</hi> Deut. 31.9.) once a piece of <hi>Ieremy,</hi> exhorting to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and denouncing miſeries elſe to come upon them (<hi>Ier.</hi> 36.6.) once the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> to them (1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.27.) <hi>that,</hi> to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſians,</hi> to them, and the <hi>Laodiceans;</hi> and that from <hi>Laodicea,</hi> to the <hi>Coloſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> (Col. 4.16.)</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 2.</hi> From the Old Teſtament.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>n.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>That in 700. years together (<hi>viz.</hi> from <hi>Ioſuah's</hi> reading it (<hi>Ioſ.</hi> 8.34.) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til <hi>Ioſiah's</hi> (2 Chron. 34.30.) any part of the Scripture (more then once, the piece of <hi>Ieremy</hi> abovementioned) was
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:34171:65"/>
ever read to the people; or the Prieſts ever blamed for neglecting it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Argu.</hi> 2 Chron. 17.9.</p>
                  <p>It was read to them in <hi>Iehoſaphat's</hi> time.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>Like enough. But the text faith not ſo: and our trial now is by <hi>expreſſe</hi> Text.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>n.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>That there was in that Nation, any copy (more then the <hi>original</hi> one, in the Temple) of any one Sacred Book.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Argu.</hi> 2 Chro. 17.9.</p>
                  <p>Was not that a <hi>copy,</hi> as the Prieſts in <hi>Iehoſaphat's</hi> time carried about with them?</p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>It may be ſo: but perhaps not.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 3.</hi> From the Prophets.</head>
                  <p>That any one of them foreſaw, that any one title of the Goſpel should be written.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Argu. Ezek.</hi> 1.5.</p>
                  <p>Your ſelf will ſay, <hi>Ezekiels</hi> four Beaſts, preſignifying the four Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:34171:66"/>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>I will not ſay, it is certain. And though I would; our trial is now by <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs</hi> Text.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§ 4.</hi> From the New Teſtament.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>n.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>That anie lay-Chriſtian, ever read a word in the Bible.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Argu.</hi> 1. Acts 17.11.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Bereans</hi> did.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>But they were <hi>(then)</hi> no Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p>2. <hi>Argu.</hi> 1 Cor. 1.13.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Corinthians</hi> did.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>It may be not (See <hi>ſup. anſ.</hi> to 10. <hi>arg.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3. <hi>Argu.</hi> 2 Pet. 3.16.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe did, that wreſted it to their damnation.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Perhaps, thoſe were <hi>Teachers.</hi> 2. If <hi>people;</hi> they might do <hi>that,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>reading it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>n.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>That our B. Saviour, or anie Apoſtle,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:34171:66"/>
took anie care or order, for the means neceſſarie to the reading of Scripture by the people; namelie, preſerving the Original, or ſome Authentical Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie of it; tranſcribing, and diſperſing copies of it throughout the world, tranſlating it into vulgar languages, compiling the pieces of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (written ſtraglinglie, ſome in one Countrie, ſome in another, 500 miles aſunder) into ſome one volume, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§ 5.</hi> From the Goſpels.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>n.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>That our B. <hi>Lord,</hi> ever <hi>ſpake word</hi> touching H. <hi>Scripture,</hi> unto anie <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> (more then to bring proofs out of it to his incredulous Diſciples, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.27, 44.) or as to anie uſe wherein it was to be, <hi>after his aſcenſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Argu.</hi> S. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.39.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>[Search the Scripture,]</hi> Was not that ſpoken to <hi>Chriſtians?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>No, but to <hi>Infidel</hi>-Iews, and <hi>as</hi> ſuch;
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:34171:67"/>
as appears by the words immediately afore, and after <hi>[you believe not in me, you will not come to me;]</hi> and by the <hi>end,</hi> for which he ſent them to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, namely, to bring them to <hi>faith.</hi> Conſequently, neither ſpoken, nor meant to any properly, or neceſſarily, but <hi>infidel Iews.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>n.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>That he ever <hi>intended,</hi> or <hi>foreſaw</hi> (otherwiſe then as he was God) that, <hi>any one tittle of his Goſpel should</hi> ever <hi>be written.</hi> (And pray note this well.)</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 6.</hi> From the Acts.</head>
                  <p>That any Apoſtle <hi>wrote,</hi> or <hi>intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> or <hi>knew</hi> of, or <hi>foreſaw</hi> the writing of, any one ſyllable of the Goſpel.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 7.</hi> From the Epiſtles.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>n.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>That any Apoſtle, at his death, knew there was any tittle of the Goſpel then written, more then by himſelf (except that S. <hi>Peter</hi> knew of ſome of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.) or to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:34171:67"/>
                     <hi>Argu.</hi> 2 Cor. 8.18.</p>
                  <p>S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of S. <hi>Luke,</hi> as famous then for his Goſpel, throughout Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
                  <p>It is certain he <hi>ſpake</hi> not of, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps <hi>meant</hi> not, either S. <hi>Luke,</hi> or his <hi>Goſpel,</hi> or any <hi>written</hi> Goſpel: but ſome companion of his (<hi>Silas, Barnabas,</hi> or ſome other) famous for his zeal and painfulneſs in <hi>preaching.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>n.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>That he that dyed laſt of them (S. <hi>Iohn</hi>) left, at his death, any ſuch vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume, as is now called [<hi>the Bible,</hi> or <hi>New Teſtament:</hi>] or any two Books of the New Teſtament in one volume, yea, or in one Countrey (except where two Eptſtles were written to one Church or perſon:) or any <hi>original,</hi> yea, or <hi>(perfectly)</hi> authentical copy, of any one book, of Old, or New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. If you can prove none of theſe; you cannot but ſee how far you are, from any hope or likelihood, of proving any ſuch thing as your principle.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:34171:68"/>
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:34171:68"/>
            <head>THE FOVRTH PART: Confuting the Proteſtant Tenet.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Vrging the firſt argument,</hi> [The ſilence of Scripture.]</head>
               <p>I Hope you ſee, how far the Scripture is from affirming your tenet. Which you wil not wonder at, when you shal ſee how much may be ſaid out of it, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it: which is my next, and laſt work.</p>
               <p>I ſay then, it is againſt reaſon, to think, Scripture was left for <hi>[the means of teaching the Goſpel.]</hi> My reaſons are ſix.</p>
               <p>The firſt; becauſe (as appears by the former part) <hi>it affirmes no ſuch
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:34171:69"/>
thing touching it ſelf.</hi> For though a <hi>negative</hi> argument from it <hi>(not in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, therefore not true)</hi> be not <hi>alwayes</hi> good; its always good <hi>againſt you</hi> (who uſe it as good againſt us;) and in <hi>ſuch a tenet</hi> as this of yours (condemned by the Church;) and in <hi>ſuch a point</hi> as this (the moſt fundamental in Religion.)</p>
               <p>This ſilence, if it be well conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, will appear ſo ſtrange to any ration<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al man, as he cannot imagine it poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, had your tenet been true.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>Conſiderations aggravating the ſilence</head>
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 1.</hi> Of the Prophets.</head>
                  <p>Firſt, the ſilence of the <hi>Prophets</hi> is very ſtrange. For</p>
                  <p n="1">1. There is not any <hi>eminent</hi> particular pertaining to the <hi>exterior</hi> form of the Church, but we may finde it <hi>foretold,</hi> in ſome one or other of them: and ſome, very plainly, and in divers of them; this, touching <hi>the means of teaching the Goſpel</hi> (according to our opinion) in almoſt every one of them; and to ſome
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:34171:69"/>
                     <hi>minute</hi> circumſtances (<hi>when</hi> it was to begin, in <hi>what</hi> City, in what <hi>part</hi> of the City, in what <hi>manner,</hi> and by what <hi>means</hi> to <hi>ſpread</hi> over the world, <hi>how long</hi> to continue, &amp;c.) ſtrange, if Scripture were to be it, it should never be ſo much as mentioned.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And yet how <hi>many,</hi> how <hi>just</hi> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions were there for mentioning it, if to be as you ſay? namely, when, they name the <hi>School,</hi> the <hi>maſter,</hi> the <hi>word,</hi> or <hi>Law</hi> of God, yea, the <hi>Goſpel</hi> (though by your Tranſlators, rendred profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>good tidings:</hi>) Eſa. 40.9. compared with <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15. when <hi>Ieremy</hi> came ſo near the <hi>Scripture,</hi> as to promiſe the <hi>writing</hi> of the <hi>new</hi> Law; and to name, by <hi>whom, with,</hi> and in <hi>what</hi> it was to be written. But then indeed he ſaith, it was not to be, by any <hi>creature,</hi> or with <hi>ink,</hi> or in any <hi>material</hi> tables (much leſs, <hi>stony</hi> ones) as the <hi>old</hi> was; but in a more excellent way (befitting a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Law) by <hi>God</hi> himſelf, with <hi>grace,</hi> in the <hi>hearts,</hi> of the <hi>Pastors,</hi> teaching it from hand to hand, of the <hi>people,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving it, <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.31.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="136" facs="tcp:34171:70"/>3. Again, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> in his eight laſt Chapters, deſcribing at large the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and perfection of <hi>the Church</hi> (whoſe glory was to exceed that of the <hi>Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue,</hi> Agg. 2.9.) names all the eminent particulars wherein it was to conſiſt, under the name of their <hi>types</hi> in the Temple of <hi>Solomon:</hi> and among the reſt, her <hi>Paſtors,</hi> very largely, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, under the name of <hi>Sadoc, and his ſons,</hi> Ezek. 44.15, &amp;c. But upon all the <hi>liſt,</hi> we finde not the <hi>tables of Moſes Law:</hi> albeit that was one of the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſeſt <hi>jewels</hi> of the <hi>Temple</hi> (1 King. 8.9.) and the <hi>proper</hi> type of the <hi>New</hi> Teſtament.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 2.</hi> Of the Goſpels.</head>
                  <p>More ſtrange is the ſilence of our B. Saviour, in the Goſpels.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. When the <hi>Law</hi> was to be written, good God! what care taken? 1. For its <hi>writing.</hi> The principal part of it, written by an <hi>Angel</hi> repreſenting God's perſon, <hi>Exo.</hi> 24.12. The reſidue, by his ſpecial <hi>command,</hi> by <hi>Moſes.</hi> 2. For its <hi>cuſtody.</hi> Layed up in the <hi>Ark</hi> (the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:34171:70"/>
ſacredſt Cabinet the world ever ſaw;) there kept under the wings of the ſame <hi>Cherubins</hi> as kept <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> Deut. 10.5. 3. For the giving <hi>copies</hi> of it, &amp; to <hi>whom,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.28. 4. For the <hi>reading</hi> of it to the people; and at what <hi>times</hi> neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.9. And all theſe thought fit to be recorded, and within the book it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>And yet <hi>that,</hi> was to be the law but of that <hi>one</hi> Nation; to endure but a <hi>short</hi> while; to be but a ſmall <hi>part</hi> of their Scripture; was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>either neceſſary, nor available to <hi>juſtifie</hi> the obſervers (<hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20.) and beſide it, they were to have not onely a conſtant race of <hi>Teachers</hi> divinely authorized, but <hi>Prophets</hi> all along until the Meſsiah's coming (<hi>Mat.</hi> 11.13.)</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Law, was to oblige <hi>every</hi> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to endure to <hi>world's end;</hi> to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, &amp; ſufficient to <hi>juſtification.</hi> And can it then be thought in reaſon, he would go hence, and leave it to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to writing, and that writing to be, after the Apoſtles death, the
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:34171:71"/>
                     <hi>onely</hi> means (as you ſay) of teaching it with authority, and never ſpeak any ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable concerning it?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Nor can his ſilence touching it, be imputed to accident, or incogitancy: for he could wel remember to take care for the <hi>preaching</hi> of it, <hi>who</hi> were to preach it, <hi>to</hi> whom, <hi>what</hi> was to be taught, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And how many, how tempting oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, had he to have mentioned the Scripture (if to be as you ſay) at leaſt, in ſome kinde or other. If not as <hi>the means</hi> of reaching, or <hi>the matter</hi> to be taught, or <hi>the rule</hi> or condition of it; yet as a <hi>part</hi> of the means, matter, or rule, at leaſt, as a <hi>Record,</hi> helpful to the office, namely; when, giving the <hi>Commiſsion,</hi> and <hi>Inſtructions</hi> to his Church, for the teaching of his Goſpel; when naming <hi>the matter</hi> to be taught; and <hi>the means</hi> by which he intended for ever to guide her into all truth. (<hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.16. &amp; 16.13.) when charging all creatures, <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely,</hi> to believe and obey her teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; denouncing hell to them that
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:34171:71"/>
should not, aſſuring heaven to them that thould (<hi>Mat.</hi> 16.16.)</p>
                  <p n="4">4. And how eaſilie, how ſoon, had a <hi>word</hi> been ſpoken of it, in ſome one or other of theſe occaſions: For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to have ſaid [<hi>write</hi> the Goſpel; or, Teach <hi>Scripture;</hi> or, <hi>it</hi> shall guide you into truth; or, he that believes you (or the Church) teaching <hi>out of,</hi> or <hi>according to it, &amp;c.</hi>]</p>
                  <p>Nor can you ſay, he did, or might <hi>mean,</hi> that condition, though he <hi>named</hi> it not. For, beſides that this is proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, that [<hi>adding to, and taking from</hi> Gods word written, which S. <hi>Iohn</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces that heavy curſe to (<hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.18.) by <hi>this,</hi> no greater authoritie is given to <hi>the Church</hi> (that <hi>City,</hi> or <hi>Houſe of God,</hi> of <hi>which ſuch glorious things are ſpoken</hi> in Scripture;) then muſt be given to any Tinker, Woman, Childe, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, nay to the verie Devil himſelf; for we ought to believe him, teaching according to Scripture.</p>
                  <p>And certainlie, any man conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the multiplicitie of Sects in theſe
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:34171:72"/>
parts of Chriſtendom, and all ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves in Scripture, when he (<hi>the author and finisher of our faith,</hi> Heb. 12.2.) never ſo much as mentioned it, in order to <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> or his <hi>Law;</hi> may wel aſcribe it to his ſingular wiſdom, and goodneſs, that he waved all mention of it: for, what would have been, had he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver referrd us to it, in any kinde what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever? Surely, had he ever mentioned it in any of thoſe <hi>kindes</hi> abovenamed; and the New Teſtament, in the <hi>form</hi> wherein it is; and the <hi>people,</hi> judges of the ſenſe of it: he had left his Church, in a more defective, and miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, then ever any Prince, or Law-giver, left Common-wealth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 3.</hi> Of the Acts.</head>
                  <p>No leſſe ſtrange is the ſilence of the <hi>Hiſtorie</hi> of the <hi>Primitive</hi> Church.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It was written purpoſely for a <hi>record</hi> of what the Apoſtles did, in order to the good of religion, moſt <hi>importing</hi> poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to be recorded. Among which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly nothing can import us more then
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:34171:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
what they did, in planting, ſettling, and declaring the <hi>means</hi> for teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, after their deceaſe, throughout all future ages.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Nor could any thing, more, or more early, deſerve and require their induſtry, and ſollicitude, then the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding, and ſettling the means; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering (among other reaſons) their own <hi>mortality.</hi> It cannot be therefore, but if a <hi>VVriting,</hi> or <hi>Book</hi> were to be it; one of their firſt cares and diligences would have been imployed, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing it to be written (the <hi>old</hi> Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture being improper to this purpoſe;) declaring, and recommending it for ſuch, to Paſtors, and people; cauſing copies of it to be tranſcribed, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed over the world; ſecuring ſome original of it, in <hi>Ieruſalem, Antioch, Rome,</hi> or other ſafeſt City; tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it into vulgar Languages, for the uſe of the common people; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering it to Presbyters at their Ordination, as the <hi>Matter,</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi> of their teaching: finally, cauſing
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:34171:73"/>
record to be made of what they did in it, either within the book it ſelf, or in the <hi>history</hi> of their <hi>Acts</hi> (nothing poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to be written of them, being of the thouſand part of that concernment for the knowledge of future ages, as this.)</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If they neglected, or deferred the doing any thing in it, for ſome years at firſt, whiles together in health, at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and the Teachers all of one minde; yet afterward, when they ſaw S. <hi>Iames</hi> beheaded, and S. <hi>Peter</hi> (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a miraculous reſcue) like to have been ſo too (<hi>Acts</hi> 22.1.) when they ſaw Sects ſpringing up apace, ſo as there was need of holding a Council, to decide the controverſie (<hi>Act.</hi> 15.2.) when, <hi>that,</hi> was like to be the laſt time of their ever meeting together in the world; when ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monished by that example, how ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and neceſſary it then was, for them to ſettle and declare <hi>the judge</hi> and <hi>guide of faith</hi> (if to be any other then the <hi>Church:</hi>) how could they delay any longer to do ſomething in it? or if they
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:34171:73"/>
did, the Hiſtorian not thinking it worth the writing.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. He could note the great zeal and pains of <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> in <hi>viſiting</hi> the Churches; <hi>confirming</hi> them; <hi>leaving among them the decrees of the Church to keep; ordaining</hi> Paſtors to feed, and guide them; <hi>inſtructing</hi> thoſe Paſtors, for the diſcharge of their office after their death; <hi>recommending</hi> and <hi>naming</hi> to them the proper and ſufficient means to that end (<hi>Acts</hi> 8.32. &amp; 14.21, 23. &amp; 15.36. &amp; 16.4. &amp; 20, 20, 28.32.) what occaſions were theſe, for him to have ſaid ſomething of what they did in <hi>writing</hi> Scripture, or diſtributing it to the Churches for to keep, or recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending it to the Paſtors for to teach? eſpecially, when they came ſo neer to it, as to recommend them <hi>the word of God's grace?</hi> Acts 20.32.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. And yet afore the finishing of this Hiſtory, there were written (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide S. <hi>Luke's</hi> own) two of the Goſpels (S. <hi>Mathew's</hi> and S. <hi>Mark's</hi>) moſt of S. <hi>Paul's</hi> Epiſtles; and ſome of them
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:34171:74"/>
written in that very <hi>City,</hi> and at that very <hi>time,</hi> when he was with S. <hi>Paul</hi> (Col. 4.14. 2 Tim. 4.11.) and (as is likely) wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this Hiſtory; yet he takes no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice at all of them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 4.</hi> Of the Epiſtles.</head>
                  <p>Moſt ſtrange of all, is the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> own ſilence, in their <hi>Epiſtles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. They were vvritten, ſome to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, ſome to the people, to give them the beſt advices and inſtructions they could, either for them in preſent, or to be left upon record, for all Paſtors, and people in future ages. Among which none could be more important, then to declare and recommend to them, the <hi>Guide</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi> of Religion after their own deceaſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And how frequent, how proper occaſions had they to have named the Scripture for it, if it were to be? Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; when, adviſing the <hi>Paſtors</hi> to teach the Word, naming the matter they were to teach; the rule they vvere to teach by; and coming ſo neer the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, as to cal it <hi>[the word of truth, &amp;c.]</hi>
                     <pb n="145" facs="tcp:34171:74"/>
1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.3. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.15. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when, deſcribing, and enumerating the <hi>qualifications</hi> of the Teachers (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.7.) &amp; what was to be committed to them, in their Ordination, to teach (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2.) when moniſhing the <hi>people</hi> touching falſe Teachers, and giving the marks whereby to know them (<hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.2.6.) when char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them <hi>abſolutely [to obey their Paſtors, follow their faith, receive their teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as God's word, with the meekneſs of new born babes,</hi> Heb. 13.7. Iam. 1.21. 1 Pet. 2.2.) when, naming <hi>the rule of faith</hi> (Rom. 12.6.) <hi>the ground of truth</hi> (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.) the means <hi>left by Christ for the perfecting of the Saints</hi> (Epheſ. 4.11.) finally, when naming the end vvherefore Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture vvas given by God, and to which it is profitable, 2 <hi>Timoth.</hi> 3.16.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And how eaſily, how ſoon, had it been named, in one or other of theſe occaſions? For example; to have ſaid,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:34171:75"/>
to <hi>Timothy,</hi> or <hi>Titus</hi> [Teach <hi>Scripture;</hi> or, <hi>according to it,</hi> &amp;c.] or to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, [Prove all things by <hi>Scripture;</hi> or, Make <hi>it</hi> your rule, or guide; or, Obey your Paſtors, teaching out of, or, according to <hi>it;</hi> or, it was given, or, is profitable that the <hi>Christian man</hi> may be perfect, &amp;c.]</p>
                  <p n="4">4. At leaſt, they might have given the people ſome advice or encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (in plain words) <hi>to read</hi> to ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times; or the Paſtors, ſome charge to read it ſometimes to them.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Nor was it of forgetfulneſs, that they balked the giving theſe inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. For in their Epiſtles to the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors,</hi> they could well remember to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe and encourage them to give dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to the <hi>reading</hi> it: (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.) and in ſome Epiſtles, to ſome Churches, to charge the reading of ſome particular Epiſtles, in ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregations, once (1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.27. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.16.) and S. <hi>Peter</hi> could once take occaſion to ſpeak of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Paul's</hi> Epiſtles, and by that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:34171:75"/>
of Scripture in general; but what he ſaith of it, is ſo far from encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging people to read it (much leſs, to make it their guide or rule) as it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſcare any one (either people, or Divines) from meddling with it, without a good <hi>interpreter.</hi> (2 Pet. 3.16.)</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Some of theſe Epiſtles were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by them, when now <hi>ready to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered</hi> (2 Tim. 4.6. 2 Pet. 1.14.) by S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> when now 100. year old, and all the other Apoſtles dead, and (perhaps) rotten long afore, and he ſaw the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches round about him ſwarming with Sects, and wrote to that end chiefly, to confirm. Catholicks in faith, and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish them againſt Sects, and shew them the beſt means and way to diſcern and avoid them. Nor could he but know in what a ſad condition, the ſacred wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings were like to be left by him. Some, <hi>corrupted</hi> by Hereticks (<hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.18.) ſome, <hi>counterfeit</hi> (2 Theſſ. 2.1.) ſome, <hi>uncertain</hi> (Luk. 1.1.) ſome, <hi>loſt</hi> (vid. infr. c. 5. arg. 9. §. 4.) ſome in one Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:34171:76"/>
ſome in another (perhaps 500. miles aſunder;) not ſo much as a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of their <hi>names,</hi> or <hi>number,</hi> &amp;c. yet he left the world, as the reſt had done afore him, without any leaſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> (or any <hi>part</hi> of it, more then what he wrote him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; or <hi>that,</hi> as to any office of <hi>teaching</hi> Religion.)</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Vrging the ſecond Argument, [<hi>Scripture, not</hi> for the people.]</head>
               <p>MY ſecond reaſon is; becauſe [<hi>it was never ordained, or meant, ſo much as for the peoples</hi> reading <hi>(fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the Church should ſee expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to permit it)</hi> but given into the hand of the Church, for her to teach it to them; and to be an inſtrument helpful to her in her office of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. As is manifeſt. For,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:34171:76"/>1. When God Almighty had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>the ten Commandments</hi> (the firſt piece of Scripture that was written;) though it were the plaineſt, both for ſtile, and matter, and moſt proper and uſeful for the people, and to be the principal part of their Cateciſm; yet he delivered it not to <hi>them,</hi> but to <hi>Moſes,</hi> with theſe words, expreſſely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the whole intent of it as to the people, [<hi>I give thee the Law which I have written, that thou maiſt teach it to them,</hi> Exod. 24.12.]</p>
               <p n="2">2. In like manner, when <hi>Moſes</hi> had written the <hi>Law,</hi> he delivered it not to the <hi>people,</hi> (though the <hi>whole Nation</hi> were then preſent afore him in Aſſembly,) but (<hi>finally,</hi> or <hi>ſupremely</hi>) unto <hi>Ioſuah,</hi> or <hi>Eleazar</hi> (the one, chief Ruler or Paſtor, in <hi>ordinary;</hi> the other, in <hi>extraordinary,</hi>) with theſe words, expreſſely declaring the whole intent of it; as to the <hi>people,</hi> and the <hi>right</hi> they were to have to it. <hi>At the end of every ſeven years, thou shalt</hi> read <hi>this, &amp;c.</hi>] Deut. 31.9.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:34171:77"/>3. This copy, delivered by <hi>Moſes</hi> into the High-Prieſts hand, was there to remain, without any one to have a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of (for ought appears) until there should be a <hi>King</hi> (who was to share the ſupream office with the High-Prieſt) who was not to be in 500. years after; and he was to <hi>write him a copy of it, out of that which was before the Prieſts,</hi> (Deut. 87.19.)</p>
               <p n="4">4. In their cuſtody it remained (2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17.9. <hi>Neh.</hi> 8.1.) without any copy of it, for certain, in all the land of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> after <hi>Ieroboam's</hi> ſchiſm (2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 15.3.) and if not <hi>after,</hi> moſt likely nor <hi>afore;</hi> for we do not finde that he med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled at all with the Bible: and but <hi>one,</hi> in the Church of <hi>Iudah,</hi> until after the <hi>Captivity;</hi> to wit, <hi>that</hi> in the Prieſts cuſtody in the Temple; as should ſeem by the great matter was made of the finding it, when it had been loſt ſome years, and by <hi>Ioſiah's</hi> proceeding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to a <hi>Reformation</hi> by it, which afore it ſeems he could not, for want of it, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.14, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:34171:77"/>The ſame may be ſaid for the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi> For</p>
               <p n="1">1. S. <hi>Iohn's Apocalypſe</hi> (the onely book of it written by <hi>command</hi>) was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely written to the <hi>Angel</hi> (or Paſtor) of the Churches to which it was to be ſent; and to him alone, <hi>immediately,</hi> Apoc. 2.1, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His <hi>Goſpel</hi> was likewiſe without all queſtion delivered by him to ſome <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors,</hi> to be by them taught and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished, as appears by their teſtimony to it, (<hi>Ioh.</hi> 21.24.)</p>
               <p n="3">3. Three of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles for certain were written to <hi>Paſtors</hi> alone, (the firſt and ſecond to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> to <hi>Titus:</hi>) and very probably, a fourth, to <hi>Philemon,</hi> whom he calls his <hi>fellow labourer,</hi> (Phil. 1.)</p>
               <p n="4">4. So were alſo, probably, S. <hi>Lukes Goſpel,</hi> and <hi>Acts: Theophilus</hi> to whom they were dedicated, being by ſome ancient Writers ſaid to have been a <hi>Bishop.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Two other of S. <hi>Paul's</hi> Epiſtles, though dedicated to <hi>Churches,</hi> yet were
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:34171:78"/>
delivered <hi>immediately</hi> into the hand of the <hi>Paſtor,</hi> to be by him <hi>read</hi> to the people; or elſe that charge of <hi>reading</hi> them to them, had been ſuperfluous, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.16. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.27. So, in his hand, they remained alſo after the reading, and at his diſcretion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he would read them the ſecond time; and much more, whether per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any of the people copies of them. And by parity of reaſon, the ſame is to be preſumed of the other Goſpels, and Epiſtles, dedicated to <hi>Churches,</hi> or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out dedication.</p>
               <p>But what need I prove it thus, by inferences, and preſumptions? When the text affirms it expreſſely, that the Scripture was written purpoſely for the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>(immediately.)</hi> for her alone; to be an inſtrument in her hand for teaching the people, and furthering and helpful to her, for the better diſcharge of her of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</p>
               <p n="6">6. So ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi> touching his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to <hi>Timothy [Theſe things write
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:34171:78"/>
I unto thee, that thou maiſt know how thou oughteſt to behave thy ſelf in the Church which is the ground of truth.</hi> 1 Tim. 3.15.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Nay touching the <hi>whole</hi> Scripture, univerſally <hi>[All Scripture is given by God, and is profitable, for doctrine, &amp;c. that the man of God, &amp;c.]</hi> that is, [The whole Scripture, is given by God, unto the Paſtor, and is profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to this end, to furnish him per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, for doctrine, reproof, corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, inſtruction of the people in <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> (as you call it,) and for every other good work, proper or pertaining to his function.] 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16, 17.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Vrging the third Argument. [Scripture not <hi>proper,</hi> &amp;c.]</head>
               <p>MY third Reaſon is; Becauſe [<hi>it is not proper to give the firſt inſtruction</hi> (vvhich is the firſt,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:34171:79"/>
incomparably principal, and moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary act of <hi>Teaching.</hi>) As ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears;</p>
               <p n="1">1. From that of S. <hi>Paul, [How shall</hi> (any one) believe in him of whom they have not heard? or hear, without a <hi>Preacher?</hi> Rom. 10.14.]</p>
               <p n="2">2. From that of S. <hi>Peter, [The un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned wriſt the Scripture to their deſtruction,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.16.] Therefore, to a profitable and ſafe uſe of it, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires and ſuppoſes a reader ſomewhat pre-inſtructed in Religion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. From the <hi>form</hi> of it; becauſe not <hi>Catechiſtical;</hi> but <hi>Hiſtorical,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="4">4. From the <hi>dedication</hi> of all the books in it vvhich have any; vvhich is not to any, but either <hi>Paſtors,</hi> or Catholick <hi>Churches</hi> (the <hi>Romans, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> &amp;c.) or at leaſt, <hi>Catholick perſons, walking in the truth,</hi> (2 Ioh. 4.) &amp; 3.3.</p>
               <p n="5">5. From the <hi>ſtile</hi> of it, <hi>vid. inf. c.</hi> 4. §. 2.</p>
               <p n="6">6. From divers paſſages in it, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:34171:79"/>
ſuppoſing the reader, one need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no <hi>catechiſing</hi> (1 Ioh. 2.20, 27.) In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as they check ſome in the Churches they vvrote to, for <hi>needing</hi> it. (<hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12.) nay, they ſuppoſe him one not needing <hi>neceſſarily</hi> any <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> (Luk. 1.4. Rom. 15.14. 1 Cor. 1.5. Col. 3.16, &amp;c.) And therefore declare, the end of their vvriting (thoſe that declare any) to be, not to teach <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſtical,</hi> or <hi>Fundamental</hi> doctrines, but the higher <hi>perfecting,</hi> myſteries, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1.) to exhort, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monish, ſtir up to remembrance, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage, comfort, eſtablish, rectifie ſome errours, and abuſes crept in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them; to give the Paſtors ſome advices, and ſuch like ends, pertaining to doctrine <hi>Concionatory,</hi> or <hi>perfecting, (Luk.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.31. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.2. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.1, 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.15. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.22. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.1. <hi>Iude</hi> 3. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſequently, it is ſo far from being uſeful, or intended to teach us (<hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinally,</hi> or <hi>Catechiſtically</hi>) the articles
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:34171:80" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of our <hi>Creed,</hi> the form of <hi>Church-Government, VVorship, Sacraments, &amp;c.</hi> as it is but <hi>incidently,</hi> and (as it were) by <hi>accident,</hi> that it mentions any thing of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Vrging the fourth argument.</hi> [Scripture not the <hi>principal.</hi>]</head>
               <p>A Fourth Reaſon is; Becauſe [it <hi>is not the principal, as to the effect of teaching, but onely an inſtrument, in the hand of the Church, and one of her Scholars.</hi> And conſequently <hi>improper,</hi> but as in their hand, to give any <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> yea or <hi>Divine,</hi> ſo much as his <hi>perfecting</hi> inſtruction. And I shall give four proofs for it.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 1.</hi> Scripture for the Church.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The firſt shall be; Becauſe</hi> [the Church was not ordained for it; but it for her, as it's end, to be helpful, and furthering to her, in, and for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:34171:80"/>
diſcharge of her office.] <hi>As is proved</hi> ſupra. cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 2.</hi> Not proper to Catechiſe.</head>
                  <p>The ſecond; becauſe (as appears by the former <hi>Chapter) it is not proper to give the firſt inſtruction.</hi> Conſequently, nor the ſecond, but to him the firſt <hi>right.</hi> For, the <hi>firſt</hi> inſtruction, gives us our firſt, and tranſcendent rule, notion, or inſtrument, by which we meaſure, and judge of all things we read or hear of afterward (generally ſpeaking) in Religion. Conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, one falſe <hi>principled,</hi> is in as bad, (nay, many times worſe) a condition, for underſtanding Scripture, then a novice: as the eye is more deceived uſing a falſe ſpectacle, then none at all; and one that hath a wrong direction given him, is (many times) worſe, for finding the way, then he that hath none at all. Now, for giving men their <hi>firſt</hi> inſtruction right; no means (<hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent</hi> to Scripture) is imaginable, but the <hi>Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="158" facs="tcp:34171:81"/>Or briefer, thus, Becauſe it ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes its reader, a <hi>Catholick.</hi> And therefore cannot be proper for any one's uſe, but a <hi>Catholicks.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 3.</hi> [VVants ſenſe and reaſon.]</head>
                  <p>The third (and vvhich, though, I name it here onely, is of as much, or more, force, in giving the <hi>firſt</hi> inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;) becauſe it vvants <hi>underſtanding,</hi> and <hi>ſenſe;</hi> faculties, abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to diſcharge the office of <hi>teaching.</hi> Becauſe,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Every one is of a ſeveral capacity, rank, or form (as I may call it) in knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; ſo as vvhat is plain to one, is dark to another. And vve are all, by <hi>nature</hi> (1 Cor. 2.11.) <hi>dull of hearing,</hi> in ſpiritual things (<hi>Heb.</hi> 5, 11.) and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry apt to underſtand them in <hi>carnal</hi> ſenſe (as vve ſee in <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> (Ioh. 3.4.) the vvoman of <hi>Samaria</hi> (Ioh. 4.15.) the Capernaltes; (<hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.52.) yea, after vve have been a good vvhile in Chriſt's School, to think vve under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them as vve ought, vvhen (God knovvs) many times very ſorrily and
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:34171:81"/>
erroneouſly (as vve ſee in the Apoſtles themſelves. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.36. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.45. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.6.) And therefore <hi>that</hi> vvhich is to <hi>teach,</hi> muſt be able to conſider the ſcholars need, capacity, and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and accordingly to fit his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to every one ſeverally; to one thus, to another thus; <hi>to babes milk, to men ſtronger meat.</hi> (1 Cor. 3.1. Heb. 5.11.) And to that end, muſt be able to be interrogated by the ſcholar (<hi>Mat.</hi> 13.36. <hi>Lu.</hi> 2.46. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.34.) yea, if need be, again and again, until he underſtand the inſtruction aright and fully as he ought: yea, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogate him too, to ſee if he do.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Again, every one is of a ſeveral calling, quality, humor, ſtate of ſoul, or conſcience, degree in vertue, &amp;c. So, <hi>that,</hi> which is uſeful counſel, or doctrine to one, is impertinent to another; nay, vvhat is one mans meat, is often anothers poyſon. For, many vices, are like vertues, and contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vertues like vices, ſo as it is very apt for men, vvithout good judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:34171:82"/>
and experience in ſuch matters (<hi>Heb.</hi> 5.14.) to miſtake one for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And H. Scripture relates many things done <hi>ill,</hi> by <hi>Saints; well,</hi> by <hi>wicked</hi> men, without giving judgement which was well, which ill done; ſo as it will be very eaſie to erre in making it a rule by it ſelf. Beſides, the <hi>extreams</hi> come very neer another, that which parts them, many times no broader then the edge of a raſor, nay, vertue muſt be many times compos'd of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of each extream duty tempered (<hi>Mat.</hi> 10.16.) Beſides, caſes are alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by <hi>circumſtances;</hi> ſo as what is ſound doctrine in one caſe, may in another, by the alteration of ſome one circumſtance (imperceptible to an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary or unexperienced judgement) be falſe and pernitious. And theſe circumſtances, varying caſes, are of that <hi>infinite</hi> variety, as they are incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible within any written rule, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it should conſiſt of more vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes then the world contain. And therefore that which is to guide or
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:34171:82"/>
direct us in matters of practice or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, muſt be able to conſider, and judge of the <hi>perſon,</hi> and <hi>caſe,</hi> in all its <hi>circumstances,</hi> and apply his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and reſolution to every one ſeveral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (which S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls [<hi>rightly divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the word,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.25.] To <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers</hi> one counſel, to <hi>Merchants</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. (S. <hi>Lu.</hi> 3.10.) To <hi>new veſſels,</hi> one ſort of wine; to <hi>old,</hi> another. (<hi>Mat.</hi> 19.17.) To <hi>tender</hi> ſouls, one ſort of doctrine [<hi>the Lord is ſweet to all</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.9.] to <hi>preſumptuous</hi> ones another [<hi>It is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God.</hi> Heb. 10.31.] In one caſe to ſay <hi>[thou maiſt not bow down, to, or afore any Idol,]</hi> in another, <hi>thou maiſt,</hi> 2 King. 5.18.] In one caſe, to ſay <hi>[thou maist not do any work on the Sabbath,]</hi> in another, [<hi>thou maiſt.</hi> Mat. 12.5.] And to this end, muſt be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be <hi>interrogated</hi> by his conſulter (Mat. 19.3. &amp; 22.17. 1 Cor. 7.1.) yea again and again, if need be (<hi>Mat.</hi> 19.7.) For, many times the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to one queſtion begets more
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:34171:83"/>
and new doubts: yea, and to interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate him too, to ſee if he underſtand the reſolution aright; and to proceed with him till he do. For we are apt, through paſsion, intereſt, ſelf-love, &amp;c. to miſtake, not onely the caſes, but their reſolution too.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Again, every one hath different principles, or notions in his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, whereby he judges of things differently from another, and is apt to interpret the Scripture, or doctrine of the Church; to be for his opinion, or ſenſe; and hence ariſe Sects. When therefore any controverſie is on foot, needing deciſion, the <hi>judge</hi> muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity be able to hear and weigh what is alledged &amp; proved on both ſides, and thereupon to give ſentence in ſuch manner, as the parties litigant, and all other concerned, may, and until they do (without their own pervicacy be in fault) know and underſtand for which ſide it is given, and ſo ceaſe further ſtrife touching it. Nay, many times the very <hi>ſentence</hi> it ſelf, will beget new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:34171:83"/>
touching its ſenſe, requiring another ſentence, and that another, &amp;c. and ſo, the judge muſt be able, (from time to time, as there is occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) to explicate even his own ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</p>
                  <p>Other <hi>teaching</hi> then this, is a meer <hi>Chymaera,</hi> deviſed by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and his inſtruments, to delude ſouls.</p>
                  <p>Now <hi>this</hi> therefore the Scripture is no way proper of, or by it ſelf alone: becauſe it is void of theſe faculties; for it <hi>ſaith</hi> nothing (in <hi>ſpeech properly</hi> ſo called:) and what it <hi>ſaith</hi> (in its <hi>kinde</hi> of ſpeech, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.3.) or <hi>God,</hi> in, or by <hi>it;</hi> is no more then <hi>mute</hi> letter, or word; and ſo, one, and <hi>the ſame,</hi> to <hi>every</hi> reader. And ſo the reader (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome one to interpret that <hi>mute</hi> word) may eaſily think it ſpeaks to <hi>him,</hi> or his caſe, when it is to <hi>another;</hi> or ſaith <hi>ſuch</hi> a thing (in <hi>ſenſe</hi>) when it doth the <hi>contrary.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="164" facs="tcp:34171:84"/>
                  <head>§. 4. <hi>Not</hi> Plain. <hi>Proved firſt, from</hi> 2 Pet. 3.16.</head>
                  <p>The fourth reaſon; becauſe <hi>it is not plain, no not in fundamentals</hi> (as you call them) <hi>without the Church for its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And for this, needs no other proof, but to shew you the <hi>Sects</hi> now afore your eyes in <hi>England,</hi> and betwixt <hi>Divines,</hi> even your <hi>learnedst,</hi> and in points <hi>fundamental</hi> (if any may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſo, but theſe, <hi>that there is a God, a Chriſt, a Scripture.</hi>)</p>
                  <p>But I shall give you three proofs for it, out of Scripture it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>The firſt, shall be that ſpeech of S. <hi>Peter, [The unlearned wreſt Paul's epiſtles, as they do other Scriptures al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, unto their own deſtruction,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.16.]</p>
                  <p>Spoken, no doubt, of <hi>Christians,</hi> and (at leaſt) paſt their <hi>Catechiſme;</hi> nay, (its very probable) of <hi>Divines,</hi> and them alone. My reaſon is, becauſe it is not like, he would have called <hi>them</hi>
                     <pb n="165" facs="tcp:34171:84"/>
whoſe duty, or calling it is not, to be <hi>learned [the unlearned,]</hi> but rather <hi>[the ſimple, or ignorant].</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And it is in charity and reaſon, to be ſuppoſed, they (whoever he ſpake of, if <hi>Chriſtians</hi>) read it with a <hi>love of the truth,</hi> and deſire to finde it there, and of a godly intent to promote themſelves in knowledge, and piety; and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out humble and hearty prayer to God, to give them his H. Spirit to illuminate them to the underſtanding of it. Yet, preſuming to expound it to themſelves (without the means apponted by God for its interpteter,) their prayer, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, was abominable to him, and therefore they left by him to <hi>ſtrong illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Devil,</hi> in miſunderſtanding of it; and that, in points <hi>fundamental;</hi> for in no other, can <hi>damnable</hi> error be committed.</p>
                  <p>Nor will it help to ſay, he ſpeakes not of <hi>all</hi> things in Scripture; but <hi>ſome</hi> onely. For, there being no <hi>Catalogue</hi> given of thoſe <hi>ſome;</hi> nor <hi>rule,</hi> or <hi>mark</hi> for diſcerning them from the other;
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:34171:85"/>
and all people being apt to think thoſe things true, and plain in Scripture, which they have been bred up in the belief of: his ſpeech is in effect, as if he had ſaid <hi>indefinitely, [The things in Scripture are hard to be underſtood, but by the learned.]</hi> As if a Phyſician, should ſay, of a book of pills, <hi>[In this are ſome pills, which the unskilful mistake to the poyſoning themſelves;]</hi> it would be, in effect, as to ſay, <hi>[The pills in it, are dangerous to be uſed, but by the skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.]</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>§. 5. <hi>Cauſes in the</hi> ſtile.</head>
                  <p>The ſecond, shall be a demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the <hi>cauſes</hi> (not <hi>all,</hi> but a few of the <hi>principal,</hi> and moſt <hi>common</hi> and <hi>obvious:</hi>) which are partly, in the <hi>ſtile,</hi> partly in the <hi>form.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thoſe I shall name in the <hi>stile;</hi> are,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the ſenſe of it, is ſometimes <hi>proper,</hi> ſometimes <hi>figurative,</hi> and often (without an interpreter) unevident whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in <hi>fundamental</hi> points (or, <hi>import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſalvation;</hi>) for I shall be careful
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:34171:85"/>
not to inſtance in any other. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; in theſe ſpeeches, <hi>[This is my body.] VVhoſe ſins ye for give.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. It hath oftentimes divers <hi>proper</hi> ſenſes, to wit, <hi>literal,</hi> and <hi>mystical:</hi> and ſometimes unevident whether, <hi>e.g.</hi> in this ſpeech [<hi>Eſau have I hated,</hi> Rom. 9.13.]</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It hath oftentimes divers literal ſenſes; to wit, <hi>prophane</hi> (or <hi>grammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi>) and <hi>Eccleſiaſticial.</hi> And ſometimes unevident whether; <hi>e.g.</hi> in this ſpeech [<hi>Not as Lords over</hi> cleron, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3.] whether <hi>cleron</hi> ſignifie <hi>Clergie,</hi> or <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. It hath oftentimes divers <hi>gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical</hi> ſenſes; and ſometimes unevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent whether be it; <hi>e.g.</hi> in this ſpeech [<hi>Thou art</hi> Petros, Mat. 16.18.] whether <hi>Petros,</hi> ſignifie <hi>Peter,</hi> or a <hi>rock.</hi> And in this <hi>[Eſau have I hated:]</hi> whether <hi>[hated]</hi> mean a <hi>poſitive</hi> averſion, or onely, a <hi>not,</hi> or <hi>leſs</hi> loving (as it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times means (<hi>Deut.</hi> 21.15.)</p>
                  <p n="5">5. It abounds with <hi>phraſes proper to the H. Ghoſt,</hi> and <hi>terms of Art in Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie;</hi>
                     <pb n="168" facs="tcp:34171:86"/>
which therefore without ſome <hi>Maſter in that ſcience</hi> to interpret them to us, are no better then ſo much <hi>Greek,</hi> or <hi>Gibrish:</hi> eſpecially, becauſe the writers, ſuppoſing the reader a <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> (underſtanding the language of the Church, took no care to explicate them, or annex a <hi>Dictonary.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nor can you ſay, their ſenſe may be found out in time, by it alone and an underſtanding reader, by conſidering the occaſion, ſcope, coherence of the place, comparing it with the other, &amp;c. Becauſe,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In ſome there is neither occaſion, ſcope, nor coherence viſible; <hi>e.g.</hi> in theſe [<hi>Shall he finde faith?</hi> Luk. 18.8. <hi>Quench not the Spirit,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.20.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Some, are never uſed but once, <hi>e.g.</hi> theſe [<hi>He shall be in danger of a Councel,</hi> Mat. 5.22. <hi>The ſin againſt the Son of man, and the H. Ghoſt,</hi> Mat. 12.31. <hi>The word was made flesh,</hi> Ioh. 1.14. <hi>Retaining ſins,</hi> Ioh. 20.23. <hi>Saving by fire,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.15.] <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="169" facs="tcp:34171:86"/>3. Some, are alike dark in <hi>all</hi> places; e.g. <hi>Binding, and loſing,</hi> Mat. 16.19. &amp; 18.18. <hi>Delivering to Satan,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.5. 1 Tim. 2.20.]</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Few of them, but in <hi>divers</hi> places, have divers <hi>ſenſes;</hi> and many times un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evident whether or no; and if; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be it: e.g. <hi>Faith,</hi> in theſe, Mat. 17.19. Lu. 18.8. Act. 19.9. Rom. 14.23. 1 Cor. 13.2. <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> Mat. 3.6, 11, Mar. 10.38. Acts 1.5. 1 Cor. 15.29. <hi>Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hands,</hi> Mat. 19.15. Act. 8.17. &amp; 9.17. &amp; 13.3. 1 Tim. 4.14. &amp; 5.22. Heb. 6 1. <hi>Bishop.</hi> Act. 20.28. Phi. 1.1. Tit. 1.7. <hi>Presbyter,</hi> Act. 11.30. &amp; 15.2. &amp; 20.20. 1 Tim. 4.14. &amp; 5.1, 22. 1 Pet. 5.1. <hi>Election</hi> or <hi>elect.</hi> Mat. 20.16. &amp; 24.24. 1 Pet. 1.1. <hi>Sin,</hi> Rom. 5.12. &amp; 7.17. 1 Ioh. 1.8. &amp; 3.8. <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> Rom. 2.13. &amp; 8.33. <hi>VVorks,</hi> Rom. 4.2. Iam. 2.21.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Some of them, ſeem to ſome Divines to have divers ſenſes in divers places; to others, but one in all: <hi>e.g.</hi> this name <hi>[the Church:]</hi> upon the true ſenſe whereof, depends (in fine) all faith &amp; religion, &amp; conſequently the ſalvation of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde;
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:34171:87"/>
and yet there among your learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edſt Teachers, as many differing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitions of it almoſt as there are Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; to ſpeak ſadly, as many as are <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeable by the wit of man;</hi> and all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to Scripture.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Finally (and which is of greateſt difficulty, to the Interpreter, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the <hi>(not Catholick)</hi> reader;) the <hi>words</hi> of it, in their <hi>proper,</hi> and <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical</hi> ſenſe, are often times <hi>repugnant</hi> to themſelves: ſo as it is neceſſary, in the one place, to forſake it for another <hi>improper,</hi> to the end to reconcile it with other; and many times unevident; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them is to give the law of ſenſe to the other; and what that ſenſe is which is to reconcile them. Inſtances hereof you will ſee divers anon: mean time theſe may ſerve [<hi>God hardned Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh's heart,</hi> Gen. 7.3. <hi>God tempts no man,</hi> Iam. 1.13. Again, <hi>The ſin againſt the H. Ghoſt shall never be forgiven,</hi> Mat. 12.31. <hi>Come unto me all that are heavy laden, and I will refresh you,</hi> Mat. 11.28.]</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <pb n="171" facs="tcp:34171:87"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 6.</hi> The first cauſe in the form's <hi>[Stragling.]</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Thoſe I shall name in the <hi>form,</hi> shall be but two.</p>
                  <p>The one; that often times it delivers the rule, <hi>incompleatly,</hi> and <hi>ſtraglingly:</hi> part in one place, part in another; and ſo, one muſt be made up, by, or with the other. And ſometimes unevident, even to the learnedſt Divines (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Churche's shewing,) which, and how many texts, appertain to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating of it. For inſtance.</p>
                  <p>One place relates how <hi>Abraham was juſtified by faith,</hi> (Gen. 15.6.) another, how <hi>by offering his ſon,</hi> (Gen. 22.16.) now <hi>ſupply</hi> (as S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith; you, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, <hi>fulfil</hi>) the one Scripture with the other, as he there shews you the art of it, <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.23.) and they give you the true doctrine of <hi>juſtification;</hi> otherwiſe, taken apart, but a part of it.</p>
                  <p>Again; in one place, our ſweet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour promiſes, he <hi>will refresh all peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinners that come to him,</hi> Mat. 11.28. In another, he inſtitutes and declares
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:34171:88"/>
the <hi>means,</hi> by which he vvill refresh them: to vvit, <hi>the word of Priestly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution,</hi> Ioh. 20.21. Now ſupply the former place vvith the latter, and they will give you the true ground of hope of remiſsion of ſins upon your going to Chriſt, vvith ſorrovv and confeſsion of them: othervviſe, in ſtead of hope, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude you into damnable preſumption.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>§. <hi>7.</hi> The ſcond cauſe <hi>[repugnancy.]</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The other (and maineſt of all;) is, that ordinarily, vvhat it ſaith in one place, it gain-ſaith in another, in</hi> words, <hi>taken in their</hi> proper Grammar <hi>ſenſe, and in all ſenſe imaginable, ſo</hi> ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>as the beſt Divines have many times their hands full to reconcile them; and the comparing places, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the ſcope, coherence, &amp;c. is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times ſo unſerviceable to that end, as it rather inflames the difficulty. Nay, it creates works enough ſometimes for the Church her ſelf to do it; and in one age she gets one ſtep tovvard it, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps three or four ages more, ere she get another; ſo as she hath not yet done
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:34171:88"/>
it in all, in that</hi> perfect <hi>manner, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps she may hereafter, vvhen God shall give her more light. And in thoſe she hath reconciled; the certainty (as to</hi> us) <hi>of the truth of the reconcilement, comes not from any evidence of the</hi> thing, <hi>but onely from the</hi> authority <hi>of the</hi> Interpreter. <hi>Nor is it always poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be done, no not by</hi> her, <hi>by</hi> any means, rule, or help of interpretation, <hi>to be found in Scripture; but she muſt</hi> pray in aid <hi>from her own</hi> ſenſe, <hi>or</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. <hi>To name a few inſtance among many.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1. In one place,</hi> [The Lord he is God; one Lord; no Lord beſide him, <hi>Deut. 4.45. &amp; 6.4.] In other</hi> [The Gods <hi>(Elohim) ſaid,</hi> Let us make man, <hi>Gen. 1.27.</hi> The Lord rained from the Lord, <hi>&amp;c. Gen. 19.24.</hi> Thee the onely God, and whom thou haſt ſent, Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>Ioh. 17.3.</hi> But one God, the Father, and one Lord Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>1 Cor. 8.6.</hi> In the name of the Father, the Son, and the H. Ghoſt. <hi>Mat. 28.19.</hi>]</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2. In one place</hi> [My Father, and I
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:34171:89"/>
are one, <hi>Ioh. 10.30.] In another,</hi> [My Father is greater then I, <hi>Ioh. 14.28. you will ſay, that was meant, in reſpect of his</hi> divers natures. <hi>True: but where's</hi> that, <hi>ſaid in Scripture?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3. In one,</hi> [If we ſay, we have no ſin, we lye, <hi>1 Ioh. 1.8.] In other,</hi> [They were both righteous before God, walking in all the commandments of the Lord, blameleſs, <hi>Luk. 1.6.</hi> I know nothing by my ſelf, <hi>1 Cor. 4.4.</hi> The childe of God ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not, <hi>1 Ioh. 3.9.</hi>]</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4. In one,</hi> [He that is not with me, is againſt me, <hi>Mat. 12.30.] In another,</hi> [He that is not againſt us, is for us, <hi>Luk. 9.50.</hi>]</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5. In one,</hi> [If I bear record of my ſelf, my record is not true, <hi>Ioh. 5.31.] In another,</hi> [It is, <hi>Ioh. 8.14.</hi>]</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6, In one,</hi> [Paul took Timothy, and circumciſed him, <hi>Acts 16.3.</hi>] In ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, [He that is circumciſed, Chriſt shall profit him nothing, <hi>Gal. 5.2.</hi>]</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7. In one,</hi> [If Abraham was juſtified by works, &amp;c. <hi>Rom. 4.2.] In another,</hi> [VVas not Abraham juſtified by works? <hi>Iam. 2.21.</hi>]</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <pb n="175" facs="tcp:34171:89"/>
                     <hi>8. In one,</hi> [My loving kindeneſs will I not utterly take from him, my covenant will I not break for any wickedneſs of his children, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal. 89.33.] In the very next verſe,</hi> [Thou haſt caſt off, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred thine Anointed, thou haſt made void thy covenant with him, thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned his crown. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9. In one,</hi> [There was given him a kingdom, that all nations should ſerve him, his dominion is an everlasting domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, &amp;c. <hi>Dan. 2.44. &amp; 7.14.] In another.</hi> [VVhen the Son of man comes, shall he finde faith on the earth? <hi>Lu. 18.8.</hi> All the world worshipped the Dragon, &amp;c. <hi>Apoc. 13.4, 8.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10. In ſome</hi> [Call upon me, in the day of trouble, and I will deliver thee, <hi>Pſal. 50.15.</hi> Every one that askes receives; knock, and it shall be opened unto you, <hi>Mat. 7.7, 8.</hi> Come unto me all, &amp;c. and I will refresh you, <hi>Mat. 11.28.</hi>] VVhoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever calls upon the name of the Lord, shall be ſaved, <hi>Rom. 10.13.] In other,</hi> [In the day of trouble they shall call upon me, and I will laugh at them, <hi>Pro. 1.28.</hi> They
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:34171:90"/>
came knocking, ſaying, Lord, <hi>open unto us. But he ſaid,</hi> Away from me, I know you not, <hi>Mat. 25.11.</hi> Ye know how that afterward when Eſau would have inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the bleſsing, he was rejected, finding no place of repentance <hi>(in his father)</hi> though he ſought it carefully with tears, <hi>Heb. 12.17.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12. In ſome,</hi> [Come unto me, <hi>all, &amp;c. Mat. 11.28.</hi> The blood of Ieſus Chriſt cleanſes us from <hi>all</hi> ſin, <hi>1 Ioh. 7.9.] In other,</hi> [All manner of ſin shall be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given unto men, <hi>(upon their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;)</hi> but the blaſphemy againſt the H. Ghost, never, <hi>Mat. 12.31.</hi> It is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsible for thoſe who were enlightned, &amp;c. if they shall full away, to renew them again unto repentance, <hi>Heb. 6.4.</hi> To them that ſin wilfully after know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth, there remains no more ſacrifice for ſin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Heb. <hi>10.26.</hi>]</p>
                  <p n="13">
                     <hi>13. In ſome</hi> [To you, it is given to know the myſteries of the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but to them it is not given, <hi>Mat. 13.11.</hi> Many are called, but few choſen, <hi>Mat. 20.16.</hi> The Lord added daily to
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:34171:90"/>
the Church, ſuch as should be ſaved, <hi>Act. 2.47.</hi> As many as were ordained to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, believed, <hi>Act. 13.48.</hi> VVhom he did predeſtinate, them he called, <hi>&amp;c. Rom. 8.30.</hi> Before the children had done, either good or evil, <hi>&amp;c. Rom. 9.11.] In other,</hi> Preach the Goſpel to every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he that believes, and is baptized, shall be ſaved, <hi>Mar. 16.15.</hi> God will have all men to be ſaved, and come to the knowledge of the truth, <hi>1 Tim. 2.4.</hi> Give diligence to make your calling, and electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſure: for if, &amp;c. <hi>2 Pet. 1.8.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 8.</hi> Third proof, from <hi>inſtances.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The third, and laſt proof, shall be from <hi>instances.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. The old Teſtament was not ſo plain, for that which we (by reaſon we were taught it in our childehood) think it to be moſt plain for; <hi>that there are An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Spirits, and a Reſurrection to be:</hi>] but that the Sadduces (great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines then) denied them all [<hi>Acts</hi> 23.8.) and had objections out of Scripture againſt them, [<hi>Maſter, Moſes ſaid,</hi> &amp;c.] Mat. 22.24.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="178" facs="tcp:34171:91"/>2. It was not ſo plain (with S. <hi>Mathews</hi> Goſpel, added to it,) for a reſurrection to be, at the end of the world; but that ſome, (and no doubt, <hi>Divines;</hi> for at that time, few others were broachers of hereſies, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.24. &amp; 20.32. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2, 2, 6.) ſaid; <hi>it was past already,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.18. An opinion ſo monſtrouſly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, as were it not in Scripture affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, one would think it incredible any should be ſo ſtupid. And we may be ſure they fetched their proofs for it, out of Scripture. For elſe, neither could they have had any colour for ſuch a wilde opinion, nor the impudence to broach it among Chriſtians, much leſs the ſucceſs, <hi>to overthrow the faith of any,</hi> as they did of <hi>ſome.</hi> Which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, no doubt God Almighty put there on purpoſe to shew unto us, how that there is no conceit poſsible to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into mans brain ſo abſurd, or non-ſenſical, but Sectaries will be able to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Scripture for it; yea, and with ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs too. Whereof we have an inſtance at preſent in another almoſt as non-ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:34171:91"/>
a fancy as that was; <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Anti-Chriſt is come already, and is a Chriſtian, nay, ſits in S.</hi> Peter's <hi>Chair.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The 53. Chapter of <hi>Eſay</hi> was not ſo plain that <hi>Chriſt ought to ſuffer for our ſins;</hi> but that the <hi>Eunuch</hi> reading it, and no doubt with a very humble and pious heart lifted up to God to enlighten him, was glad to ask one who ſeemed to him an authorized interpreter of Scripture, <hi>[I pray thee of whom ſpeaks the Prophet this, &amp;c.]</hi> And being before asked by him, in the general, if he underſtood what he read; readily anſwered, <hi>[How can I, except ſome man should guide me?]</hi> Act. 8.31, 34. wherein the H. Ghoſt would, in that <hi>first,</hi> and <hi>onely</hi> (expreſs) example of a lay-man reading the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, inſumate unto all <hi>lay</hi>-readers of it; with what diſpoſition of ſoul they ought to read it, to attain the true ſenſe of it.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It was not ſo plain (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all S. <hi>Paul</hi> could urge out of it) for the abolitition of the Moſaical Law; but that divers of the <hi>primitive</hi> Divines;
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:34171:92"/>
yea (as is probable) of them upon whom the H. Ghoſt came down at Penticoſt) found it, as ſeemed to them, plain to the contrary, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.1. And for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, ſo it was in expreſs <hi>words</hi> (vid. inf. ſome of the texts named in §. 9. <hi>n.</hi> 2.) nor were the Chriſtians of <hi>Antioch,</hi> after they had heard all that could be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged from S. <hi>Paul</hi> for it, out of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, able to know what to believe in it, without ſending to the <hi>ſupreme In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter,</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> Act. 15.2.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>§. <hi>9.</hi> Inſtance, in the queſtion touching Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>I shall conclude with one notable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which I shall ſet forth a little more particularly and at large, becauſe it shews moſt lively, not onely how <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper</hi> H. Scripture is, to determine any, the moſt fundamental, points of faith, in the hand of any but a <hi>Catholick</hi> Teacher: but how <hi>pernicious</hi> an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it is in the hand of others (too much addicted to it, with neglect of the Church) to lead them into, and confirm them in moſt damnable errors.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="181" facs="tcp:34171:92"/>The grand Controverſie of faith, at the time of our Saviours being upon earth, was, <hi>VVhether he were the Chriſt?</hi> He ſent them who doubted of it, and were obſtinate againſt all other teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, to <hi>ſearch the Scriptures</hi> (which they believed) as <hi>teſtifying of him</hi> (Ioh. 5.39.) His adverſaries, <hi>the Rulers,</hi> in like maner, ſent people to them, as <hi>testifying</hi> againſt him [<hi>They ſaid to him (Nicodemus,</hi> when they perceived him hang that way;) <hi>Art thou alſo of Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilee? Search</hi> (the Scripture) &amp;c. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7.52.] Nay, they were not able to bring any other arguments againſt him, but what they brought out of <hi>Scripture.</hi> Inſomuch as it is certain, there was no one thing, whereby they more ſteeled their own and the peoples hearts againſt believing in him, then <hi>Scripture</hi> (as they underſtood it.) For inſtance;</p>
                  <p>[<hi>Some ſaid; This is the Christ. Others ſaid; Hath not the Scripture ſaid,</hi> &amp;c. Ioh. 7.41.]</p>
                  <p>Again, ſaid they to the Officers when
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:34171:93"/>
they ſaw them ſtaggered with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineneſs of his doctrine, <hi>[Have any of the Rulers, or Phariſees believed on him?]</hi> Why, not they? O forſooth, becauſe they <hi>knew the Law (the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.) [But this people that know not the Law, are accurſed;</hi> that is, miſerably deceived by believing in him to their eternal perdition, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7.49.] Juſt the ſame as you ſay now of our people, for their ignorance in Scripture.</p>
                  <p>Again, the man that was cured of his blindneſs, by Ieſus, ſaid to them, [<hi>VVil ye alſo be his diſciples? they reviled him, and ſaid, Thou art,</hi> (or be thou) <hi>his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple.</hi>] Why, not they? O forſooth [<hi>we are Moſes diſciples, we know</hi> (by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture) <hi>that God ſpake unto Moſes, &amp;c.</hi>] Ioh. 9.27. See <hi>the veil</hi> (of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law) that <hi>lay upon,</hi> and blinded their <hi>hearts,</hi> againſt believing in him (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.15.) and ſo does, to, and at, this day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVill you ſee the cauſes of it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>One was, becauſe they ſaw him teach, command, and practice, ſome things evidently repugnant to the expreſſe
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:34171:93"/>
                     <hi>words</hi> of Scripture. For inſtance:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>It</hi> ſaid [<hi>Thou shalt do no manner of work upon the Sabboth.</hi> Particularly, <hi>Thou shalt not bear any burthen thorow the city,</hi> Ier. 17.21.] <hi>He,</hi> commanded one whom he cured, to carry no leſs a burthen then the bed he lay upon, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the City, on that day, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.9. When therefore they ſaw him afterward work a manifeſt miracle in proof that he was the Chriſt: what had they to choak the mouth of that evidence with, but this [<hi>This man is not of God</hi> (for all his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles,) <hi>becauſe he keeps not the Sabboth day.</hi>] Iuſt the ſame as your men ſay ſometimes of our Church; <hi>She cannot be of God, notwithstanding all her mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, becauſe the worships images, prays to Saints, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Again; <hi>it</hi> ſaid, <hi>Thou shalt keep theſe ordinances, as everlaſting ſtatutes, through all generations for ever,</hi> Gen. 17.7. Exo. 17.10. &amp; 31.17. Deut. 12.5, &amp;c.] <hi>He</hi> ſaid, <hi>He was Lord of the Sabboth,</hi> Mat. 12.8. &amp; diſcovered an intent to change it, and all the ordinances of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                     <pb n="184" facs="tcp:34171:94"/>
and introduce others in their place; <hi>viz.</hi> in ſtead of worshipping God, by a <hi>carnal</hi> and <hi>figurative</hi> ſacrifice, in the Temple of <hi>Ieruſalem onely;</hi> the <hi>ſpiritual, true, pure, worship, that God longed for,</hi> to be celebrated <hi>all the world over</hi> (Ioh. 4.2. Mal. 1.11.) in ſtead of <hi>the Paſsover,</hi> the Sacrament of his <hi>Body and Blood,</hi> Ioh. 6.32, 53. inſtead of <hi>Circumciſion, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</hi> Ioh. 3.3. Now how abominable a deſign they apprehended this in him, may be gueſſed at from their charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one of his diſciples, [<hi>This man ceaſes not, to ſpeak blaſphemous words, againſt this holy place, and the Law. For we have heard him ſay, that this Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus of Nazareth shall destroy this place, and change the cuſtomes which Moſes delivered us,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Acts</hi> 6.13.]</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Again; <hi>it</hi> ſaid, [<hi>There is but one God, and he a pure ſimple Being, Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, Infinite, Omnipotent,</hi> &amp;c:] and appointed, that if any one, yea though a <hi>Prophet giving a ſign of his</hi> Miſsion or Doctrine, should entice them to
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:34171:94"/>
the worship of any thing viſible, or created; they should <hi>ſtone him to death,</hi> as a <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> and <hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> Deut. 13.1. <hi>He,</hi> a viſible man, cloathed with flesh and blood, and all infirmities of humane nature, born but the other day, of a Carpenter, &amp;c. ſaid, he was <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>his Son e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to him;</hi> and required to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped <hi>as ſuch.</hi> And this they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be evident <hi>blaſphemy</hi> [Ioh. 10.33.] and that, according to the expreſs words of Scripture, he ought, as <hi>ſuch,</hi> to be put to death, [<hi>VVe have a Law, and by our Law he ought to dye, becauſe he made himſelf the Son of God,</hi> Ioh. 19.7.] And this ſeemed ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident to them in Scripture: (as no doubt, for that cauſe principally (if not onely) they vvould rather attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute his miracles (as you do ours) unto the <hi>Devil;</hi> then entertain a doubt of his being the Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.24.</p>
                  <p>Another cauſe was; becauſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies touching the properties &amp; ſigns
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:34171:95"/>
of the Meſsiah, were not onely <hi>dark,</hi> (and in that reſpect, needing an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter to <hi>expound</hi> them (<hi>Acts</hi> 8.34. &amp; 17.3.) yea even to <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> Lu. 24.27, 45. 2 Pet. 1.9.) but <hi>repugnant,</hi> in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs <hi>words;</hi> and therefore needing an Interpreter to <hi>reconcile</hi> them. And thence it was, that they were able to urge it, as plainly, and aboundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (yea perhaps I should ſay true, if I ſaid <hi>more] againſt</hi> his being the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiahs as he, <hi>for</hi> it. For inſtance:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In ſome; he was to be [<hi>Davids Lord,</hi> Pſal. 110.1.] yea [<hi>God's Son,</hi> Pſal. 2.6.] yea [<hi>the everlaſting God, &amp;c.</hi> Eſa. 9.6.] In other, [<hi>a</hi> viſible, mortal <hi>man, like unto Moſes,</hi> Deut, 18.15. God's <hi>ſervant,</hi> Pſal. 78.70. <hi>Davids ſon,</hi> Pſal. 132.11.] now that one and the ſame perſon, should be all theſe, though it be eaſie now to us that are taught it by the Church in our childehood, was ſuch a riddle then, to them, (<hi>Mat.</hi> 22.46.) and ſtill is to any creature, in ſtate of <hi>nature</hi> (Mat. 16.17. 1 Cor. 2.8, 14.) as is incomprehenſible by any humane
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:34171:95"/>
brain, without ſpecial light, and by any light in Scripture's ſelf, without an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter,</hi> or any interpreter, of leſs <hi>authority</hi> then <hi>Divine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. In ſome; <hi>He was not to bruiſe a broken reed, &amp;c.</hi> Eſa. 42.3. In other; <hi>to break in pieces the Potentates of the earth like a potsheard, and rule them with a rod of iron,</hi> Pſal. 2.9.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In ſome; he was <hi>to be the contempt of the common ſort,</hi> Pſal. 22.6. In other, <hi>all Kings of the earth, to lick the duſt of his feet,</hi> Pſal. 72.11.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. In ſome; <hi>to have no form, nor come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe in him,</hi> Eſa. 53.3. In other, <hi>to be the faireſt among the children of men,</hi> Pſal. 45.2.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. In ſome, <hi>to be ſlain for us,</hi> Dan. 9.27. In other, to <hi>live,</hi> and <hi>reign a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous King for ever,</hi> Pſal. 72.15. Dan. 7.14. And therefore when the people heard him talk of <hi>his being lift up</hi> (meaning, upon a croſs, or gibbet) they were not able to reconcile that, with his being the <hi>Meſsiah;</hi> ſeeing they <hi>had been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes taught out of Scripture, that
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:34171:96"/>
Chriſt abides for ever,</hi> Ioh. 12.34.</p>
                  <p>No doubt, but he anſwered <hi>their</hi> texts, and explicated his <hi>own</hi> ſo as to reconcile them one with the other. But no doubt alſo they did the ſame with <hi>his,</hi> and their <hi>own</hi> (as they verily thought.)</p>
                  <p>Nor can you ſay of <hi>all,</hi> that it was only pride, vain-glory, malice, or obſtinacy of will, that hindred them from ſeeing the truth of his ſenſe. For, no queſtion, but multitudes of them <hi>Act.</hi> 13.27. compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.8. namely, S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Act. 26.9.) were <hi>purely ignorant,</hi> and ſought the truth in Scripture (according as it was <hi>alledged,</hi> and <hi>opened,</hi> on both ſides) with <hi>a love of the truth,</hi> and a deſire to finde it, and with many a prayer, and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tear to God Almighty for light to ſee it. And yet were <hi>confirmed,</hi> and by Scripture principally (<hi>which they had known from children,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.15.) that <hi>they ought to do things contrary to the name of Ieſus;</hi> till God Almighty by ſome other means then <hi>it,</hi> shew'd them the truth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="189" facs="tcp:34171:96"/>If you ſay; Wherefore did he then ſend them to Scripture for it? the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer hath been given already; that it was not as to a <hi>Teacher</hi> of that point, but a <hi>VVitneſs</hi> onely; nor a witneſs of his <hi>choice,</hi> but which they compelled him to, by their obſtinacy to the other; nor as a witneſſe, proper or ſufficient by <hi>it ſelf alone,</hi> but in company with the other, for <hi>corroboration,</hi> and as <hi>by him</hi> alledged, and expounded; and his Expoſition <hi>warranted</hi> evidently to ſenſe and reaſon, from God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by the <hi>token</hi> of <hi>miracles, beyond all that appeared then, in the Synagogue,</hi> Acts 2.22. &amp; 10.38.) And without that <hi>ſigne,</hi> he <hi>deſired</hi> not any one, (much leſs vvould he <hi>oblige</hi> him) to believe him, or his Interpretation of Scripture, (<hi>Iohn</hi> 5.31. &amp; 15.24.)</p>
                  <p>Conſequently, for all the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; it is as <hi>improper</hi> at this day to decide any controverſie, or reſolve any caſe of conſcience, &amp;c. but in the hand of one <hi>credited</hi> for an <hi>Interpreter</hi> of it,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:34171:97"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="189" facs="tcp:34171:97"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="190" facs="tcp:34171:98"/>
by the ſame <hi>token</hi> from God Almighty, either in his <hi>perſon</hi> (as <hi>he</hi> was,) if he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to miſsion <hi>extraordinary</hi> (or <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical;</hi>) or in <hi>the Church</hi> that ſends him; if he pretend to <hi>ordinary</hi> miſsion. And I pray mark this well.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Vrging the fift Argument,</hi> [Scripture not ſimply neceſſary.]</head>
               <p>MY fift Reaſon is, Becauſe <hi>[neither was it written of any neceſſity; nor, ſince its writing, is it neceſſary to the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of faith.]</hi> (where, by <hi>[not written of any neceſſity.]</hi> I mean not to exclude the neceſsity of <hi>command,</hi> for the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſome <hi>few pieces</hi> in the Old and the <hi>Apocalypſe</hi> in the New Teſtament.) For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. There were as great believers, and holy Saints, afore Scripture was (<hi>Heb.</hi> 11, 4, &amp;c.) as any were after.</p>
               <p n="2">2. After <hi>Moſes</hi> Law was written, we finde not, it was read, either by, or ſo much as <hi>to</hi> the people, in 700. years
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:34171:98"/>
together. Nor was there, for the firſt 1000. years, any more then one copy of it: and <hi>that</hi> too, once <hi>loſt</hi> (and God knows, for how many years together) 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.14. and yet the people were <hi>taught the good knowledge of the Lord</hi> (2 Chro. 30.22.)</p>
               <p n="3">3. In the <hi>Church;</hi> there were as great believers, and holy Saints, afore any <hi>new</hi> Scripture was (<hi>Acts</hi> 2.46. &amp; 4.32. &amp; 9.36, &amp;c.) as any ſince.</p>
               <p n="4">4. After its writing, you cannot finde it was ever read <hi>by,</hi> or ſo much as <hi>to</hi> the people; or intended it should be (more then ſome epiſtles, once, to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church they were written to, and one <hi>neighbour</hi>-Church.) 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.27. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.16.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Church was compleatly ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled in all her <hi>form</hi> (eſſential) of <hi>doctrine, worship, diſcipline, &amp;c.</hi> and in <hi>the means</hi> for <hi>preſerving</hi> that form, uncorrupt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to world's end, divers years afore any <hi>tittle</hi> of the New Teſtament was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; and neer 70. afore it was <hi>all</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten (<hi>vid. ſup. par.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4, 5.)</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="192" facs="tcp:34171:99"/>6. The writers of it expreſſely ſay, they wrote what they did (not of any <hi>command,</hi> but) of their own charity, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, or diſcretion [<hi>becauſe it ſeemed good,</hi> or <hi>meet</hi> to them, <hi>Lu.</hi> 1.3. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13.] upon particular occaſions, reaſons, or motives, hapning as it were by <hi>acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi> (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Iud.</hi> 3.) Nay S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith plainly, [<hi>He had many things to write, which he would not,</hi> 2 Ioh. 12. &amp; 3. Ioh. 13.] Sure then, both he wrote, at his own <hi>diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> and what he wrote, was not <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> to be written.</p>
               <p n="7">7. When S. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> there were two Goſpels (of S. <hi>Mathew</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi>) extant, and had been, twelve or thirteen years a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: yet he being to urge to them the words uſed by our Saviour in the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the <hi>B. Euchariſt;</hi> would not urge them out of either of thoſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpels, but onely from <hi>tradition,</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23.) By that example, giving all Chriſtians for ever to underſtand, how it ſuffices to their faith, and practice,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:34171:99"/>
in the higheſt myſteries of Religion, if they hear from their Paſtor, <hi>[I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the Lord, what I deliver, or have delivered unto you.]</hi> Nor is the caſe different (as to <hi>ſubſtance</hi>) becauſe they cannot mean, receiving it from Chriſt <hi>immediately.</hi> For 1. Perhaps, neither did he. For though he received <hi>ſome doctrines</hi> by <hi>inſpiration</hi> (Gal. 11.2.) yet not <hi>all</hi> perhaps; and namely, not thoſe of the <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> as this was; he being taught them by the ordinary means (and as is like, by <hi>Ananias,</hi> afore he was baptized <hi>Act.</hi> 9.6.) at leaſt, afore he had any <hi>viſion</hi> or <hi>revelation</hi> (2 Cor. 12.1.) 2. Grant he meant it, as received <hi>immediately:</hi> as <hi>Paſtors</hi> ſucceed to him, in the office of teaching with divine au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; ſo, their receiving their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine from Chriſt, by the <hi>mouth</hi> of his <hi>Church</hi> (which H. Scripture ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times calls <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.13. &amp; 12.12.) ſucceeds to his receiving it by <hi>inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. For ought appears; 1. Seven of the Apoſtles were not able <hi>to write.</hi>
                  <pb n="194" facs="tcp:34171:100"/>
2. If they were; left nothing in <hi>wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> with the Churches of their plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (which was a very conſiderable part of Chriſtendom.) 3. Nor did any of thoſe that wrote, dedicate their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings unto the <hi>whole</hi> Church, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>particular</hi> perſons, or Churches on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or at moſt, the faithful <hi>indefinitely;</hi> and without any intimation of intent, or deſire, to thoſe they wrote to, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſe, or impart them to other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. So as at the Apoſtles death, the New Teſtament was not extant, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps heard of, but in a ſmall part of Chriſtendome (in which the two chief Apoſtles laboured;) <hi>viz.</hi> in the <hi>leſſer Aſia,</hi> from <hi>Ieruſalem westward;</hi> and in the South of <hi>Europe,</hi> from <hi>Rome eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> (Rom. 15.19. 1 Pet. 1.1.)</p>
               <p n="9">9. It hath ever been, and now is, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to all ſorts of caſualties as all other books are (I mean, not the <hi>parts</hi> onely, but the <hi>whole:</hi>) which could not be, if it ſimply neceſſary, For, 1. The Book of the Law (and it's probable, <hi>all</hi> the copy then was of it) was <hi>loſt</hi> for divers
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:34171:100"/>
years, (2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.14.) 2. All the copy that was, of a conſiderable part of <hi>Ieremie's</hi> Prophecy, was burnt by <hi>Iehoiakim</hi> (Ier. 36.23.) 3. So were all the copies of the Old Teſtament, that could be found by, <hi>Antiochus</hi> (1 Mac. 1.50.) 4. Divers pieces of the <hi>Old</hi> Canon are utterly <hi>loſt,</hi> that we know of, (1 Sam. 10.25. 2 Chron. 9.29. &amp; 26.22, &amp;c. and perhaps that <hi>Prophet</hi> quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by S. <hi>Mathew,</hi> Mat. 2.23.) 5. So are divers of the <hi>New;</hi> namely, a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Epiſtle of S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> (1 Cor. 5.9.) <hi>Epheſians,</hi> (Epheſ. 3.3.) <hi>Philippians,</hi> (Phil. 3.1.) that from <hi>Laodicea,</hi> (Col. 4.16.) and of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> to ſome Church in <hi>Aſia,</hi> (3 Ioh. 9.) 6. There is not (for ought I can hear) at this preſent, in the world, any <hi>origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> (yea or perhaps <hi>perfectly authenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi>) copy of any one ſacred Book.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Finally, it ſelf aſſures us, that <hi>the new Ieruſalem shall have no need of Sun, or Moon,</hi> (any <hi>created</hi> means of light, though naturally incorruptible) becauſe the <hi>Lamb</hi> is to be her light, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:34171:101"/>
to his promiſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. Apoc. 21.23. And that, to believe, and follow what is taught us by our Paſtors, is <hi>ſufficient to any ones ſalvation,</hi> (Lu. 11.28. Act. 11.14. Rom. 1.16. 1 Tim. 4.20. Iam. 1.21.)</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Vrging the last Argument,</hi> [Scripture <hi>not</hi> ſufficient, &amp;c.]</head>
               <p>MY ſixth and laſt Reaſon is, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>[it contains not expreſſely every particular of the Goſpel.]</hi> For</p>
               <p n="1">1. It contains not every particular, 1. Of the things <hi>commanded</hi> by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to his Apoſtles, to be taught all creatures, as his <hi>Goſpel</hi> (Mat. 28.20. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.15.) 2. Much leſs, of thoſe he <hi>reſerved</hi> the teaching of, unto the <hi>H. Ghoſt,</hi> after his <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> (Ioh. 16.12.)</p>
               <p n="2">2. It contains not every particular, of <hi>the form of Doctrine, VVorship, &amp;c.</hi> taught and ſettled in the Primitive
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:34171:101"/>
Church, by the Apoſtles, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.42.) and <hi>committed</hi> by them <hi>viva voce</hi> to the Paſtors to teach, and obſerve, and <hi>commit</hi> in like manner, <hi>viva voce,</hi> to others (Acts 20.20, 27. 2 Tim. 1.13. &amp; 2.2, &amp;c.)</p>
               <p>If you ſay, it does; <hi>it will lye upon you</hi> to shew where; 1. By making a <hi>Catalogue</hi> of all the particulars. 2. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it to be a <hi>perfect</hi> one. 3. Naming, <hi>where</hi> every of them is contain'd.</p>
               <p>I ſay, <hi>it will lie upon you;</hi> becauſe <hi>preſumption</hi> of reaſon is againſt it; for two reaſons, chiefly, 1. Becauſe in thoſe places, where it was moſt proper to have named the particulars, if it had been intended, none are named (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept one or two of the chief) but all wrapped up in <hi>generals</hi> [Teach <hi>the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,</hi> Mar. 16.15. Teach <hi>all things I have commanded you,</hi> Mat. 28.20. They continved in the <hi>Apoſtles doctrine, and fellowship, and breaking of bread, and prayer,</hi> Act. 2.42. <hi>Hold the form of ſound words, which thou haſt heard of me, &amp;c.</hi> 2 Tim. 1.13. <hi>Preach the word, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="198" facs="tcp:34171:102"/>
2 Tim. 4.2.] 2. Becauſe, in ſome places, they warn the <hi>people</hi> to whom they wrote, to hold faſt all they had taught them, whether <hi>by word, or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</hi> 2 Theſſ. 2.15. And refer the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of ſome things pertaining to the adminiſtration of diſcipline, <hi>until their coming</hi> (of which no more is ſaid after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.) 1 Cor. 11.24. Nay, expreſſely left power with the Church to <hi>ſet in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the things that were wanting,</hi> Tit. 1.5. Nay, S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> who wrote laſt, and (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) in the laſt piece he wrote, <hi>had many things to write, which he reſerved to word of mouth,</hi> 2 Ioh. 12.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It contains not thoſe writings that are <hi>loſt</hi> (named <hi>ſup. c.</hi> 5. <hi>arg.</hi> 9. §. 4, 5.)</p>
               <p n="4">4. To put it beyond all gain-ſaying: it contains not any <hi>expreſs</hi> rule, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving theſe queſtions: <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. What a <hi>Sacrament</hi> is?</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>How many</hi> Sacraments, Chriſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in his Church?</p>
               <p n="3">3. What <hi>water,</hi> and <hi>action,</hi> is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, and ſufficient, to the <hi>matter:</hi> what <hi>perſon,</hi> to the <hi>Miniſter;</hi> and
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:34171:102"/>
what <hi>words,</hi> to the <hi>form</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether baptizing <hi>Infants,</hi> be <hi>pious;</hi> or <hi>neceſſary,</hi> or <hi>available,</hi> to their <hi>ſalvation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. What, and which, is <hi>the Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Who is a <hi>lawful</hi> Paſtor?</p>
               <p n="7">7. What is meant by theſe names, <hi>Presbyter, Bishop, Deacon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Whether <hi>anointing the ſick with oyl</hi> (Iam. 5.14.) be an obſolete Law?</p>
               <p n="9">9. Whether <hi>abſtaining from things ſtrangled, and from blood</hi> (Acts 15.19.) be an obſolete Law?</p>
               <p n="10">10. Whether, that ſpeech, <hi>[This is my body]</hi> were <hi>proper,</hi> or <hi>figurative?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. What <hi>proving</hi> (1 Cor. 11.28.) is neceſſary, and ſufficient to <hi>worthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. VVhat is <hi>the ſin againſt the H. Ghoſt?</hi> and whether it may be <hi>repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> of? and if ſo, whether <hi>remiſsible,</hi> or not, to the <hi>penitent?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. VVhat is <hi>juſtifying</hi> faith?</p>
               <p n="14">14. What is <hi>juſtification?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. In caſe of conteſt, or doubt, who are to be judged, <hi>[the higher powers?]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">
                  <pb n="200" facs="tcp:34171:103"/>16. Whether the Law of the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both,</hi> (and namely, that part of it, as concerns <hi>reſt from ſervile work</hi>) was, by Chriſt <hi>abrogated,</hi> or <hi>transferred</hi> onely to another day? which ſoever it were; whether in <hi>whole,</hi> or in <hi>part</hi> onely? and if the later; in <hi>what</hi> part (at moſt, and leaſt?)</p>
               <p>It were eaſie to name a thouſand more, of the like ſort; and the leaſt of them, <hi>importing mankinde to ſalvation.</hi> But theſe are enough for inſtance.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>Concluſion of the Firſt Treatiſe.</head>
            <p>ANd now (dear Reader) think ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with your ſelf, what reaſon you have, any longer to believe, as now you do, that the Scripture was left for <hi>your Guide and Rule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Is it becauſe you have been ever taught ſo? That is no reaſon, unleſs your Teachers have been <hi>ſent,</hi> Rom. 10.14. which there is not one of them <hi>(Independents, Presbyterians, or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latical)</hi>
               <pb n="201" facs="tcp:34171:103"/>
hath any more authority to teach you, then you to teach them (as will be demonſtrated in the next Treatiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is it, becauſe you have read, or heard ſo much in Scripture it ſelf? you cannot but ſee (unleſs you shut your eyes,) it ſaith no ſuch thing; but the direct con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, in a hundred places.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Is it, becauſe it ſpeaks touching it ſelf very great things? you will not find any thing ſaid of it; but the ſame, or ſomething more excellent is ſaid of the Church, or her teaching. For inſtance.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Is it called <hi>[the VVord, Law, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Oracles, or Goſpel, &amp;c. of God, Chriſt, Salvation? &amp;c.]</hi> Her teaching is more: to wit; 1. The word of God, and all other theſe attributes in <hi>ſimple</hi> ſenſe; whereas <hi>it</hi> is onely the <hi>written</hi> Word, Law, &amp;c. and ſo her doctrine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes the other, as a part of it. For a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>among other grounds of Religion, taught us in our catechiſing, that is one <hi>[There is a Book given by inſpiration of God: this is it, &amp;c.]</hi> And for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon alone <hi>(becauſe she teacheth it)</hi> we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:34171:104"/>
it at firſt. And for that reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone <hi>ſupremely, or finally,</hi>) we believe it ever after; for elſe, she were not <hi>the ground of truth.</hi> 2. The <hi>word of God,</hi> in <hi>proper</hi> ſenſe; becauſe at this preſent <hi>ſpoken</hi> by her, as his <hi>mouth,</hi> or <hi>Angel,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our <hi>ears</hi> (Mal. 2.7. Luk. 1.70.) and ſpoken to me, and you, and <hi>every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> in ſeveral, or in his particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (<hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16.) by an inſtrument in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with ſenſe, and reaſon, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by able to explicate, both her terms, and doctrine; and by applying her inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and direction, to every one, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his capacity, need, ſtate, &amp;c. to ſet, and guide him, in ſuch a <hi>plain high-way, as the way faring men, though fools,</hi> (or children of five years old) <hi>shall not, erre therein,</hi> Iſa. 35.8. And ſo, hers is that <hi>word,</hi> elſewhere alſo promiſed by <hi>Eſay</hi> to the elect under the Goſpel (<hi>The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple shall dwell in Zion, &amp;c. And though the Lord give you the bread of adverſity, &amp;c. yet shall not thy Teachers be removed into a corner any more</hi> (as you ſay the Church may be ſometime <hi>inviſible</hi> to
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:34171:104"/>
the eye of ſenſe;) <hi>but thine eyes shall ſee thy Teachers, and thine ears shall hear</hi> (from their lips) <hi>a word behind thee,</hi> (becauſe, at firſt, by <hi>nature,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, by actual <hi>ſin,</hi> we are all going in a wrong path toward hell, with our backs toward God Almighty, and his holy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation; and ſo he is fain to <hi>follow after us</hi> with his good inſpirations) <hi>ſaying, This is the way, walk in it;</hi> or, that you are to walk in, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 30.19.] A <hi>word</hi> therefore far more uſeful, and benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to us then the other; ſeeing there are multitudes of people, yea, Nations in the world, who cannot <hi>read;</hi> and of them that can, none able to underſtand Scripture, without ſome other inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter then it ſelf. And ſo it is but a <hi>mute</hi> word (properly ſpeaking) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out her.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is it, <hi>a</hi> light? She, is <hi>the</hi> light.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Was it <hi>written for our learning?</hi> She, was given for our <hi>Teacher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Is it <hi>the Book</hi> of truth? She, is <hi>the ground of truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="204" facs="tcp:34171:105"/>5. Is its teaching, of, or with <hi>divine authority?</hi> So is hers, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Did Chriſt ſend <hi>ſome</hi> to <hi>ſearch</hi> it, as a <hi>witneſs</hi> to his <hi>perſon?</hi> He ſent <hi>all</hi> to <hi>hear</hi> her, as the <hi>Teacher</hi> of his <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Is he <hi>bleſſed that reads it;</hi> So is he, that <hi>hears her word,</hi> Lu. 11.28. And no reader of it, but he that is alſo <hi>her hearer,</hi> Apoc. 1, 3.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Is it <hi>able to make ſome Chriſtians wiſe to ſalvation, by faith in Christ?</hi> Her vvord, is <hi>able to ſave all creatures ſouls, by receiving it,</hi> Mar. 16.19. 1 Tim. 4.16. Iam. 1.21.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Is it <hi>profitable for doctrine, &amp;c. that the man of God may be perfect, throughly furnished to every good work?</hi> She is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and ſufficient, for doctrine, &amp;c. that every creature may be perfect, throughly furnished to every thing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to faith, or holineſs.</p>
            <p n="10">10. In a word; is it profitable, in any kinde, to any uſe vvhatſoever? It is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as an <hi>inſtrument,</hi> in the hand of her, or her Scholars.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="205" facs="tcp:34171:105"/>So, whatſoever can be ſaid of it, the ſame, or more excellent, may be ſaid of her, or the word by her preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But then there are abundance of <hi>glorious things ſpoken of her</hi> (Pſal. 87.3.) none whereof can be ſaid of it; namely, all thoſe, named <hi>ſupra, pag.</hi> 13, 14, 15. <hi>[The Houſe of God, the Angel of the Lord, the Light of the VVorld, the Power of God unto Salvation, the Ground of Truth, the Rule of Faith, &amp;c.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVhich I ſay not, of any intent to extoll her above it, <hi>abſolutely:</hi> but to beget in you a due eſteem of her, as in <hi>ſome reſpects</hi> excelling it, as it does her in many other.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Is it, becauſe it vvarnes you of ſome danger poſsible in making <hi>her</hi> your guide? not a ſyllable in it, to any ſuch ſenſe; it doth, of danger in making <hi>it</hi> ſo, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Is it, becauſe it tells you, you need not believe or obey her, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then she teaches out of, or
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:34171:106"/>
conſonantly to it? It tells you no ſuch thing; but the quite contrary, when it calls her <hi>the ground of truth.</hi> For, if she, <hi>the ground of truth,</hi> we are not to judge of the truth of her doctrine by it, but contrarily, of its <hi>true</hi> ſenſe, by her doctrine. It being poſsible for it to have divers ſenſes; but not poſsible for it to have any <hi>true</hi> one, repugnant to her doctrine: as neither poſsible for her (being <hi>the ground of truth</hi>) to miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, ſo as to teach any thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to it.</p>
            <p>Would then any of your Miniſters, undertake to prove to me, by it, that she may, yea hath at ſometime or other ſince the Apoſtles death, yea, at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent does erre in her teaching? I would ask him, if he would prove it, by the <hi>expreſs</hi> words of it, or no. If, nay: would tell him, no <hi>implications,</hi> or <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions,</hi> though never ſo evident to reaſon, were to be of force againſt ſuch <hi>expreſs</hi> promiſes as are made to her; and thoſe not <hi>conditional</hi> only (ſo much as <hi>implicitely</hi>) but <hi>Prophetical,</hi> ſuch as
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:34171:106"/>
that [<hi>Day and night, shall not ceaſe, while the earth remains,</hi> Gen. 8.22.] for ſo ſaith it. [<hi>If you can break my Covenant of the day, and my Covenant of the night, and that there should not be day and night in their ſeaſon: then may alſo my Covenant be broken with David my ſervant, that he should not have a Son to ſit upon his throne</hi> (and you will not, I hope, ſay, that Chriſt's throne was to judge errors) <hi>and with the Levites the Prieſts my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, &amp;c.</hi> Ier. 33.20.] Nay, God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty for our greater aſſurance in this point, expreſſely declares, that no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault or wickedneſs of the Paſtors of the Church, should ever defeaſe his Covenant with her [<hi>If his children for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake my law</hi> (in practice of life) <hi>&amp;c. I will viſit their tranſgreſsions with the rod, &amp;c.] But my loving kindeneſs will I not utterly take from him, nor ſuffer my faithfulneſs to fail, &amp;c.</hi> Pſalme 89.30.]</p>
            <p>Such <hi>expreſſe</hi> promiſes are made to her, for her immunity from all error in doctrine, ſo long as the world en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures:
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:34171:107"/>
Namely, for inſtance, <hi>theſe [My ſpirit which is upon thee, and my words which I have put into thy mouth, shall not depart out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeed, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeeds ſeed (ſaith the Lord) from henceforth, and for ever,</hi> Eſa. 59.21.] Again [<hi>The ſpirit of truth shall abide with you for ever</hi> (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſpake not to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> but the <hi>Church</hi>) Ioh. 16.3. <hi>and guide you into all truth,</hi> Ioh. 14.16.] Now <hi>all</hi> truth, excludes any <hi>one</hi> (leaſt) er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. If he ſay, yea; and should (which is impoſſible) bring a Text in expreſſe words againſt ſome do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, or avowed practice of hers: I would ask him, if thoſe vvords were to be underſtood in their <hi>proper, literal, grammatical,</hi> or (ordinary) <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> ſenſe. If he ſay, yea: afore I admitted him for an <hi>Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> I vvould ask him for his <hi>token,</hi> vvithout vvhich not our Lord Chriſt himſelf vvould deſire any one to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to his Interpretation of it againſt
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:34171:107" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the <hi>Synagogue,</hi> Ioh. 5.31. &amp; 15.24. And if (which is alſo impoſsible) he should shew it (I mean not, a <hi>ſign,</hi> Deut. 13.1. Mat. 24.24. but a true <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle,</hi> Pſal. 136. 4. Ioh. 3.2. &amp; <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.31.) I would anſwer him, that from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward, I would neither believe <hi>her,</hi> nor <hi>it.</hi> Not <hi>her;</hi> becauſe teaching contrary to that, which she told me was the <hi>word of God.</hi> Not <hi>it:</hi> becauſe teaching contrary to her, who it told me was <hi>the ground of truth,</hi> and her preaching, <hi>the word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Weigh then vvell (as I ſaid,) with your ſelf, dear Chriſtian Brother, what reaſon you have to make it your guide, Nay, what an abſurd ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thing it will be in you (after this admonition, and demonſtration to you) to leave <hi>the fountain of living wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for a broken ciſtern; the ground of truth, for a quick-ſand of errour,</hi> I mean, the <hi>Church,</hi> for the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> (not in its due nature, or uſe, God forbid any ſuch thing, in the mouth, or thought, of a Chriſtian,
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:34171:108"/>
but in its abuſe, as <hi>interpreted</hi> to you, <hi>by your ſelf,</hi> a man not onely ſubject to all kinde of error, but falſe principled; or by <hi>Miniſters,</hi> or <hi>Synods,</hi> ſuch as <hi>yours,</hi> as ſubject to error, and falſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipled, as your ſelf): to leave the <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, unto</hi> which our B. Saviour ſaid <hi>[Do you teach the Goſpel to every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,]</hi> and <hi>of</hi> which he ſaid, to you, and me, and every creature [<hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves</hi> (her, or her teaching) <hi>and is baptized, shall be ſaved: that not believes</hi> (her, or her teaching) <hi>shall be damned,</hi> Mar. 16.16.] for a <hi>book,</hi> of which he never ſpake ſyllable unto <hi>Christians,</hi> or in order to <hi>teaching his Law;</hi> nay of which it appears not, that (as <hi>Pastor</hi> of his Church, or according to his <hi>humane</hi> nature] he ever intended, or ſo much as foreſaw the writing of one tittle of it: and of which, he, to whom he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted for ever after, the feeding of his flock (<hi>Ioh.</hi> 21.15.) ſpeaking unto Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians purpoſely, of ſome part of the New Teſtament then written, and by that occaſion, of the Scripture in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:34171:108"/>
as in the hand of the <hi>people,</hi> yea (it's more like) <hi>Divines:</hi> all that he ſaith of it is ſo far from encouraging, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting them unto it, as their guide, or rule; as it is rather to the contrary (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16.): in a word, to leave <hi>that,</hi> of which it is certain, out of Scripture's own mouth, that it is moſt proper, by it ſelf alone; to teach every creature, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing pertaining to the Goſpel; for <hi>that,</hi> which is not proper by it ſelf alone, to teach any creature, any thing.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe God Almighty should do you the favour he did S. <hi>Stephen,</hi> to let you ſee the heavens open, and <hi>Ieſus</hi> ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at his right hand, and teaching ſome perſon ſtanding by; and you should hear him ſay to that party [<hi>Teach this man</hi> (meaning <hi>you) what I have taught you. If he believe, he shall be ſaved; if not, damned</hi>]: and anon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, you should ſee him deliver to him <hi>a book,</hi> ſaying to him, <hi>I give thee this, that thou maiſt teach it to him,</hi> Exod. 24.12.] and afterward ſome one should ſnatch that book from him, and give it
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:34171:109"/>
to you, ſaying] <hi>Do not believe him, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then is here written; he will teach you errors; read this your ſelf, and guide your ſelf, and judge of his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine by it, &amp;c.</hi>] would you not think, it a brainſick act, to follow ſuch coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel? Sure, you would, in reaſon. Such very ſame Counſel, is that of your Miniſters; [<hi>Neglect the Church, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Scripture.</hi> Nay it is more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to you, that Chriſt ſpake thoſe words to her, concerning you, from that record of them [<hi>Preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel to every creature,</hi> Mar. 16.15.] then if you should hear or ſee it now in ſuch a viſion; by how much the word of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is <hi>a more ſure word,</hi> then any ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble viſion can be, <hi>Lu.</hi> 16.31. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.</p>
            <p>Nor therefore may you think, or hope God Alm. will (upon your prayer to him, though never ſo humble, never ſo fervent) by his Spirit, direct or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten you in the right underſtanding of Scripture, ſufficiently to your ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without the Churche's miniſtery. For, he having placed that office in her,
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:34171:109"/>
in the ſame maner as the office of <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing [Teach</hi> all, <hi>baptizing</hi> them <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19.] he will no more give you the one grace, without her miniſtery, then he will the other: and therefore to begg of him to <hi>teach</hi> you <hi>himſelfe,</hi> would be an act of as damnable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, as to begg of him, to <hi>ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſe</hi> you himſelfe. And therefore when S. <hi>Paul</hi> not knowing then, who els he was to goe to, begged it of him; he ſent him to the Church, for that grace. <hi>Act.</hi> 9.6. See the reaſon <hi>ſup. p.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>VVhat needs any more to be ſaid to ſuch a good ſoul as I ſuppoſe you to be. Let it ſuffice, you have hitherto embraced this falſe principle, out of ignorance, and beguiling of hereticall Teachers. After this admonition, you have great cauſe to fear, God will not <hi>wink at your ignorance,</hi> any longer; but expects from you exact obedience to this his <hi>commandement</hi> or <hi>ordinance,</hi> (Mal. 2.4.) of hearing and following the Church as your <hi>Guide</hi> in Religion.</p>
            <p>This doing, you will ſoon finde that
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:34171:110"/>
               <hi>Reſt of ſoul,</hi> the Title of this Book pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed.</p>
            <p>If you neglect it; neither this <hi>Book,</hi> nor the <hi>Church</hi> will have need <hi>to accuſe you</hi> to your Iudge at the dreadful day: <hi>there are others to accuſe you; Moſes, Mathew, Paul, &amp;c. in whom you truſt: for had you believed them</hi> (as you ought) <hi>you would have believed her,</hi> for <hi>they write of her</hi> (and much more plainly then any Prophet did of Chriſt.) <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.45.</p>
            <p>Nor may you flatter your ſelf, with hope upon your faith, baptiſm, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, or holineſs, great and ſenſible particular favours of God to you (as may ſeem to you) in interior lights, conſolations, aſſurances of your being one of his, &amp;c. for unleſs you be an humble child, or ſcholar of his Church, no hope can be built upon them. And two reaſons (among many other might be given) are;</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe, <hi>without</hi> (divine) <hi>faith, it is not poſsible to pleaſe God,</hi> Heb. 11.6. Now your faith cannot be ſuppoſed <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</hi>
               <pb n="215" facs="tcp:34171:110" rendition="simple:additions"/>
becauſe not grounded (finally) on <hi>the Church, the ground of all truth;</hi> and if of <hi>all truth,</hi> of <hi>all faith</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe not to <hi>hear,</hi> or <hi>believe,</hi> the Churche's teaching, is a mortal ſin, (<hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16.) and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, inconſiſtent with <hi>holineſs, without which no man shall ſee God,</hi> Heb. 12.14. See more places, if you pleaſe, to the ſame purpoſe, Mat. 10.14. Lu. 10.16. Acts 2.47. &amp; 13.48. Gal. 5.20. <hi>(Hereſies)</hi> Apoc. 21.24. And therefore you may be certain, the ſpirit that guids you to a neglect of her, and flatters and comforts in you in it, is not God's, but the evil ſpirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3.</p>
            <p>What remains then, but (as you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſee the bliſsful face of God, and avoid eternal torments) you, in the firſt place, ſeriouſly ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or otherwiſe enquire and reſolve your ſelf well, touching this firſt Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; <hi>VVhat Christ left for your Guide?</hi> That done; to enquire, <hi>VVhich is she?</hi> That having found her, you may <hi>ſeek his Law at her mouth:</hi> that if you find,
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:34171:111"/>
               <hi>they</hi> whom you learned your <hi>firſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> from, was not <hi>she;</hi> you may learn them anew of her that is. And then you will have ſome competent rule, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to judge aright of doctrines and teachers, and of the true ſenſe of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; which not only you now <hi>want,</hi> but in ſtead of it uſe a <hi>falſe</hi> one. <hi>God Alm. of his goodneſs, open your eyes, to ſee, in this your day, this truth which belongs ſo much unto your peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Treatiſe (by Gods help) shall follow, as ſoon as I am able.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>read.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>122</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>barely</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>127</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>preſignified</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>141</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>that</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>143</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>think</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>145</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>c.</hi> 1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>147</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>admonish</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>160</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>duely</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>166</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>box</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>171</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>forme</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>179</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>inſinuate.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>140</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>left</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>143</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>ſome</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>150</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>it</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>157</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>that hath</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>160</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>would</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>163</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>for</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>166</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>and that,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>170</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>are</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>183</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>Joh. 9.16.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 3.20. del. [1 King. 17, 24] pag. 32. lin. 26. del. unto theſe words, [if any] &amp;c.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34171:111"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
